<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Berith Anti-Baal, or Zach. Croftons appearance before the prelate-justice of peace, vainly pretending to binde the covenant and covenanters to their good behaviour. By way of rejoynder to, and animadversion on Doctor John Gauden's reply or vindication of his analysis, from the (by him reputed) pitiful cavils and objections; but really proved powerful and convincing exceptions of Mr. Zach. Croftons Analepsis. / By the author of the Analepsis, and (not by the Dr observed) Analepsis anelephthe, to the continuing of St. Peter's bonds, and fastning his fetters against papal and prelatical power.</title>
            <author>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 222 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80839</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6988</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1085_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208062</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867064</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867064</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119354</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80839)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119354)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 161:E1085[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Berith Anti-Baal, or Zach. Croftons appearance before the prelate-justice of peace, vainly pretending to binde the covenant and covenanters to their good behaviour. By way of rejoynder to, and animadversion on Doctor John Gauden's reply or vindication of his analysis, from the (by him reputed) pitiful cavils and objections; but really proved powerful and convincing exceptions of Mr. Zach. Croftons Analepsis. / By the author of the Analepsis, and (not by the Dr observed) Analepsis anelephthe, to the continuing of St. Peter's bonds, and fastning his fetters against papal and prelatical power.</title>
                  <author>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 15, [1], 68 [i.e. 71], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.S. for Ralph Smith at the three Bibles in Cornhil; and for Thomas Parkhurst at the three Crowns over against the great Conduit in Cheapside,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The author of the analepsis = Zachary Crofton; at end of text is a bibliography that is headed: Books written by Mr. Zach. Crofton.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Gauden, John.  Anti Baal-Berith.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-Dp4s, B-Kp4s.</note>
                  <note>Signature K is irregularly numbered.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "march 14th", "1660"; imprint date crossed through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gauden, John, 1605-1662. --  Anti Baal-Berith.</term>
               <term>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672. --  Analepsis.</term>
               <term>Covenanters --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119354:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Berith Anti-Baal, OR, <hi>Zach. Croftons</hi> Appearance Before The Prelate-Juſtice of Peace, Vainly pretending to binde the <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Covenanters</hi> to their good Behaviour.</p>
            <p>By way of Rejoynder to, and Animadverſion on Doctor <hi>John Gauden's</hi> Reply or Vindication of his <hi>Analyſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> from the (by him reputed) <hi>pitiful Cavils and Objections;</hi> but really proved <hi>Powerful and Convincing Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of Mr. <hi>Zach. Croftons</hi> ANALEPSIS.</p>
            <p>By the Author of the <hi>Analepſis,</hi> and (not by the Dr ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved) <hi>Analepſis Anelephthe,</hi> to the continuing of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Bonds,</hi> and <hi>faſtning his Fetters</hi> againſt Papal and Prelatical Power.</p>
            <q>Claudicat ingenium, delirat linguaque menſque.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 16.7.</hi>
               </bibl> The legs of the lame are not equal, ſo is a parable in the mouth of fools.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>V. 4.</hi>
               </bibl> Anſwer not a fool according to his folly, leſt thou alſo be like unto him.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>V. 5.</hi>
               </bibl> Anſwer a fool according to his folly, leſt he be wiſe in his own conceit.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Ralph Smith</hi> at the three Bibles in <hi>Cornhil;</hi> and for <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt</hi> at the three Crowns over againſt the great Conduit in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119354:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119354:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous and Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Octor <hi>John Gauden</hi> finding no regular, rational, or religious way to releaſe St <hi>Peter,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore him to his <hi>Epiſcopal chair,</hi> thinks it beſt to leave him in his bonds, or <hi>holy Fetters,</hi> and as a <hi>Juſtice of Peace</hi> proceeds againſt his keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and to binde him and his adherents to their <hi>good behaviour;</hi> (we ſay of the Devil, that change demonſtrates the non-prevalency of his temptations.) In order whereunto, after nigh forty weeks from the appearance of my <hi>Analepſis</hi> in the world, againſt the <hi>Analyſis,</hi> his pregnant Genius was delivered of a Reply thereunto; without the leaſt regard to any other thing by me written, to enforce and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh the Sacred and Indiſſolvable Bond of the moſt <hi>Solemn League and Covenant</hi> that ever paſt on Chriſtian Church or People, (which
<pb facs="tcp:119354:3"/> God hath ſeverely, and before our eyes aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on the Violaters, in that part, which was (for its <hi>matter</hi> mainly Civil; and will undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly appear no leſs jealous for that part which is Religious) and yet it is ſwoln into ſuch a bulk, and dreſſed in ſuch a garb, as that it is not for every man to <hi>buy;</hi> nor any civil, ſober, wiſe man to <hi>read,</hi> much leſs to <hi>rejoyn unto;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to do no more, but fill their mouths, who are minded to make a clamour, and think ſpeaking (though to no purpoſe) to be a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient anſwer to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Crafton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I having animadverted this <hi>Anti-Baal-Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rith,</hi> finde a neceſſity to Apologize for the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry act of my animadverſion, and fear nothing more then to be <hi>bound to my good behaviour,</hi> for miſ-behaving my ſelf ſo much, as to <hi>anſwer a fool according to his folly;</hi> wherein I may ſeem <hi>like unto him;</hi> did not the very next words give me ſome encouragement, directing me to <hi>anſwer a fool according to his folly, leſt he be wiſe in his own conceit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, what I ever expected and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed to many, is now effected by the Doctor, <hi>viz.</hi> That he would never be ſo hardy as to encounter me ſingle, or aſſault the reaſon, and ſtrength of argument objected in my <hi>Analepſis</hi> to his <hi>Analyſis;</hi> but his honour engaged in an evil cauſe, provoked him to ſay ſomthing, to keep up a repute among the ſimple; he would take up the <hi>Anonymous Anatomiſt,</hi> (whoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alect I cannot approve) which unhappily had
<pb facs="tcp:119354:3"/> ſtarted into the world, ſome <hi>two hours</hi> before my <hi>Analepſis;</hi> and ſcoulding at that and its Author, would ſhuffle in my Book and N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me, (which yet as one that could not read, or fought blindfold, not ſeeing his adverſary, he hath miſtaken through his Book, writing M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Grafton,</hi> as if I ſhould anſwer D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Gaudie</hi>) and ſeem to ſay ſomthing in it, though nothing to the purpoſe: How exactly this is done, I leave the Reader to obſerve.</p>
            <p>It is indeed to be acknowledged, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he enter the Stage with a Title that beſpeaks him ſome ſtrange <hi>Hercules fureus,</hi> or <hi>Ajax Maſtigophorus,</hi> and his raging, rambling, raving diſcourſe towards his late <hi>Anatomiſt,</hi> doth too much verifie the ſame; yet he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth himſelf with as much civility, reſpect, and modeſty towards M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cr.</hi> as can be looked for from ſuch a ſarcaſtical Pen; that I wonder he could make it conſiſt with ſo much rage; I could not but expect his prudence to have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected him, no way to conjoyn two ſuch dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent tracts in the ſame furious expoſtulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, leſt his wrath had run beyond its propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed end; or his Reader ſhould apply the whole diſcourſe beyond the Authors intention, as indeed they commonly do; for he knoweth, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulgus non diſtinguit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am not inſenſible, the <hi>barking Curre</hi> in the Embleme (moſt ſcurrilouſly) prefixed to his Book without colour of reaſon, is by many applyed, and underſtood to be intended to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent
<pb facs="tcp:119354:4"/> Mr <hi>Cr.</hi> which if ſo, I leave the Reader to judge its aptneſs; the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> taking no notice of any Book written by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cr.</hi> ſave the firſt, which hath found much acceptance for the <hi>ſobriety of its Stile;</hi> ſo far from <hi>barking,</hi> as that its modeſty is acknowledged by the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> himſelf; and all rational men muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the <hi>Moon,</hi> for its mutation, ſpots, dark, cloudy, uncertain light, and cold chilling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, to be much a more apt Embleme of inconſtant, uncertain, ambiguous, obſcure, and luke-warm Biſhop <hi>Gauden;</hi> whoſe Epiſcopal Influence is like the <hi>Moon,</hi> more likely to kill, then animate Religion; and his glorious light of his rude Rhetorical ſwadoes, to lead men into a <hi>fools Paradiſe;</hi> for children to play by, rather then direct mens duties, or reſolve their doubts, or guide them into paths of ſafety: But I have more charity, then to think that this (though by the vulgar applyed) was by the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> intended, as ſuch an Embleme of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cr.</hi> 's book; becauſe though he is reſtleſly unquiet in <hi>barking out</hi> the <hi>barking property</hi> of his <hi>Anatomiſt,</hi> yet he doth not ſo much as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude thereunto in all his debates, with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cr.</hi> otherwiſe, I could have anſwered a fool ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his folly; and to this piece of ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rility (unbeſeeming a man of common mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, much more a Chriſtian, a Miniſter, nay one who as a Biſhop pretends to more piety, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and gravity) have oppoſed, and prefixed to this Tract, the figure of a <hi>Wheel,</hi> with a
<pb facs="tcp:119354:4"/> 
               <hi>Tongue</hi> on it, <hi>whirling</hi> about without order or ſtay, to the only raiſing of a <hi>cloudy duſt,</hi> with this Motto; <hi>Who is this that darkneth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge by words without wiſdom?</hi> Or this, <hi>A fool is full of words, a man cannot tell what ſhall be, and what ſhall be, who can tell?</hi> My nature is as <hi>bad,</hi> and fancy as <hi>wilde</hi> as the D<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> can be; but I bleſs God for the reſtraints of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> which bridles I hope I ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver break or caſt off.</p>
            <p>The Dr doth in the cloſe of his elaborate Tract, complain that he had <hi>tired himſelf,</hi> and <hi>his Reader;</hi> nor is it without cauſe, he might have ſaid it in the middle, nay beginning of his journey; and remembred that wiſe obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.15.</note> 
               <hi>The labour of the fooliſh wearieth every he one of them</hi> (guide, or guided,) <hi>becauſe he knoweth not how to go into the City;</hi> which one thus illuſtrates, <hi>Neſciunt viam in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lava.</note> 
               <hi>qui a recto tramite aberrant, &amp; in loca a via addu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur:</hi> The D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> having in his <hi>Analyſis</hi> looſed from the Haven of Reaſon, true Religion, and the fear of God, <hi>runs adrift</hi> where-ever the wind of his own words can hurry him, and leads his Reader into a wilderneſs, where he hears no ſound but the ſhrieks of Satyrs, bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and howling of beaſts, at beſt, raging and rayling of men, or wilde and improper diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, that direct to no certain end; The D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> having unhappily returned <hi>railing</hi> unto what ſeemed rational in his <hi>Anatomiſt,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to what is noted as uſual with heretiques,
<pb facs="tcp:119354:5"/> 
               <hi>Haeretici cum perver ſitatis ſuae non poſſunt red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere rationem, in maledicta convertuntur;</hi> and endeavoured by words and ſhuffling gloſſes, to darken the plainneſs, and clearneſs of the truth urged by the <hi>Analeptiſt;</hi> of whom we muſt ſay, as Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> of the Jeſuite <hi>Harding,</hi> in his confutation of him; <hi>Who ſo takes upon him to maintain untruth, muſt needs be forced to diſcourſe about with long vagaries, to lead his Reader from the purpoſe, and to feed him with words for want of matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Defence of the Apologie of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Preface to the Reader.</note>The truth is, the Reverend D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> hath expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed great affection to <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> in his zeal for it, fully matching <hi>Harding</hi>'s apprehenſion of the Papacy, and Aſſertion, That <hi>the Popes chair,</hi> (or Engliſh Prelacy) <hi>is the very knot of Chriſtian <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity;</hi> and ſo branding with <hi>Schiſm</hi> all that ſay the contrary: Nor falls he much ſhort of Pope <hi>Boniface,</hi> having according to the meaſure of his Prelatical power, <hi>Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized</hi> all Presbyters, as he did <hi>Aurelius,</hi> and <hi>all the Biſhops of the Councel of Africa,</hi> not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empting <hi>Auguſtine</hi> himſelf; <hi>Aurelius, cum col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legis ſuis inſtigante diabolo, ſuperbire caepit contra Romanam Eccleſiam:</hi> Nor is he much defective in their <hi>ſubtilty,</hi> whilſt <hi>viſum eſt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, ut ſcribatur ad Epiſcopum Romanum, ut conſideret res noſtras, &amp; det conſilium;</hi> will more eaſily ſignifie the Popes power, and be rendred, It hath <hi>ſeemed good that we write un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Biſhop of Rome, that he viſit us, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine our matter by his ſentence;</hi> then <hi>I
<pb facs="tcp:119354:5"/> ſwear with reality, ſincerity, and conſtancy, to endeavour the extirpation of Prelacy;</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>the Government by Arch-biſhops, Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. can be rendred, <hi>I do ſwear to my power to eſtabliſh and advance Prelacy, the Government by Arch-biſhops, Biſhops;</hi> only I will conſent to reform <hi>the exceſſive and defective abuſes thereof:</hi> but the cauſe cannot be good, that muſt be ſalved by ſuch ſtrained, yea contrary interpretations; eſpecially in matters of an Oath: with how great ability the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged his <hi>great affection</hi> againſt his <hi>little An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſt,</hi> let wiſe men judge; the weight of the cauſe, and ſome mens doting on the <hi>bare ſay ſo of a Biſhop,</hi> more then the cogency of the Reply hath produced this following Tract, to thy coſt and trouble, as well as my pains, and expence of more precious time; into which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I paſs thee, I muſt minde thee of theſe two things, pretermitted in the following Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Gauden</hi> ſeems to gather much ſtrength from the <hi>ſilence, or ſeeming complian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of ſome to his abſurd, contradictory inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations of the Covenant: Becauſe I will do him, or them on whom he reflects no wrong, read his own words, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I finde no men of learning and ingenuity, but are aſhamed to appear in ſuch a cauſe; Sober Presbyterians do very loyally, piouſly, prudently own, yea and profeſs to the King's Majeſty, a quieſcence under Epiſcopal Government, as no
<pb facs="tcp:119354:6"/> way inconſiſtent with the Covenant: Epiſt. to the Reader. This mitigated, and juſt ſenſe of the Covenant, ſome that were and are great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in our Iſrael, and aſſertors of the Covenant, are now content to owne, abating the rigour which ſomtime poſſeſſed ſome Covenanters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Epiſcopacy, in that ſenſe, wherein this, and moſt other Churches ever owned, and uſed Epiſcopal Government, and Authority among and above Presbyters: yea many of them begin to caſt a favourable eye on Epiſcopal dignity, no leſs then on Church lands, fearing nothing ſo much as not to have a ſhare of them; much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulating, as the King's happy reſtauration, ſo the hopes of recovering the priſtine Honour and Government, with the Revenue and Rights of the Church, in point of Epiſcopacy; not in the fallacy of a Presbyterian parity, but of a preſidential, conſtant eminency of Biſhops in authority over Presbyters,</hi> pag. 72, 73.</p>
            <p>That any have by their <hi>ſilence, or ſeeming compliance</hi> given the leaſt occaſion to this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation, is matter of grief and ſcandal to good men: who yet have obſerved the ſubtile at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, &amp; ſtrenuous endeavors of <hi>Prelats</hi> and their abettors, to tempt &amp; debauch the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of ſome <hi>Zealous Covenanters;</hi> and cannot but bleſs God that any have obtained power to withſtand ſuch temptations, &amp; decline ſuch glorious baits; w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſhould they, and many have admitted, I was, &amp; am reſolved through divine grace, to ſing no ſong under the ſufferings that
<pb facs="tcp:119354:6"/> are threatned againſt me, ſave only this, <hi>All this is come upon me, yet have I not dealt falſly in thy Covenant:</hi> but charity bids me conclude, that the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> reckons without his hoſt, and that the boaſting clamour is a baſe calumny: He profeſſeth the reaſon of the ſo late appearance of this elaborate wilderneſs, was, an expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what others would ſay in the cauſe; and yet he runs ſo faſt as not to heed the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters Plea,</hi> which would have told him, ſome men no way ſhort, in <hi>learning and ingenuity,</hi> of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Gauden,</hi> did appear in ſuch a cauſe: more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, many may and do appear in it, that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear not to write for it; <hi>Pen and Pulpit are different capacities;</hi> multitudes of books need not; let the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> judiciouſly (not judicially) confute one of his Antagoniſts; I dare aſſure him more will take up the quarrel, and defend it: I could (if he call on me) ſhew the letters of many faithful Covenanters out of many Counties in <hi>England,</hi> joyntly and ſingly own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame cauſe of the Covenant with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cr.</hi> and are neither afraid nor aſhamed to own it: I know not what any <hi>particular Presbyter</hi> might profeſs to his Majeſty; I hope ſuch on whom the Dr reflecteth, will in due ſeaſon vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate themſelves; I have cauſe to think, the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> reports this as faithfully as he did M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter's diſcourſe about the Liturgie:</hi> I well know, that thoſe who had immediate conference with his Majeſty, profeſſed in private debates with their Brethren, another judgement of the
<pb facs="tcp:119354:7"/> 
               <hi>Covenant and Epiſcopacy,</hi> then what is now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of them: I am ſure at a general meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Covenant Presbyters in and about the City of <hi>London,</hi> the cauſe of the Covenant was debated, generally owned in its oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Epiſcopacy, and other things returned amongſt us; and by joynt conſent it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, to petition his Majeſty, and the Houſes of Parliament; the heads of which petition, being agreed on, was committed to certain brethren to prepare and draw up; and was this.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty.</head>
                        <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
                        <p>YOur Petitioners humbly bleſſing God for your Majeſties <hi>happy Reſtauration</hi> to the Throne of your Royal Father, being alſo ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of your Majeſties gracious acceptance of our humble <hi>Addreſs</hi> made to your Majeſty; as likewiſe of the great piety and zeal in your Majeſties late Proclamations for ſuppreſſing of prophaneneſs, and countenancing &amp; prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of godly Miniſters, are thereby encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to lay this humble preſentation and Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with our ſelves, at your Majeſties feet.</p>
                        <p>That whereas your Petitioners by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the <hi>two Houſes of Parliament,</hi> were brought under the ſacred obligation of a <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Oath,</hi> wherein, with our hands lifted up to the moſt high God, we did Covenant to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour a <hi>Reformation in Doctrine, Worſhip, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline and Government,</hi> and <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity of
<pb facs="tcp:119354:7"/> the Churches of God in the three Kingdoms;</hi> and in purſuance thereof, the ſaid Honourable Houſes, with the advice of the Aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, did ordain <hi>a Form of Church government, a confeſſion of Faith, a Directory for Worſhip, and the greater and leſſer Catechiſms,</hi> which we and our Congregations have through God's goodneſs for many years together, and ſtill do comfortably enjoy and practiſe.</p>
                        <p>We are therefore humbly bold, in the name and for the ſake of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt (for the prevention of diviſions, offences, &amp; ſnares to the conſciences of many thouſands within the three Kingdoms, both Miniſters and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who are pious and peaceable) with all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility to beſeech your Majeſty,</p>
                        <p>That the things of God and Religion, which have been ſo <hi>ſolemnly Covenanted</hi> for, may be owned and confirmed by your Royal Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; which notwithstanding, we do ſincerely profeſs our readineſs to accommodate with our Godly and Orthodox brethren diſſenting from us, ſo far as may conſiſt with our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and <hi>Covenant.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>This Petition however by ſome State ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems and Court complement, and over pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent cowardize of ſome, who contrary to the due order of all Aſſemblies, would never let it be reported, it was prevented from being preſented to his Majeſty; yet I know it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed and aſſented unto by many learned and ingenious men, who are yet ready in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble,
<pb facs="tcp:119354:8"/> lawful, and ſubmiſſive wayes, to own the ſame cauſe of the Covenant, in which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cr.</hi> hath appeared; and is here inſerted as a check to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Gauden</hi>'s fancied complyance of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted Presbyters.</p>
            <p n="2">2. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Gauden</hi> doth often ſuggeſt the <hi>extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of Epiſcopacy to be inconſiſtent with loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to the King,</hi> and therefore affectionately wiſheth, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cr. may maintain and expreſs his loyalty, to which he findeth him a pretender.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this, give me leave, as Dr <hi>Gauden</hi> hath done before me, to play the fool, and boaſt; and I can ſay without vanity, <hi>in expreſſions of loyalty on conſcience of the Covenant,</hi> I think I have not come behinde the higheſt Prelate which pretendeth moſt to it; though it be not ſo viſible at Court as they make theirs to be, yet all <hi>England</hi> knows M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Croftons conteſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the cruel and barbarous murther of his late Majeſty,</hi> &amp; how plainly he did in the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit at <hi>Nantwitch</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> to the face of the chief Republican agents reprove it, as an actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al &amp; poſitive breach of Covenant, in a ſolemn Aſſembly, and Thankſ-giving held on <hi>Jan.</hi> 25. 1649. what rage and reproach he that day un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwent, and what hazard he thereby ran in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, the yet Miniſter of that Town, and other Gentlemen loyal to his Majeſty, can declare.</p>
            <p>In conſcience of this Covenant, and loyalty to his Majeſty, he withſtood and declined the <hi>Engagement,</hi> and that againſt the open and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent threats of promoters of it; perſwaſions
<pb facs="tcp:119354:8"/> of complying brethren, one of whom preſſed me to it with this great argument, <hi>The fight at Dunbar is l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt; the Kings Intereſt quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown; theſe times afford few Martyrs;</hi> yet M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cr.</hi> reſolved to make one, and conflicted with a violent and vexatious people, to a <hi>Sequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Eſtate,</hi> on no other reaſon, but not ſubſcribing to the Engagement. It is too long to report my conſtant <hi>praying for, and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up</hi> the King's Intereſt, to the conviction of the enemy; my conſtant refuſal to obſerve any of their <hi>Faſts, or ſolemn Thanks-givings,</hi> my preaching at <hi>Weſtcheſter</hi> at the beginning of S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>George Booths attempt,</hi> and my troubleſome attendance on the Councel of State, and Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, with the threats and rage I then under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went: <hi>The Articles of Treaſon againſt Oliver,</hi> charged againſt me, for which I underwent much trouble; the <hi>friendly and angry conflicts</hi> I have often had with <hi>John Bradſhaw,</hi> whom I feared not to minde of his <hi>wages of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs:</hi> my conſtant aſſerting of his Majeſties Intereſt, and ſubjects duty of <hi>returning to the Lord, and to David their King,</hi> which I preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in St <hi>Peters Cornhil,</hi> when the hearers trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and all the City expected M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Crofton's bonds</hi> at the leaſt: All which were expreſſions of <hi>loyalty to the King, and conſcience of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi> But I will only preſent thee with a Letter which I ſent unto a Member of the <hi>Rump Parliament,</hi> on the very day of their tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant return from <hi>Portſmouth;</hi> it was then
<pb facs="tcp:119354:9"/> publiſhed (though without my name) I ſhall now affix it to this Epiſtle, and leave thee to judge, how far <hi>conſcience of the Covenant</hi> hath acted M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Croftons loyalty to the King,</hi> and tell thee he retaineth the <hi>ſame duty for his Majeſty,</hi> and in ſenſe of it doth (and cannot but do it) now conteſt for, and aſſert the <hi>ſolemn League and Covenant,</hi> in that religious part which muſt be promoted with utmoſt zeal, by all who wiſh well to King and Kingdom; though the devil and his inſtruments do endeavour to damp, deaden, and divert the diſcharge of duty, by the clamorous charge of <hi>Treaſon, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, Sedition, and Diſloyalty</hi> of that Act, which is in its <hi>Nature, Principle, and Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Agents,</hi> moſt truly <hi>loyal and faithful</hi> to the King, and Kingdoms Intereſt, Honour, and Happineſs; which none hath, or can more ſincerely ſeek and promote, then the <hi>zealous, conſcientious, Covenanters,</hi> amongſt whom to be reckoned, (coſt what it will) is the Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Reſolution of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>March</hi> 14. 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Zach. Crofton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119354:9"/>
            <head>A Letter written by a Miniſter in <hi>London,</hi> in Anſwer to one ſent from a Member of the Long PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOurs of the <hi>18<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> inſtant I received; whereby I diſcern your ſenſe of the ſad hand of God upon theſe Nations, <hi>in the many ſad Revolutions</hi> to which they have been ſubject. And now you ſeem ſtudious of the way of its recovery, in which I rejoyce. Though, Sir, your Enquiry doth a little amaze me; not ſo much for the matter, as that you ſhould preſs me to it in this juncture of time. You well know, Sir, I have not declined to let you know my thoughts of all the late tranſactions of thoſe who called themſelves, <hi>The Long Parliament.</hi> Did I not much preſume on your Faithfulneſs never to uſe it to my damage (however God deal with you) I might burn my pen and paper for fear of a Charge of Treaſon and High Court of Juſtice. But I will not fear to write at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to whom I have often ſpoken freely, and yet met with the fidelity of a Friend.</p>
            <p>Sir, your Enquiry is ſerious and ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and calls for a better reſolution then I can render.</p>
            <p>It is this.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is to be deſired by them that wiſh well to</hi> England?</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119354:10"/>
            <p>I underſtand your Enquiry as grounded on the preſent ſad ſtate of the Nations affairs; and ſo my reſolution is, as of a Miniſter of God, that of Iſraels <hi>Repentance</hi> promiſed in <hi>Hoſea 3.5. Afterwards ſhall Iſrael return, and ſeek unto the Lord their God, and unto Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid their King,</hi> is the <hi>unum neceſſarium,</hi> one only thing to be deſired for <hi>England</hi> as her ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Remedy againſt all her maladies by the hand of God inflicted on her.</p>
            <p>On ſerious obſervation of <hi>England,</hi> I cannot but judge her the parallel of the ten Tribes <hi>in ſin and ſorrow,</hi> and wiſh ſhe may precede them in a ſerious and ſeaſonable Repentance. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, Sir, the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> his Prophetical Marriage of an Harlot, and leaving her a long time with this charge,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>To abide for him, and not to play the Harlot, or be for any other,</hi> is a lively Emblem of <hi>Englands</hi> ſtate and duty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>England,</hi> Sir, as <hi>Iſrael,</hi> have gone <hi>in the way of Jeroboam,</hi> and have ſinfully, againſt all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, Civil and Religious bonds, caſt off and ſhut out their <hi>Lawful Governours and Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Government</hi> left them by their Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Englands</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe.</note> and under which ſhe long flouriſhed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Enriching of her ſelf, Envy of her Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, Nations, and Encouragement of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches: And that after many Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, Proteſtations, Vows, Oaths, and the SOLEMN LEAG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E AND COVENANT for the defence and preſervation of the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Perſon and Poſterity, the Priviledges of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119354:10"/> Parliament, and the Liberties of the Subject, and that Sworn in a day of Extremity, when they ſeem'd to be in danger, and men were Jeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous (the ſubverſion ſince effected) was intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Nay, and after a vaſt expence of Blood and Treaſure in the defence of them; and when un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an Obligation inviolable and never to be diſpenſed withall, wherein we have ſworn to God, <hi>Not to ſuffer our ſelves by any commina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, perſwaſions or terrors whatſoever, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or indirectly to turn aſide to the right hand or to the left, or to make defection from this Cauſe.</hi> Yet have our Nation, to the Scandal of Religion, Reproach of the Nation, and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy of God, and Provocation of his Juſtice, with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> made defection from their Lawful &amp; Natural Prince, yea and altered their unalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Government at the Luſts of Men ſubvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very Foundations. Only, Sir, I muſt be free to let you know, that in two things <hi>Englands</hi> defection hath been more vile then that of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raels, in that it was made by a violent, baſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, extrajudicial, barbarous <hi>Regicide,</hi> with an hypocritical pretence of Juſtice. Secondly, In that Members of the Parliament have been to themſelves an <hi>Herod Aſcalonite</hi> to violently <hi>break up their own Sanhedrin;</hi> and <hi>Guido Faux, to blow up King, Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled,</hi> to the everlaſting blemiſh of the Proteſtant Religion, and in the room thereof have been ſubjected to uſurpation and ſelf-created Governours, with whom moſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119354:11"/> of the Nation have concurred, and to them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented. And for the ſupport of this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped Magiſtracy, Calves have been ſet up at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethell,</hi> all falſhood in Religion Tolerated, the Miniſtry laid common, <hi>who will becomes a Prieſt unto the Lord.</hi> So that, Sir, Schiſm and Sedition, Rebellion unto Regicide, Perfidie and Perjury is become <hi>Englands</hi> Guilt, and impiety written in ſuch legible and indelible Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters, that all men muſt ſay, She is become an Harlot, and ſee repentance abſolutely neceſſary to prevent her ruine.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>England.</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers.</note> Sir, give me leave to tell you, <hi>Englands</hi> ſin (like <hi>Iſraels</hi>) hath been point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out by her <hi>Sorrows;</hi> for ſhe having ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſhaken off her Rightful Governour and Government, hath been proſtituted to the Luſts and Ambition of particular men, and proudly trampled on by Military inſolency, in ſo much that our very Bell-men can reproach us as we lie in our Beds. Shall I, Sir, make bold to inſert a Bell-mans ſound which I heard with my own ears. It was this,
<q>
                  <l>Whilſt you ſecurely Sleep, I Ring my Bell,</l>
                  <l>Which lately hath rung out your Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms Knell.</l>
                  <l>Your Souldiers, now, your Sovereigns are become,</l>
                  <l>Your Laws and Liberties command by ſound of Drum.</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119354:11"/>
                  <l>Nor is it ſtrange, for they read no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</l>
                  <l>Regard no Bonds, but proſper by Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion.</l>
                  <l>By Pride and Perjury, theſe Saints moſt rude.</l>
                  <l>Have Cut off the King, and Parliament ſubdu'd.</l>
                  <l>Your eyes have ſeen't, vile Slaves, yet in this ſeaſon,</l>
                  <l>You are Rid like Aſſes, and not Rul'd by Reaſon.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Oh, Sir, how many ſad and ſhameful revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have paſſed upon us, and yet we are full far from Settlement? <hi>Authority,</hi> like a Tennis-Ball, hath been caſt up and down for him to catch that catch can, and hath been toſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a republican pack, and ſingle Perſon, whilſt both are plain and palpable <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers; for indeed in nature, and by Gods juſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Revolution is the conſtant Attendant on Uſurpation;</hi> the Globe of Magiſtracy muſt roul up and down, whilſt off its Pin, and from its Center, it only reſteth in right Subjects; and now we are covered with confuſion, and left without <hi>King,</hi> any lawful, nay, without <hi>Prince,</hi> any unlawful Governours, without any eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment in Church or State, Civil and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous order, and this was the puniſhment of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, now is of <hi>Englands</hi> adultery: The eſtate of her widdowhood, the time of divine deſertion;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119354:12"/> for <hi>Civil Order</hi> is Gods preſence in the World, and <hi>Religious Order</hi> his preſence in the Church. The very Heathen conclude from the confuſions in the world, the <hi>Gods have forſaken the Earth;</hi> ſo that, Sir, he muſt have no Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion who ſeeth not in <hi>Englands</hi> caſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude and cry out, <hi>Righteous art thou, O Lord, and juſt are all thy Judgements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, Sir, I have ſhewed <hi>Englands</hi> diſeaſe and diſtemper; it remains that I direct the cure and remedy, and that I ſay is, <hi>Repentance,</hi> true and hearty,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Englands</hi> Cure and Remedy.</note> General and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> Let the Miniſters of God lift up their voice, and cry, <hi>Repent, England, repent, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent;</hi> let all that wiſh well to <hi>England,</hi> pray that God would pour out a <hi>Spirit of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> that from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſheba</hi> all <hi>Iſrael</hi> may return and ſeek unto the Lord, and to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> their King.</p>
            <p>Sir, Repentance is the <hi>end and errand of all Afflictions,</hi> Iſai. <hi>27.11.</hi> Men cry out of doing the Work of God, nor doe I deny it in all our ſtrange revolutions; only I deſire it may be noted, it is Gods <hi>ſtrange work,</hi> ſpeaking his diſpleaſure, and ſummoning his Peoples Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: A relenting heart, a returning ſpirit ſhall no ſooner be effected, but theſe ſharp rods will be rejected. God will walk contrary to a ſtubborn People, untill their uncircumciſed heart be humbled,<note place="margin">Levit. 26.</note> but no longer, for, then his end is effected.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119354:12"/>
            <p>Repentance doth <hi>engage divine return;</hi> for he hath promiſed, that when ever he <hi>ſpeaks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Nation, to pluck it up, or root it out, if that Nation repent, he will repent,</hi> Jer. <hi>18.8.</hi> He ever meets relenting <hi>Ephraim</hi> with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for inflicted judgements; his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod is to give <hi>Repentance and Remiſſion of ſins:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 31.18.</note> The greateſt good intended for Iſrael is contracted into the promiſe of repentance; the Sun doth not more certainly follow the morning Star, then the return of Gods preſence doth attend repentance:</p>
            <p>Nay, Sir, in this caſe repentance is an <hi>actuall re-enjoyment of bleſſing,</hi> not only a quality diſpoſing to it, but an act putting into the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of it; as your Armies late repentance for their back-ſliding, put your Members actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally into the Houſe, to rule and govern, and their counter repentance put you out again, ſo the repentance of your pretended Parliament, and the People of <hi>England</hi> puts <hi>lawfull Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours</hi> into their proper places, and fixeth <hi>Authority</hi> in its right Center, which ſin un hingeth and expelleth. You may obſerve, <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> Repentance was an actual and ardent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>to bring home the King.</hi> Repentance breaks open the Bar of Sedition and Rebellion which ſhutteth out lawful authority; will but God give Repentance, the Reſtitution of <hi>Englands</hi> Government will be very feaſable and ſpeedy. For this Repentance conſiſts in two parts.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119354:13"/>
               <hi>1. To abide for rightfull Governours,</hi> however expelled, and at preſent excluded; and <hi>not to be for any other Magiſtrate,</hi> by any act of Allegiance, or acknowledgement of Loyalty; ſtrike not hands with, conſent not to any <hi>ſelf-created Governours,</hi> by Pride, Perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and Rebellion, ſlipping into a Chair of State; play not the wanton with any <hi>ſelf-advancing Abſalom,</hi> be not ſeduced by every <hi>ſeditious Sheba:</hi> If proud men have power and profaneneſs to catch a Scepter, and ſtamp Authority upon themſelves, let men maintain their Chaſtity, deny their Allegiance, court them not as rightfull Governours: Mens <hi>giddy unconſtancy is the blood that nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Rebellion:</hi> reſolved chaſtity is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke of adulterous attempts; if with <hi>Mephi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſheth,</hi> men cannot follow their exil'd <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> let them abide in their widdowhood, and retain their Loyalty untill he return. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Nature and Scripture a people may better be <hi>without any Prince, then ſtrike hands with a Uſurper,</hi> for in that is <hi>ſorrow,</hi> but in this is <hi>ſin:</hi> I ſhould, Sir, wiſh that fond and blind affection may not engage any to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit lewdneſs with any the Members of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> late Husbands body; let not any the Members of our Collective Body (now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, and bemangled,) cheat us with the claim of Allegiance by pretence of Relation, and cry of a Long Parliament; but rather let theſe Members be diſperſed throughout the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119354:13"/> Tribes of Iſrael as evidences of that <hi>unheard of violence, and unparallell'd cruelty</hi> which hath been acted on <hi>our Eſpouſed Lord. Englands</hi> Subſcription of ſinful Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ſhamefull Addreſſes to unlawful Powers, hath been the breach of her chaſtity; let us abide for lawful Government, when we can doe no more, evidence our integrity, and aſſert our duty and relation, when we cannot enjoy our right.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Act of Repentance to be done,<note place="margin">Second part of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</note> is to <hi>return unto the Lord, and to David their King. Return to God, is the formall act of true Repentance;</hi> Sin and Repentance have the ſame object, though ſome ſin is more immediately againſt God, yet all ſin is a tranſgreſſion of his Law: The ſame God that ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt have none other Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my face,</hi> ſaid alſo, <hi>Thou ſhalt honour thy Father and thy Mother;</hi> and, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adultery:</hi> Iſraels Rejection of <hi>Samuel,</hi> was a Rejection of the Lord; as light as men make of Civil Right and Order, it <hi>is Gods direction</hi> in the ſecond Table of his Law: The complaint of the Penitent for any ſin, is <hi>unto God, Againſt thee, thee only have I ſinned;</hi> ſeeking <hi>to the Lord,</hi> will ſpur a ſeeking <hi>unto David their King;</hi> ſence of God offended, <hi>engageth a return from all ſin,</hi> not only from laſt, but firſt acts of violence done unto Authority; not only the interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119354:14"/> made on you in <hi>1653.</hi> but thoſe chiefly made by you in <hi>1648.</hi> and that with fulneſs of Reſolution to back-ſlide no more; a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to God <hi>will awe the conſcience, and obviate all the difficulties and diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Repentance;</hi> danger ſinfully crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by rebellion ſhall not deter repentance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a return to God, <hi>ready to forgive;</hi> let me ſay to <hi>England</hi> as God to <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>If thou wilt return, return unto the Lord,</hi> who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned your duty; whoſe Law hath been vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by your impiety; <hi>unto the Lord,</hi> to whom you ſware in the day of your diſtreſſe; who is a God of jealouſie, and will avenge the quarrel of the Covenant; ſad is the Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance which is but <hi>an exchange of ſin,</hi> or of ſins object; a bewailing of one rebellious act, but maintaining and proceeding in a ſeries of Rebellion, violence, and ſedition. Sir, whatever Souldiers doe, Saints muſt not thus return.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſraels</hi> return to God muſt be with <hi>a return to David their King;</hi> by <hi>David</hi> is generally underſtood the Meſſiah the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, nor doe I deny it, only Sir, I wiſh it may be noted, the Meſſiah is called <hi>David</hi> for Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Succeſſion ſake, becauſe the ſame ſeed and rightful Succeſſour of <hi>David,</hi> as the <hi>Pharaohs</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Caeſars</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> he is <hi>their King,</hi> not only as the Meſſiah, but by a lineall diſcent from, and lawful ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119354:14"/> to the Crown of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> ſo that a return to <hi>David</hi> their King is mentioned with an alluſion unto their Apoſtacy from, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> which muſt be repented in their return; for they muſt embrace the Lord Jeſus, not only as the Meſſiah, but alſo <hi>as their naturall Prince</hi> and <hi>lawfull Sovereign;</hi> and therefore <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> cryeth out, <hi>Aliter vere &amp; ex animo De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quaerere non potuit, quin ſe etiam ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jiceret Legitimo imperio cui aſtrictus erat; they could no way ſeek the Lord in truth, but by becoming Subject to their lawfull Soveraign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Englands</hi> repentance muſt be according to this, they muſt ſeek the Lord, through Chriſt, by <hi>ſubjection to their lawfull Government and Governours,</hi> from which they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted; the formality of Repentance from Rebellion is a return to Loyalty. Sir, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution is an eſſentiall act of Repentance;</hi> the only reſtitution made for repented of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, is a re-eſtabliſhment of Authority, and a return to Loyalty, becoming ſubject for conſcience ſake: Iſrael repenting the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion into which they run after ſelf-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing <hi>Abſalom;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.</note> they fell to ſtrife among themſelves about <hi>fetching home their King:</hi> Nay, <hi>Shimei</hi>'s Character of repentance is this, <hi>Thy ſervant doth know that I have ſinned, therefore behold I am come down the firſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119354:15"/> of all the Houſe of Joſeph to meet my Lord the King;</hi> if God will doe <hi>England</hi> good, he will give them hearts to give God the things that are Gods, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars,</hi> which have been too long held back with violence.</p>
            <p>I wiſh, Sir, that none may pretend an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtency between this act of Repentance, and <hi>the Good Old Cauſe of God and his People,</hi> for whoever ſhall ſo doe, muſt ſell themſelves unto poſitive blaſphemy, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall profaneneſſe; pretending that to be the <hi>Cauſe of God</hi> which is expreſly repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to his revealed Will, and reſolving Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion is the honour of Religion, and only work of Saints; and wilfully ſhut their eyes, that they may cozen their Conſciences: For, Sir, is not the <hi>Kings Preſervation,</hi> Honour and Happineſſe, <hi>the Priviledges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> the <hi>Liberty of the Subject,</hi> and defence of the Government by King, Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, written in ſuch Legible Characters in the Parliaments, Cities, and Armies <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Remonſtrances, and Proteſtation; in all our Vows, Oaths, and Covenants,</hi> as the Good Old Cauſe for which ſo much bloud and treaſure was expended, that none but the wilfull impenitent can chuſe but run and read it; I ſhall for more full conviction refer you to Mr. <hi>Prynns Good Old Cauſe truly ſtated,</hi> which I know you have ſeen,</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119354:15"/>
            <p>Neither, Sir, would I have <hi>the hazard of any mans life or eſtate,</hi> threatned by this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, be any bar unto it; for, Sir, this hazard is ſelf-created, and ſinfully procured; which, ſhould it be inflicted, were but the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per effect of Juſtice, better to be undergone here then hereafter unto eternity; happy may be the ſtroke of Juſtice which may ſave a Soul from Hell; the ſinful eſcapes of humane Juſtice will one day be found exceeding ſad: Running away from the rod of correction, is an <hi>heightning</hi> rebellion, and <hi>note of a Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate;</hi> and whither will ſuch flie from Gods all-ſeeing eye? Or will it boot any to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with God for impunity? Oh no, it will not.</p>
            <p>But Sir, ſuch men may be <hi>worſe feared then hurt;</hi> Repentance is the <hi>ſpunge of Guilt</hi> in the ſight of men, as well as in the ſight of God: God who hath the hearts of Kings in his hand, and turns them as the rivers of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, relents towards a repenting <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and maketh <hi>David</hi> relent towards a rebellious <hi>Abſalon;</hi> Royall Clemency never ſhines bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then in returns from violent exile; <hi>Shall any be put to death this day in Iſrael? for doe I not know that I am this day King in Iſrael?</hi> Is <hi>Davids</hi> anſwer to the ſon of <hi>Zer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viah</hi> provoking againſt <hi>Shimei,</hi> who had full well deſerved it? Any indifferent Politician can give aſſurance of indempnity for generall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119354:16"/> delinquency, eſpecially, when true repentance is the ſpring that doth enforce it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Sir, let none ſtand up againſt this act of Repentance, and cry, <hi>It is dangerous to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> a Free Parliament will call home the King, and he is rude and prophane, and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth among Papiſts, and will bring Popery into the Land with him. To ſuch I ſay in ſhort, How came they into Gods Chair to become ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous of Event? is uncertain fear of an iſſue any ground of bar to duty? Where is our Faith ſhould carry us on in duty againſt all dread? Needs God our Sin to preſerve the Sanctitie of his holy Name? Will not this prove a ſad ſupport unto Religion? But is not this fear groundleſſe? Is not the King a Proteſtant born and brought up? bound in the ſame Solemn League and Covenant with our ſelves? Hath not our ſin ſubjected him to the ſaddeſt temptation to turn Papiſt that ever poor Prince underwent? Doth not Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> tell us plainly and upon good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, That his exile is the great propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Catholick Cauſe, and high cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie to <hi>Rome?</hi> Sir, theſe obſtructions are all frivolous, and ſo will appear, if ever God pour on the Nation a Spirit of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>Worthy Sir, I have with the plainneſſe of a Miniſter, and freedome of a Friend, given my thoughts on your Enquirie, and that not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119354:16"/> 
               <hi>Raſhly,</hi> but as having conſulted the Oracles of God. And I cannot but beg that you perſiſt no longer in your way of ſin: Oh that God would give you and your fellow-Members hearts <hi>to give him Glory,</hi> and after your ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, <hi>to take to your ſelves ſhame</hi> for your ſinfull ſubverſion of an Eſtabliſhed Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that with pretence of Law, calling your ſelves a <hi>Parliament,</hi> when your own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences tell you, you are no ſuch thing. Sir, <hi>England</hi> is inclining to repent, if your Houſe prove not a <hi>Sheba</hi> to ſound again <hi>the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet of Rebellion.</hi> However, my advice is, Let the Miniſters of God cry out, <hi>Repent, England, Repent, Repent;</hi> and let all the people of God pray, That <hi>England may return and ſeek unto the Lord, and to David their King:</hi> Then ſhall we be eſtabliſhed enjoying our <hi>Princes as at the firſt, and our Rulers as at the beginning.</hi> I have no more, ſave with the Prophet Ezekiel, <hi>They, whether they will hear, or whether they will forbear, for they are a Rebellious Houſe, yet ſhall know there hath been a Prophet among them,</hi> Ezek. <hi>2.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119354:17"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119354:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BERITH ANTI-BAAL.</hi> OR, <hi>Zachary Croftons</hi> appearance, <hi>BEFORE The Prelate Justice of Peace.</hi> PRETENDING To bind the Covenant and all Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters to their good behaviours.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen Dr. <hi>John Gauden</hi> firſt appeared in the World with his <hi>Analyſis</hi> to the ſinful <hi>looſing of St. Peters bonds,</hi> under a plauſible pretence of counſelling a Chriſtian friend, in a matter of great concernment, and reſolving the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, in the point of the <hi>ſolemn League</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> and its oppoſition to <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> conſidering the good obſervation of <hi>Gregory</hi> the great,<note place="margin">Lib. Mor. 22. cap. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> made of the courſe of Heretiques, <hi>ſub ſpecie eonſulendi agunt negotium ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducendi,</hi> that they pretending to play the Caſuiſtes, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve conſcience, and to adviſe in matters of Religion,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119354:18"/> drive on the deſign of ſeducing ſouls, and ſubverting the truth, and Salvation. Thought it no leſs then his duty to conſider the ſame very ſeriouſly, and to try it by the rule of Scripture and right reaſon; and finding in that book (what ever was the Authors intention) too great a tendency to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ervate all ſacred bonds, Invalidate, yea annihilate the <hi>ſolemn League and Covenant,</hi> and thereby ſupplant the peace, and happineſs of our reſtored <hi>King and Kingdom,</hi> he apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it his duty, as a Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, and his Church, (though the meaneſt and leaſt to be regarded) to intimate to the worſhipful perſon concerned, and (by him) thoſe to whom that book ſhould come,<note place="margin">Sir <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.B.</hi>
               </note> the diſſatisfaction, and deluſive danger, he found in that book; and therefore he did on <hi>July</hi> 8. 1660. ſend after it an <hi>Analepſis,</hi> or St. <hi>Peters bonds abide,</hi> detecting the impiety thereof, in ſubverting the Covenant, by a pretended interpretation thereof, nay enervating the ſacred obligation and power of all Oaths, by the principles therein ſuggeſted; and its excee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing <hi>imbecil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> as to the ſatisfaction of conſcience, unto which it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed. This done, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> compoſed himſelf in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lence, and ſubmiſſion, waiting for the reply of the reverend Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Analyſis,</hi> but received none, onely more then one, though one (a ſtranger to Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi>) more eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially told him, Dr. <hi>Gauden thanked Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>for his civility, and yeilded to his reaſon;</hi> yet at length (how inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged I know not) he appeared to repeat the ſame things, and almoſt words, in an Epiſtle to an Anonymous book, called, <hi>Doubts and ſcruples,</hi> but repaired to the <hi>Oxford rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> as his fort againſt the Covenant, in which, (with other books of the ſame nature,) Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> though (good, (once for all) to conſider what was ſaid, or could be ſaid againſt the Covenant, and to anſwer them by ſeveral <hi>Antitheſes,</hi> which he did in his <hi>Analepſis Anelepthe,</hi> or the <hi>faſtning of St.</hi> Peters <hi>fetters,</hi> and ſo thought his work on that ſubject to have been done, being eſtabliſhed, and enforced by the learned, pious, and judicious <hi>Covenanters plea againſt abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> both which muſt receive a Logical, and clear theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119354:18"/> confutation, <hi>ad grecas calendas,</hi> and therefore did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply himſelf to his ordinary Miniſtry; and his little ſpare time to ſuch other things, as might be profitable to Gods Church, and prevent the backſliding of our covenanted re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, but</p>
            <p>Heark, What is this, is cryed? Dr. <hi>Gaudens Reply to Mr.</hi> Croftons <hi>anſwer,</hi> I muſt ſure ſee that: <hi>Hem, quid video,</hi> what is this, I ſee? a book with a fair bulck, nigh forty ſheets of Paper, to vindicate Dr. <hi>Gaudens Analyſis,</hi> (why not <hi>Looſing of St.</hi> Peters <hi>bonds,</hi> is he beaten out of that Title, and aſhamed to uſe or own it any longer) contained in three<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in five ſheets of Paper, ten at the moſt, <hi>(if you take in the Anatomy of his nonſence and blaſphemy)</hi> long looked for comes at laſt; it ſure, will anſwer expectation? No, it intends no ſuch thing; after its ten moneths travel, it will profeſs no more, then to vindicate his <hi>Analyſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Parturiunt montes, naſcetur tandem ridiculus mus.</q>
            <q>
               <l>As Mountains great, travels a man of worth,</l>
               <l>At length a Mouſe (ſwoln like a Toad,) creeps forth.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Howſoever, Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> nay the Covenant is concerned in it, it muſt be taken up and conſidered, what Title is that it bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth? <hi>Anti Baal-Berith;</hi> Sure the Printer hath abuſed him by a tranſmutation, the Reverend Doctor cannot be ſo mad, as to account the Solemn League and Covenant, a <hi>Baal-Berith;</hi> a Covenant for <hi>Baal,</hi> which he himſelf ſwar, and onely labours to interpret, and in the poſitive part of it doth bind unto a <hi>reformation of Religion according to the word of God,</hi> which kills, <hi>and example of the reformed Churches,</hi> who have caſt out <hi>Baal,</hi> and his Communion Table, ſet Altarwiſe, Altar (I ſhould ſay) not according to humane inventions, Papal impoſitions, or prelatical preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which advance, and maintain <hi>Baal,</hi> (if not againſt) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitour with the Lord, and in the negative part of it, bindes to the extirpation of <hi>Popery, Prelacy, ſuperſtition, hereſie, ſchiſme, and prophaneſs,</hi> under ſome of which, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119354:19"/> 
               <hi>Baal</hi> muſt be couched at the leaſt; if not viſible in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> viſibly ſupported by <hi>Prelacy,</hi> muſt not the man be out of his wits, who ſhall call this Covenant a <hi>Baal-Berith?</hi> If the Doctor did direct this title, and in this book do purſue it, it is pitty but <hi>D. B.</hi> or ſome <hi>Anatomiſt</hi> ſhould diſcover his <hi>nonſence and blaſphemy</hi> now made as plain, as the Noſe on his Face; but I will have more charity.</p>
            <p>The utmoſt this book pretends to, is to <hi>bind the Covenant and Covenanters to their good behaviours,</hi> (not abandon, or aboliſh it, as a <hi>Baal-Berith</hi>) and to this, they are ready to ſubmit, when ſummoned by a juſt authority, for they are, and ever have been <hi>(qua tales)</hi> as <hi>Covenanters</hi> of a good behaviour, neither bound nor preſuming to endeavour beyond their <hi>places and callings,</hi> though their <hi>reality, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, and ſincerity therein,</hi> by Preaching, or Writing (the works of Miniſterial calling) doth not a little vex and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe ſome Idle Lordly Biſhops, and make them complain of the Covenanters misbehaviour in diſturbing them on their Velvet couches, or not comming before their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips with ſuch cap and knee, and <hi>may it like your Grace,</hi> as they look for: but</p>
            <p>Who is this that will bind the <hi>Covenant and Covenanters to their good behaviour?</hi> It is done by the Author of the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſis:</hi> who, Dr. <hi>Gauden?</hi> I confeſs he is made a Biſhop, but is he yet made a Juſtice of peace? or do theſe <hi>coincidere</hi> by his conſecration? I have heard indeed he was entertained in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Dioceſs, and City of <hi>Exeter,</hi> like one of his Majeſties <hi>Lieutenants at War,</hi> and paſſed through rancks and files of men of War, not Citizens in their Civil Garb; well, be it ſo; but methinks, our Biſhops ſhould not yet cry out, <hi>Ecce duo gladia,</hi> but if it be his Majeſties pleaſure, I ſhall ſubmit, and Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> is ready to appear, and to give ſuch Security as his <hi>Worſhip</hi> ſhall demand; For he muſt tell him this is not the firſt time, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been (on the ſcore of the Covenant) called upon to be bound to his good beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; I remember on the tryal of a Miniſter (at the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Seſſions held at <hi>Namptwich,</hi> in the County of <hi>Cheſter,)
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119354:19"/> Indicted</hi> for oppoſing the <hi>Engagement,</hi> to be <hi>true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Common-wealth, without King or Houſe of Lords,</hi> Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> (at the deſire of his brethren who thought it their duty to ſtand by their ſuffering brother) did urge in his behalf, that the <hi>Engagement</hi> did interfere with the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant;</hi> unto whom the Atturney for the Common-wealth made no other reply, ſave, <hi>Suckling will you ſpeak, Suckling what will you ſpeak?</hi> to which Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> (then young as well as little) made this ſhort return, have you not read <hi>that out of the mouthes of babes and ſucklings, God will ordain ſtrength to confound his foes;</hi> on which, the enraged Atturney prayed the good behaviour, which fiery Juſtice <hi>Gerrard</hi> enforced againſt Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> who deſired the judgment of the Bench before he would find ſurety; and they declared, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> had onely as a Miniſter urged the Covenant, and a place of Script<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re againſt the Atturney, which was proper to him as a Miniſter, and could be no miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>behaviour; and ſo he was diſcharged. I hope I ſhall have no leſs Juſtice, from a Convocation of <hi>Prelate Juſtices,</hi> then thoſe who were civil, and under an Uſurper.</p>
            <p>But let us paſs from the Title, and look into the body of the book, and here I muſt remem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, <hi>Robora parentum, refe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri,</hi> the growth of the Children ſheweth the ſtrength of the Parent. And the bulk of this book, muſt beſpeak no little ſtrength in the Author, but wherein lies his ſtrength? In the <hi>paſſions</hi> of his ſoul, in the <hi>Pride</hi> of his ſpirit, <hi>Prophaneſs</hi> of heart, and natural <hi>fluencie</hi> of words, but in neither Rhetorick, nor reaſon, humane or divine, natural or The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ological.</p>
            <p>Whoſoevever in his right mind readeth but this book, will find it ſuch a <hi>rudis indigeſtaque moles,</hi> a me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r chaos of confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and intricate labyrinth of words (not in themſelves but) rudely ſcattered, and flung out, without any due de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance or coherence, as in the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Alchoran, and worſe then in the <hi>Rabbins</hi> Talmud; the whole method of it (though a pretended reply to a methodical exception,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119354:20"/> which might have directed him to order) is ſo indigeſted and full of confuſion and diſorder; nothing defined or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed; <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> (the ſubject of the debate) no way deſcribed, or explained; ſo that every common capacity reading it, runs into a wilderneſs of words, by want of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and connexion, leaving his underſtanding at a loſs, as to <hi>ſcope or drift,</hi> gazing as on unknown pictures, had not a marginal note (related moſt an end to words more then matter) like the bungling workman in the Painters art, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten this is a Lion, this a Bear, and that a Wolf.</p>
            <p>Leſt the reverend Author ſhould think I do him wrong, I muſt make bold to give a taſt thereof, leaving his abuſive <hi>Anatomiſt</hi> to bundle up his <hi>Nonſence and blaſpemy,</hi> which what ever it did in his <hi>Analyſis,</hi> I am ſure lyeth ſcattered in every page of this book; <hi>If the Juſtices aſſigning a baſtard born,</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 150.</note> 
               <hi>to be kept, becauſe, quod fieri non debuit factum valet,</hi> which men of any braines refer to <hi>moral, not natural entities;</hi> or Mr. <hi>Crofton ſaith Epiſcopacy muſt not be reſtored though it be good, if not proved to be neceſſary,</hi> but <hi>he that vows to take away my horſe, muſt not ſay, he will not change his vow; until it appear my horſe is not onely good but neceſſary for me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> may be taken for Nonſence, which certainly for its profoundneſs of reaſon would make an underſtanding horſe to break his bridle. Or, if it may be any way accounted <hi>blaſphemy,</hi> to denominate that a <hi>Baal-berith,</hi> which is, <hi>a Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> for the <hi>glory of God, advancement of the Kingdom of our Lord Jeſus, the honour and happineſs of the King and his poſterity,</hi> made on ſence of the <hi>plots, conſpiracies, attempts and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Enemies of God, and true Religion,</hi> and expreſly binding to a <hi>reformation of Religion, according to Gods word, and example of the beſt reformed Churches; open,</hi> vowed Enemies to Baal; and to an <hi>extirpation, of whatſoever is contrary to found Doctrine, and the power of godlineſs,</hi> all which, admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it extended to one particular thing which ought not to have been removed, (yet tended at the moſt but to the <hi>bene eſſe</hi> of Religion) in which reſpect, it at moſt could be rendred but imprudent, or unjuſt in that point, and not a <hi>Baal-Berith.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119354:20"/>
            <p>Or if the reviling, with moſt opprobrious terms, <hi>as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious, ſeditious, rebellious, perfidious pack</hi> (which I leave the Anatomiſt to gather up and preſent unto the world) the moſt lawful, rightly called and conſtituted Aſſembly of the Lords and Commons, Princes and principal Rulers of the people, by his late and preſent Majeſty often, and openly owned as a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and inveſted, during their being, with the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt Authority of the Nation; and thereby <hi>deſpiſing Dominions, and ſpeaking evil of Dignities,</hi> may be accounted blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my:</p>
            <p>Or if falſe and impudent accuſations of the <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Covenanters</hi> to have <hi>plotted, contrived, occaſioned, and effected the Kings barbarous murder,</hi> from which all ſober men (in their right wits) muſt acquit it, and them, as violated and oppreſſed, trodden down and ruined, to make way for that accurſed act by men (on whom God hath avenged the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel of the Covenant) may be accounted blaſphemy:</p>
            <p>Or if railing and deſpightful ſpeaking, in the height of rage and fury, in the moſt baſe, Billingſgate, obſcene, ſcurril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, opprobrious and diſgraceful terms that anger could di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate, or envy could deviſe, which breaketh through his own profeſſed <hi>integrity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 7.</note> 
               <hi>and thoſe holy charms by which he pretends to reſtrain his revenge,</hi> &amp; flyeth out beyond the <hi>gravity</hi> of a <hi>Miniſter, authority</hi> of a <hi>Biſhop, ſobriety</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> or <hi>modeſty</hi> (much more honeſty) of a <hi>man,</hi> unto the height of effeminate ſcolding and uncivil ribaldry, with which he hath ſtuffed more then twenty ſheets of his Book, may be accounted blaſphemy.</p>
            <p>I muſt indeed confeſs in the heat of his anger he hath treated me with as much civility as could be expected from a Biſhop to a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> judged <hi>rigid,</hi> and conſiſt with ſo much railing at another with the ſame breath; often profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>to know and keep a difference</hi> between me and his other An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſt, acknowledging Mr. <hi>Croftons civility, reaſon, honeſty, ingenuity,</hi> and the like; yet not without ſome drops of his <hi>ſarcaſtical pen;</hi> as <hi>little Mr.</hi> Crofton, <hi>ſo great a Dictator, Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian pertneſs and petulancy, hold, odious, and fallacious,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119354:21"/> and the like, which are very little ſpots in his feaſts of love, and plain errata, and ſlips of paſſion in compariſon of that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and ſerious mood of ſcolding with the other, whom he hath coupled with Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> in his vindication, yet is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to guide Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> what to look for, and obſerve that it is with Biſhop <hi>Gauden,</hi> as <hi>Rivet</hi> noteth of Biſhop <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tague, Non poteſt vir ille, ſine convitiis, quenquam a quo diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit vel in leviſſimis nominare; This man can ſcarce name with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reproach any man from whom he differs in the leaſt thing and ſleighteſt matter;</hi> But it may be this is the expreſſion of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latical ſtate and pomp; but the Lord deliver me from ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring <hi>railing for railing:</hi> I do not delight to rake in this pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle; And therefore with one note more I paſs him over, and that is,</p>
            <p>His <hi>levity and pride</hi> in proclaiming his own worth and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, as if far from his neighbors, or that they would not, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed could not commend him, ſoaring aloft in his ambitious ſelf-apprehenſions into an equality with the cheif Fathers of the Church, begining his Epiſtle to the Reader with <hi>An having had the honor and happineſs, after the example of the great</hi> Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius, <hi>the induſtrious St.</hi> Auſtin, <hi>our own Arch-Biſhop</hi> Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gift, <hi>Mr.</hi> Rich. Hooker, <hi>to encounter the enemies of this Church, King and Kingdoms with ſucceſs:</hi> When alaſs he never yet came nigh the laſt and leaſt of them in a conflict; If little Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> could have anſwered God and his conſcience for ſo vain an expence of time, he had hampered your <hi>Hieraſpiſtes,</hi> &amp; ſtrained your <hi>ſighs and tears,</hi> no leſs then he hath done your <hi>Analyſis,</hi> and yet could not for ſhame have <hi>crowed</hi> of any va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant act, in vanquiſhing the ſhadow of a Diſputant; and in pag 8. He muſt make the world to take notice of his high <hi>honor, in attendance on better perſons and better imployments,</hi> getting the Biſhoprick of <hi>Exeter</hi> unto himſelf, which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered his Reply for ſo long a time, Sir, We will excuſe you if your friends do not with blame to you ſay <hi>You are come too ſoon:</hi> Yet they, as we, muſt beleive, if your ſay ſo be enough, that your affirmations are beyond any <hi>rational or conſcientious Reply,</hi> pag. 151. becauſe indeed they never reach reaſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119354:21"/> pinch conſcience: But your Lordſhip is pleaſed to tell us, that you have <hi>condeſcended to conſider our exceptions,</hi> Sir I thought it had been a Caſuiſts duty to conſider all objections, and a Miniſters to endeavour all ſatisfaction, but I muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member you were on your Epiſcopal Sea, when little Mr. <hi>Croftons Analepſis</hi> was laid at your feet, to be taken up, or kicked away; but enough of this, it is more fit for your <hi>Anonymous Anatomiſt,</hi> then for a man of modeſty, who ſhall keep himſelf diſtinct, as you have differenced him, and ſhall therefore deſire to weigh, what your Worſhip hath againſt his <hi>Analepſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> is in this elaborate tract dealt with a part, but the little man is ſo light, that he is toſſed up and down the Wilderneſs, that ſeeking, he cannot without tyring, find himſelf, in theſe indeed <hi>tedious, and intangled</hi> (as your ſelf calls them) <hi>animad verſions;</hi> he did according to his little reaſon, unravel your laſt ſnarled skain, and reſolved it into a regular method, which methinks Sir might have kept your fluency within ſome bounds, and have curbed your wild excurſions; he ſhewed you the <hi>Rocks</hi> againſt which your reſolution daſhed, and digeſted your diſcourſe into argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation as well as he could, and dare ſay, you appeared better to the Reader in Mr. <hi>Croftons Analepſis,</hi> then in your own <hi>Analyſis,</hi> why kept you not to this? I promiſe you if this be <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> I ſhall not love it, till it keep to rule, be <hi>plain, pure, perſpicuous</hi> and <hi>methodical</hi> (without which it is but natural fluency of words, and volubility of tongue) and not fordid, <hi>tedious, obſcure, flat, wild, rabid, raging, empty and barely wordy, without ſentence, confuſed and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>methodical,</hi> as is yours, unto the very heigth of exorbitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: take notice of it, if I be (as God forbid I ſhould be) Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and an appeal be made to the Archp. againſt your writings, I will adjudge you, inſtead of your Marginal <hi>digitations</hi> to your Reader, to place over every Paragraph, the <hi>figure</hi> by which you frame your ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and <hi>mood</hi> by which you form your argument; for now you have vindicated your <hi>Analyſis,</hi> I muſt ſend to you to pray an <hi>Analyſis</hi> of your vindication; my reaſon it is too
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119354:22"/> little to make it; I muſt be fain to gueſs your meaning by your mumping.</p>
            <p>The Doctors great deſign in his <hi>Analyſis,</hi> profeſſed to <hi>reconcile the Covenant and Epiſcopacy,</hi> but how unhappily he loſt it, and miſcarried in it, was modeſtly declared by little Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> (whom I apprehend this great Doctor ſcorns to admit as a <hi>Dictator,</hi> ſo as to take notice of, or amend his errors;) on which his conſcience cannot but tell him, all his Caſuiſtical endeavou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s have been, and muſt needs be ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrackt, without all poſſibility of ſatisfaction to conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, how ever it may catch the fancy of his prelatical pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes, who are pleaſed with a ſound againſt the Covenant, and conſider not the certainty of it, and are ready <hi>jurare in verba Epiſcopi,</hi> be they never ſo groundleſs; <hi>the ſay ſo of</hi> a grave Prelate, is a ſufficient reaſon of their faith.</p>
            <p>The inadvertency of his expreſſions both for their fury, and falſhood, againſt <hi>Presbytery,</hi> the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and all thoſe whoſe conſciences cannot correſpond with his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded <hi>Prelacy,</hi> as well as againſt his particular Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, is ſo far from being abated, that it is more vigorouſly acted, and made ſo accumulative, that his book runs over with foams of rage, filling (as I ſaid before) more the twenty ſheets of paper with ſuch furious and fooliſh objurgatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, ridiculous reflexions, and ſcurrilous chiding, that he that enters this book, and paſſeth but the Threſhold, muſt needs ſay, <hi>this man is in no temper to reſolve a doubt, or ſatisfie a conſcience,</hi> he is in the heat of a ſcolding paſſion, and ſo lay it aſide, as unfit to be read: really had angry Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> been his Chaplain, he muſt have become an <hi>index expurgatorius</hi> to his book, and preſumed to dictate more ſobriety and meekneſs, before it had ſeen the world; for that the <hi>wrath of man, cannot work the righteouſneſs of God,</hi> men cannot but judge this book an hot conteſt, and violent plea for his <hi>prelatical honour and revenues,</hi> in which beginning to be warm, he groweth as hot as a Toaſt, and fearing to loſe them, falls into a fretting chafe againſt the Covenant, and Covenanters, which promiſe them little ſecurity, and therefore runs his rage againſt <hi>ſacriledge,</hi> and <hi>buying Biſhops Lands,</hi> (from
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119354:22"/> which it is well known Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> is free, nor indeed doth he charge him) rather then for his <hi>Epiſcopal office in Chriſts Church,</hi> the conſcience of which would have made him ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, <hi>a Biſhop muſt be no brawler, but patient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this angry mood, we cannot expect him to be very clear o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> certain in the <hi>ratio formalis objecti,</hi> the object of the obligation ſcrupled, and diſputed; the want of which hath been noted to him by the different acceptation of the term Biſhop, and Epiſcopacy; the which Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> did not onely explain, but propoſe unto him a doubleſence thereof, affirming the one to be <hi>Scriptural, primitive, and Catholique,</hi> the other to be <hi>Papal, Novel and tyrannical,</hi> and on the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of his words, prayed a poſitive determination which of them he owned, and would <hi>reconcile to the Covenant;</hi> but his greatneſs would not condeſcend to make a choice of either, according to Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> propoſal, but that we may know he ſcornfully takes notice that Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> had obſerved his uncertain propoſal of the object, in ambiguous words, he affords us a parentheſis, in the threſhold of his book, which runs thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The way of Epiſcopal order and authority (that is leſt Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>ſhould again miſtake my meaning, the preſidency of one chief Prebyter or Biſhop among many, and above all leſſer Biſhops or Presbyters in his Dioceſs, according to the ancient cuſtome, and laws E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cleſiaſtical and civil)</hi> I thank you Sir, for this grave caſt of your eye, did Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> miſtake you without cauſe; or clamour it to your damage? or did he not take the paines to pick up your words, and put them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and tell you that ſome of them ſpeld one thing, and ſome another diſtinct from that, and modeſtly deſire which you would own, and ſtand by.</p>
            <p>Sir, the ſpirit and men of your Dioceſs, are ſaid to be near a kin to the Welchmen, and they muſt have leave to tell their tale twice, and for ought I ſee you muſt tell yours thrice, for I am as likely to miſtake you as I was before, ſuch an <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclitus</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> you are in your Aenigmatical extrication of your own made intricacies, and rhetorical labyrinths: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I preſume to determine your meaning, I muſt enquire
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119354:23"/> what you mean by <hi>Preſidency?</hi> whether you intend not to extend it, beyond the <hi>gradus</hi> of a Moderator, unto the power and efficacy of a Preſident of a Colledge at the leaſt? what you mean by <hi>above all leſs and ſubordinate Biſhops?</hi> whether <hi>Officio &amp; honore Cathedrae,</hi> or <hi>Ordinis authoritate,</hi> which your <hi>Epiſcopal order &amp; authority doth ſuggeſt;</hi> though the title <hi>Biſhop</hi> given by you to Presbyters doth ſeem to mitigate it. What do you mean by <hi>antient cuſtom?</hi> only that which hath long uſe, and can plead preſcription, and which may have run long, and yet leave us a ſpace, in which we may ſee and ſay, this was not <hi>from the beginning?</hi> You do indeed profeſs to the firſt ſix hundred years, but I dare ſay the laſt three hundred of them are thoſe you would chiefly cleave to. And what do you mean by <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Laws?</hi> where are theſe recorded? and by what authority were they compoſed? When you have given me a plain, clear and diſtinct reſolution to theſe, if I miſtake your meaning let me be blamed, till then blame me not. I love not the <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> which contrary to its end, propoſeth objects with that obſcurity, that they cannot be with certainty determined, and that under a profeſſion to clear and convince the conſcience. Yet Sir, to do you right,</p>
            <p>When I obſerve you page 114. eat your own words, and offer (as if your Brethren Prelates had brought you now into <hi>Caſſanders</hi> School, and charged you to make an Apology for your over-friendly propoſal to Presbyterians) which you purſue by telling us, <hi>All Presbyterians do hug Biſhop</hi> Uſhers <hi>Reduction of Epiſcopacy</hi> (which in your <hi>Analyſis</hi> you aſſured us did reduce Epiſcopacy to an <hi>efficacious conjunction with Presbytery;</hi> and on which Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> concluded that ſence, which you ſay he ſeemed in a ſober mood to own, <hi>An E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy conſistent with the Covenant,</hi> pag. 191.) but now ſay, <hi>will reduce Biſhops to primitive poverty</hi> (the eſtate which attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and enforced their piety) and therefore tell us, <hi>That humble learned and pious Lord Primate, propounded that reduction not in order to binde the hands of, or limit Biſhops in England and Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and; but as a condeſcention and expedient at preſent to diſarm and binde the hands of Presbyters and people.</hi> Sir, who told you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119354:23"/> that this was the politick ſtratagem of that pious Biſhop? did not Biſhop <hi>Wren?</hi> Sure I am, he came not down from heaven to authorize you in your Book to call him <hi>hypocrite,</hi> and to tell all the world, he had in Machiavillian policy, by his grave and judicious authority affirmed, <q>That it was appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent out of the Word of God, and practice of the primitive times, that Presbyters had an intrinſecal power unto all Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction and order in the Church, and by after <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation were thruſt out; and therefore he propoſed an expedient, pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentially to reſtore them to their juſt authority; but never inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it to be believed as a truth, or ever be put in practice as a duty, but to only be jingled in the ears of crying children.</q> Are you not aſhamed, to caſt ſuch a blot, on the precious name of him, who I know was by ſome <hi>Caſſandrian Prelates</hi> judged <hi>Puritan,</hi> whilſt alive! Do you meaſure every man by your own temporizing principles? and think they are onely in a good mood, till they have opportunity to be bad and baſe? do not you bluſh to offer this reduction in one book, and call it in, in another? But whilſt I ſee you thus play faſt and looſe, I know how to truſt to you, and am holpen the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to underſtand what you mean by <hi>Epiſcopal Government;</hi> and when I obſerve the <hi>ſoveraign power by which Mr.</hi> Crofton (you ſay, and that truly) <hi>is not willing to be ruled,</hi> pag. 216. <hi>Coordination with Kings as cheif Governours by Divine appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> pag. 205. <hi>Honourable fatherhood and government,</hi> p. 203. <hi>The legal conſtitution by the Laws of England,</hi> to which our Epiſcopacy doth pretend; <hi>the continued practice and exerciſe of it in this Nation; the ſuperiority above, and authority apart and diſtinct from Presbyters, whoſe advice may be good and uſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful, but not neceſſary, as that which would make every Presbyter ſuffragan Biſhop, and the Biſhop without his Presbyters a meer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pher.</hi> All which I finde predicated (up and down your tedious diſcourſe) of that Epiſcopacy, you would advance, and which you ſay is not ſo obſcure as Mr. <hi>Crofton would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend,</hi> but in expreſs terms you tell us, is, That Church <hi>poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, honour, order and government, which our Biſhops had, and now have,</hi> and that we muſt not by an <hi>equivocal and levelling fence, confound Biſhops and Presbyters, by a ſilly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gomac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie, or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119354:24"/> cavil of names, diſtinguiſhed by a real, rational difference of place, honor, office, authority and uſe, in the Church of Chriſt,</hi> which you ſay, <hi>no learned man can doubt of or deny</hi> (but ſure you mean affirm;) when I conſider theſe things, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, I ſhould miſtake you, and do my ſelf wrong (by ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending, yea ſtifling my judgement) if I ſhould not ſee clearly, the Epiſcopacy, which you pretend to reconcile to the Covenant, is no other then that very frame and fabrick of government, which <hi>Smectymnuus</hi> tells us, was of <hi>humane invention and diabolical occaſion,</hi> by which <hi>the man of ſin was made manifeſt, and did advance himſelf in the Temple of God,</hi> innovated by <hi>Auſtin the Monck,</hi> ſo exerciſed that it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>papatum alterius mundi;</hi> which my <hi>Analepſis</hi> told you I was jealous you meant in your Analyſis.</p>
            <p>I have Sir (with tiring difficultie) diſcovered the <hi>ratio formalis objecti,</hi> which you profeſs to reconcile to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and make conſiſtent with it, and in my eyes it doth ſeem to be the very ſame with that which <hi>in terminis</hi> was co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanted to be extirpated, <hi>viz. Prelacy, that is to ſay, the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, their Commiſſaries, Chancellors, Deans, Deans and Chapters; Archdeacons,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>depending on that Hierarchy.</hi> But let us ſee how you anſwer the third part of Mr. <hi>Croftons Analepſis,</hi> and acquit your ſelf from the <hi>imbecillity of argumentation</hi> charged on you: And ſir, you ſeem to me to take a very prepoſterous and ſtrange courſe, to commend the ſtrength of your reaſon, by a tedious and long confuſed diſcourſe of rage, enmitie and oppoſition at the Covenant, or by a general <hi>hypotheſis,</hi> that it muſt bind to what <hi>is good, pious, juſt, lawful, and not againſt reaſon, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, juſtice, pietie, morallitie, duty to God and man;</hi> whereas you ought to remember, that <hi>generalia non pungunt;</hi> theſe may be all admitted, and <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> never the nearer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to the Covenant, whereas you ought to have given us a grammatical conſtruction, logical reſolution, genuine interpretation of that <hi>Article,</hi> which ſeemeth croſs to your <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and by a clear acceptation, and vulgar appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion or general ſcope of its words, make it appear that the words will without ſtraining, admit ſuch a ſence and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119354:24"/> but it may be the ſimplicitie (which becomes an oath) of the terms; <hi>extirpation or reformation,</hi> being incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible (except in a fools fancie) might ſtrike you off this: But them you ſhould Sir, have given a point blank charge againſt that Article, which claſheth with your <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> as binding to <hi>injury, injuſtice, immorality, irreligion, againſt the duty we owe to God and man,</hi> and purſued that cloſely by clear and convincing demonſtrations, then had the Biſhop ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a <hi>workman who needed not to be aſhamed;</hi> but let little Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> be never ſo great a Dictator he muſt finde <hi>è quovis lig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no non fit Mercurius;</hi> every tongue well <hi>hung,</hi> cannot be well <hi>tuned,</hi> nor will natural fluencie be eaſily kept to rules of art, or under the command of reaſon: I muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to take you as I find you; and follow you as well as I can in your own confuſion. And Sir,</p>
            <p>I find the fabrick of your diſcourſe, founded on ſome ſeeming principles, which you account <hi>undoubted and eternal,</hi> then rayſed by ſome Hypotheſes, or conjectural fancies fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in your own brain, and ſo your ſtrength is at length di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected againſt that oppoſition to your prelatical ſtructure you undertook to clear by your <hi>Analyſis:</hi> this is the onely order into which Mr <hi>Crofton</hi> can reduce you, and according to which he ſhall now conſider you.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Sir, your foundation is firſt offered to view, in pa. 8, and muſt be conſidered, and you poynt to it, (by <hi>moral and immutable grounds</hi>) in the Margin, and in the Text tell us, your <hi>Analyſis was fixed on theſe undoubted and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal principles of Juſtice, and true Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>No man can lawfully covenant, ſwear, vow or engage him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf contrary to that duty he ows to God, the King, the Church, the Laws and good of his Country, or contrary to that particular Juſtice and charity which he oweth to himſelf, or other men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>If any man be ſurpriſed, or hampered in ſuch Covenanting words, or vowing formes, he muſt find out ſuch a ſence of his words, as may conſiſt with true Religion, Juſtice, and known Laws, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>If this cannot fairely be done, he muſt preſently retract his Covenant, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119354:25"/>
            <p>Sir, before I can digeſt your Notions, and fundamental axioms as <hi>undoubted and eternal, moral and immutable,</hi> I muſt demand proof for part of the firſt, and then the next fall in and follow; think you Sir, a man may in no caſe ſwear, to endeavour in his place or calling to remove <hi>what is eſtabliſhed by Law?</hi> if ſo, you muſt prove it, I do not believe you; for the laws which were good, may become hurtful: will not you Biſhops ſwear, and purſue it to have the ſtatute 17. <hi>Caroli</hi> repealed? if you ſay no, I ſhall not believe you; nor will you be eaſily made to believe it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, and yet I dare boldly affirm it is contrary to your duty: Again, is every Oath unlawful which is againſt the particular <hi>charity and Juſtice, a man oweth to himſelf?</hi> I cannot believe it; a Marchant may find it to be much for his gain, that he Trade to a place, which is to be excluded by League between two Nations, he is required to ſwear; may he ſtand off and ſay, <hi>Charity begins at home,</hi> my <hi>particular charity</hi> doth carry me to Trade thither, to my own enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I may not lawfully ſwear againſt it? Preach this Doctrine, and the people will love you better then your Prince; <hi>my own particular juſtice,</hi> doth bind to exact the utmoſt mite of the Covenants forfeiture or damages, which I recover againſt a man; may I not lawfully mitigate it; and on ſence of the mans poverty, and my own credit, as not revengeful and cruel; may I not ſwear, I will not take one mite, or but one half? you are Sir, no Chapman for me, that will not give me leave to cut a thong out of my own hide. As to your ſecond, <hi>if a man have ſo ſworn, and be ſurpriſed, or ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered by Covenanting words, he muſt ſeek to find a juſt ſence,</hi> if you mean of the <hi>words,</hi> according to their natural ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and others vulgar acceptation, as well as the matter he would performe, I ſhall not much quarrel with you; onely tell you, the fencing of an Oath, when ſworn, is a Tickle ſlippery ſtone to place in a foundation, <hi>it is a ſnare to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure holy things, and after vows to make enquiry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Sir, <hi>for</hi> your third, <hi>not finding ſuch a ſence, he muſt fly off and retract his Oath,</hi> I can in no cauſe conſent, until you have cleared it, that the Oath of the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> was
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119354:25"/> not againſt the <hi>duty they owed to God, their Laws and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, their own charity and juſtice;</hi> or that <hi>Jeptha's</hi> vow was not againſt his own <hi>particular charity and juſtice</hi> (you have ſome whimſies concerning theſe, we ſhall weigh them in their proper places) I am ſure theſe were both ſurpriſed, and whatever you fancie the one did, I am ſure the other did not go about to <hi>ſence</hi> it, as they might much more clearly and rationally then you do the Coven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt. If Sir, theſe be your political axioms, I am ſure the Heathen would ſoon tell you, You are like to bring an old houſe on the head of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Societie, and lay them open to all kind of perſidie: what now, muſt we expect the fabrick and ſuperſtructure to be raiſed and fixed on ſo falſe and ſlippery a foundation, is like to prove? <hi>a falſis nil nifi falſa ſequuntur,</hi> ſuch as is the Theſis, ſuch muſt be Hypotheſis; the following matterials be of the ſame nature, and bear a Symerie to the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work.</p>
            <p>And Sir, when I gather up your rafters (promiſcuouſly ſcattered) to the raiſing of your <hi>Hierarchical, Anti-cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ſtructure,</hi> I find them to be a <hi>hydra</hi> of eccleſiaſtical he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, and political error, by which your Prelacie ſeems to work (like the man of ſin from whom it was derived, the papacie, of which it cannot be denied to be a ſpecies, though <hi>alterius mundi</hi>) with all <hi>deceiveableneſs unto all unrighteouſneſs;</hi> the which you muſt give me leave to pile up and lay together, that your ſelf, and ſuch on whom you pretend influence may diſcern them. Yet Sir, I have more charity then to count you an Heretick; I judge them to be the exuberancie of your inconſiderate <hi>loquacity,</hi> the excreſcencie of an unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded tongue, <hi>darkening knowledge by words without wiſdom;</hi> for <hi>in a multitude of words there cannot want much ſin:</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever by a bold and baſe <hi>petitio principii</hi> you build upon them, I hope when you ſee them naked, you will retract them, and run away from your own ſtructure, leſt it tumble on your own head, to your ruine as well as ſhame.</p>
            <p>Concerning Epiſcopacy, the <hi>Object</hi> and <hi>Ratio formalis</hi> of the debate; I have obſerved your unwillingneſs to be miſtaken, and therefore have done my diligence to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119354:26"/> you, and do think I have taken you right (and as your preſent ſtate doth declare to all the world) and whilſt I ſay the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant</hi> doth bind in the plain, lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and obvious ſence <hi>to the extirpation thereof,</hi> you do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine it cannot ſo do, <hi>rationally, juſtly, honeſtly, piouſly, morally, religiouſly,</hi> with an heap of ſuch words; but if it ſo binde us it is void; but inſtead of thoſe <hi>clear, conſtant and pregnant beams of right reaſon and true Religion</hi> which you promiſed in your <hi>Analyſis,</hi> and I demanded in my <hi>Analepſis,</hi> you us preſent with the foggie fancies of your own brain, and run away with them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y your fluid and gliding tongue or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, as if granted; as your <hi>moral and immutable princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> indiſpenſably and undeniably true, whilſt every know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man will tell you nothing but a flood of vanity can drive you to imagine them ſo to be: Particularly you conclude, as without contradiction theſe Ten things, which in their aſpect and appearance will be found (by any man converſant in Scripture, and acquainted with the eſtate and affairs of the Church) notorious falſhoods.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Presbytery hath no divine appointment, was not command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God, never uſed in the ancient Church, hath nothing in it piouſly, morally or po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itically good or neceſſary. Epiſt. to the Reader.</hi> How Sir? can you read of the <hi>Elders of Epheſus,</hi> and the <hi>Presbyterie that ordained Timothy,</hi> and ſay <hi>Presbytery was not commanded by God?</hi> Can you read in the Fathers, of the Presbyterie advancing by their own power a <hi>primus Presbyter,</hi> in the antient canons of the eſſentialitie of the Presbyteries concurrence, in all acts of Diſcipline of the Fathers Epiſtles to, and concerning <hi>Presbyteries,</hi> and yet ſay <hi>Presbytery was never uſed in the Church?</hi> Can you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider <hi>Presbytery</hi> is a Colledge of Goſpel Miniſters, gove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>communi conſilio</hi> by j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynt advice, and yet conclude there is in <hi>Presbyterie nothing piouſly, morally, or politically good?</hi> Will not every childe in his double Pſalter tell you, <hi>In the multitude of Councellors there is ſafety?</hi> and every School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boy teach you <hi>plus vident oculi, quam oculus?</hi> and yet are you ſo blind as to ſee no <hi>moral, political good in Presbyterie?</hi> but this is but one Doctors opinion; the meaneſt Clerk in your
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119354:26"/> Cathedral would tell you, your Grace was at a loſs when you thus concluded. Nor do you hit the next.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Presbytery was not conjoyned to Epiſcopacy</hi> (if you mean in its firſt conſtitution, and the order of it, which was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out and before Biſhops, afterwards made by its power, you begin well) <hi>nor hath any power or authority unto the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Church, is no way neceſſary to a Biſhop, otherwiſe then by advice, when called and required, and that to be taken or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed at the Biſhops pleaſure,</hi> pag. 289. I pray Sir, help the Papiſts and untie that knot, whether <hi>Peter received the keys of the Kingdom of heaven, as a Presbyter or Biſhop, ordinary Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, or Apoſtle, or prince of the Apoſtles.</hi> It is pity <hi>John Chryſoſtom</hi> had not you for his Advocate, when he was char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged as with a crime for ordaining without his Presbyters: I hope the correction of the ancient Canons being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to you, you will purge out thoſe that confine the Biſhop to his chair, to declare and execute the decrees of the Presbyterie, and make void the ordinations and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures made without the Presbyterie, forget them of the Council of <hi>Carthage.</hi> And Sir, there is one paſſage or two in Scripture worth your notice; <hi>Let him tell the Church, ſufficient to ſuch an one is</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment inflicted by many:</hi> You know Sir they are words that imply <hi>plurality, dignity and authority.</hi> I pray Sir, when your pen is in your hand, draw a line through theſe words, in the form of ordering Prieſts, <hi>miniſter the Diſcipline of the Church;</hi> to what end ſhould they promiſe <hi>faithful diligence</hi> to that which they have nothing to do withal, and concerneth them not. But to the third.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>To endeavour to advance Presbytery to exerciſe in the rule and government of the Church, is Schiſme and Superſtition,</hi> pag. 214, 215. How, is Church Government <hi>an Article of Chriſtian faith,</hi> and an <hi>eſſential act of Divine Worſhip?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oxford</hi> Reaſons Sect. 3.</note> your friends at <hi>Oxford</hi> were of another mind, when they charged the <hi>Scots</hi> ſuppoſed ſay ſo, to look like <hi>Schiſme and Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> What fools were <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus, Auguſtin, and Gregory the great,</hi> and other Fathers to Father <hi>John Gauden;</hi> they left us this ground of <hi>Schiſme and Superſtition, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitas
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119354:27"/> Eccleſiae catholicae non conſiſtit in uniformitate diſciplinae, ſed in unitate fidei:</hi> but our Biſhop ſtandeth on their ſhoulders, and can ſee further then little Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> who yet hopes to ſee as far, as little <hi>Zacheus in his Sicamore Tree,</hi> advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing <hi>Presbytery</hi> as <hi>Gods inſtitution,</hi> and to keep the <hi>unty of the ſpirit in the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Biſhops are the ſole and chief ciſterns, conſervators, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit, and derivators of all holy orders, diſcipline and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the principal Pillars and Fathers of the Church.</hi> pag. 221, 248.</p>
            <p>I hope Sir, you will then make your ſucceſſion as clear as the ſun: I would make a journey to <hi>Exeter,</hi> to have the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricacies thereof well unravelled, what became of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, when in <hi>Alexandria &amp; per totum Aegyptum,</hi> the Presbyters did ordain; and think you, that <hi>Denmark demoliſhed the Church,</hi> when <hi>Chriſtian their third King</hi> did by <hi>publick edict,</hi> beat down your Pillars? your charity is more to the reformed Churches, then to condemn or cenſure them as no Churches, pag. 196. but yet you will cut off their pipes, ciſterns, conduits, and make them come fetch Waters at your Wells; your charity is very rational.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Epiſcopal preſidency, and authority, is a Soveraign power, and ſpiritual juriſdiction in ordination, confirmation, cenſures, rebuking, ſilencing, excommunication, abſolution, and other exerciſe of Eccleſiaſtical power; without, above, and againſt Presbyters and people.</hi> pag. 215, 229. Well ſaid D. <hi>Gauden,</hi> I like a man that can ſpeak out, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſhall know your meaning anon; but your juriſdiction is ſo ſpiritual, that to him your <hi>Sovereign</hi> power is <hi>inviſible;</hi> it is probable you may make him feel it, though he cannot ſee it, but I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident it muſt be in his <hi>body,</hi> not in his <hi>ſoul;</hi> make good this deſcription by Scriptures, Fathers, Divine principles, or good Authors Popiſh, or Proteſtant, and if you make not a <hi>full formal Pope,</hi> I will burn the Covenant, renounce my reaſon, and believe as your Church believes; for all that I have met with, give Presbyters an intereſt (if not the greateſt ſhare) with, and without the Biſhops, in every of theſe acts of Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119354:27"/>6. <hi>The Epiſcopacy which England had, or the Engliſh Hierarchy for its difference from Presbytery, in place, honour, office, autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, uſe, and honourable ſupport, is of univerſal tradition, and obſervati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, in all ages and places, eminent in the judgment and practice of antiquity, and the Church, from Chriſt and his Apoſtles until now of late, in uſe and authority in the Church, as the Lords day, and infant baptiſme; which to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is impudence, and falſity, againſt the very letter, and practice of the new Teſtament, and judgment of all antiquity.</hi> Pag. 198, 220<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 228, 248. How Sir, the <hi>practice and letter of the new Teſtament,</hi> and yet but a tradition, you ſure will ſay more of it, you do well to paralel it to the <hi>Lords day, and infant Baptiſme,</hi> for they will be evidently grounded on the <hi>practiſe, and letter of the new Teſtament;</hi> and ſo be found more then a <hi>tradition:</hi> but Sir, will you ſtand by it, that Epiſcopacy was an <hi>univerſal obſervation in all ages, and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in all places till of late?</hi> I pray Sir, enquire when it came into <hi>Scotland;</hi> and how baſely it was driven out of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, they are places in the Chriſtian World: again was <hi>Englands Hierarchy diſtinct from Presbyters, in place, office, authority, honour, uſe, and honorable ſupport, of univerſal tradition, and practice?</hi> how am I miſtaken in the <hi>poverty</hi> of the Primitive Biſhops, and the <hi>parity</hi> at leaſt, of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie to Epiſcopacy: I muſt borrow your Spectacles when I look into any thing of antiquity, but ſure Sir, <hi>Smecty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nuus</hi> will not think you modeſt, to charge <hi>impudence and falſity</hi> on ſuch as deny it, they were bold to contradict your opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this very poynt, aſſerted by the <hi>remonſtrant,</hi> your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſour, and aſſign ſeveral things, in which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bſhops differ from the primitive, when you have reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them, we will find you more; but they will be enough for one book of forty ſheets.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>This univerſal cuſtome is not to be deſpiſed by any ſober Chriſtian; yet this Epiſcopacy is not onely tradition, and univerſal obſervation, for it hath further the ſtamp and impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of divine order and wiſdome, Scripture precept, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolique pattern, all right reaſon, prudence and policie,</hi> pag. 247. <hi>we need not go far to find the precepts, can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns, commiſſion,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119354:28"/> power and authority of this Epiſcopal juriſdiction, given by Jeſus Chriſt, and his Apoſtles,</hi> pag. 228. <hi>ſuch Biſhops rooted in Chriſt, branched in the twelve Apoſtles, and ſpread in all the Chriſtian world, and endowed with honorary ſupports,</hi> pag. 220. I like you Dr, that you ſpeak out, moſt Epiſcopal men ſtand ſtammering at a <hi>divine right,</hi> as if afraid to ſay it were to be found in Epiſcopacy; and yet Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> can plainly ſee the <hi>ſtamp and impreſſion,</hi> not onely of <hi>right reaſon, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and policy,</hi> but of <hi>divine order and wiſdome,</hi> yea <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture precept, and Apoſtolique pattern,</hi> the very <hi>canons, and commiſſion of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> I muſt confeſs I am ſo dark ſighted, I cannot ſee it; I dare not encline to ſay, or think as Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> doth, that the Apoſtles were <hi>proper Biſhops,</hi> or, <hi>ſuch as are our Engliſh Biſhops,</hi> becauſe our learned and judicious Whitaker, (whom I judge no way ſhort of Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi>) declareth it to be the fancie of a crack brain. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres cum Jacobum Epiſcopum vocant, aut etiam Petrum, non proprie ſumunt Epiſcopi nomen, ſed vocant eos epiſcopos illarum eccleſiarum in quibus aliquando commorati ſunt; &amp; ſi proprie de epiſcopo loquuntur, abſurdum eſt Apoſtolos fuiſſe epiſcopos; nam qui proprie epiſcopus eſt, is Apoſtolus non poteſt eſſe; quia epiſcopus eſt unius tantum eccleſiae, at Apoſtoli plurium eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum fundatores, &amp; inſpect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res erant; non multum diſtant ab in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſania dicere, Petrum fuiſſe proprie epiſcopum, aut reliquos Apoſtolos.</hi> I hope Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> will not charge Dr. <hi>Whittaker</hi> with <hi>impudence and falſhood;</hi> and I think he ſtrikes at the very root of his ſuppoſed <hi>Divine impreſion, and Apoſtolical practice and precedent,</hi> to which you refer us for proof; but that this may be believed, you muſt needs proceed.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>The teſtimonies of the Fathers, Councils and Hiſtorians, are ſo neceſſary to the Scriptures, that without them no man can receive ſatisfaction, concerning the diſtinct offices of the Church; the difference between the community of Chriſtian duties, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors and believers of the common verity and ſpecialty of the office of Preachers,</hi> pag. 247, 248. But Sir, is a charge of imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in the Scripture the only ſupport of your Prelacy? or doth it abide as a mark of its papacy? I apprehended the Scriptures <hi>profitable for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119354:28"/> in righteouſneſs, that the man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto all good works;</hi> which it can never be, if we cannot by it receive ſatisfaction <hi>concerning the diſtinct offices in the Church</hi> (which are the only means of intercourſe between God and the ſoul) <hi>or the common Chriſtian duties of profeſſors, and beleiving of the common verity, or ſpecialty of the off ce of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> certainly if the word be in this too ſhort, the writings of the Fathers, Councils and Hiſtorians, muſt needs <hi>aediſicare in Gehennam;</hi> guide us like a dark lanthorn into inevitable danger; for whence did they know theſe, if not from Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture? this you ſtumbled on to divert the diſpute of the <hi>Office, name, degree, order and authority of your Biſhop,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> put you upon. Sir, I am ſorry I ſhould be an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of your divulging ſuch an error, which your <hi>Anatomiſt will</hi> readily pick up as piece of <hi>blaſphemy; incidit in Scyllam, qui vult vitare Charybdim,</hi> you would avoid the diſpute of the <hi>Divine right of your Epiſcopacy,</hi> as that which was dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to your See, and have laid a foundation for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other diſpute concerning the <hi>perfection of the Scriptures,</hi> as to the <hi>common duty of Chriſtians, and ſpecial office of Preachers;</hi> and that on a fancy too; For Sir, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> would have you know, he hath an audience and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for the Fathers, Councils and Hiſtorians, as venerable witneſſes in matter of fact, but cannot receive them as judges in matter of right, and ſole Dictators of duty. Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> hath read that when <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was pinched with a paſſage out of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> he made anſwer, <hi>Sunt certilibri dominici, quorum authoritati utri<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> centimus utri<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſervimus, ibi quaeramus Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, ibi diſcutiamus cauſam noſtram.</hi> Sir, whatever you ſay in an angry mood, I wil hope you will joyn with me in an appeal to the Scriptures, and then I ſay, <hi>ibi quaeramus Epiſcopum,</hi> find your Epiſcopacy there, for otherwiſe if I find its <hi>extirpation</hi> in the Covenant, I'le ſtand by it, it muſt be <hi>extirpated,</hi> if King, and Kingdome, or peace, and glory muſt be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from Gods angry extirpation; for <hi>bona mutabilia</hi> are within the verge of mans vow, and reach of his hand, but you being looſed from the truth, tumble you know not whither, and therefore you ſuggeſt.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:119354:29"/>9. <hi>Epiſcopacy is a matter of Faith, eſſential to the being of the Church, an eminent part of Gods Worſhip, which may not be wanting, withdrawn from, or withſtood, changed or covenanted againſt, without Schiſme, and ſuperſtition,</hi> Pag. 195, 214, 215. Yet you dare not truſt it to the tryal of the Scriptures; I promiſe you Sir, I dare not admit any thing as an <hi>Article of my Creed,</hi> nor offer to God any thing as an <hi>act of his Worſhip,</hi> which is not plain and obvious in the Scriptures, without the witneſs and Authority of Fathers, Councel, or Hiſtorian. I muſt adventure the <hi>ſchiſme and ſuperſtition,</hi> I hope Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> doth not uſe Schiſme and ſuperſtition, as the old Prelates did the term <hi>Puritan,</hi> and Englands late Tyrants did the term <hi>Malignant,</hi> as words of no ſignification, but onely ſerved to nickname, and reproach the oppoſers of their prophane principles, and proceeding, and to deter men from the diſcharge of required duty, but to ſecure your Prelacy, you go one ſtep further; and ſuggeſt, yea, ſpeak out, that</p>
            <p n="10">10. <q>Biſhops are coordinate, and equal with Kings, in that commiſſion (the word) whereby God hath left liberty to his Church, or the chief Governours thereof, Kings or Biſhops, to order all things, as they ſhall judge meet, <hi>Page</hi> 205. Epiſcopacy is unalterable by any lawful humane power, Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> peremtorily determineth, that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, Kings, Lords and Commons have no prudent, moral, religious and lawful authority, to change the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, univerſal, and excellent government by Biſhops, for Chriſtian Kings and their Parliaments are obliged to the Laws of God, and rules of Chriſtian piety, and policy too, of which the whole Church in its primitive example, and conſtant cuſtome is the beſt interpreter: No legiſlative power is empowred by Gods law to bring in hereſie, error, or ſchiſme into the Church; or take away the eſſentials of ſound Doctrine, and Chriſtian Communion, ever owned and maintained in the Church of Chriſt: pag. 196. well ſaid Doctor, <hi>aut Caeſar, aut Nullus:</hi>
               </q> No Biſhop, no King, muſt now be a Scripture maxime, and article of faith, if <hi>Smectymnuus</hi> his ſtirr up, to the papacy, be not now held,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119354:29"/> 
               <hi>Salmaſius</hi> his <hi>Apparatus ad papatum aſſerted,</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> his <hi>Epiſcopi papam pepererunt</hi> verified, by the Biſhop of <hi>Exeter,</hi> I am much miſtaken, but Sir have you not ſtretched too far, and ſtept into a premunire? little Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> ſhould fear to be made leſs by the head, as guilty of Treaſon, ſedition at the leaſt, ſhould he thus confront King and Parliaments, in what all their Statutes declare to be their own <hi>creature and conſtitution,</hi> changeable at their pleaſure, even from the ſtatutes of <hi>Carlile,</hi> and 25. of <hi>Edward the</hi> 3. Declaring againſt the Pope, that <hi>holy Church was founded in prelacy, by their own donation, power and authority:</hi> Where is Sir, the Kings Prerogative over <hi>all perſons, in all cauſes Eccleſiaſtical?</hi> What is become of your Oath of Supremacy? can you make this <hi>peremptory determination</hi> (as your ſelf calls it) conſiſt with it, any more then with your Covenant? hath a gracious King lately advanced you, to debaſe, nay dethrone him, and his Parliament too? I know no better confutation of this errour, then the hundred eighteen thouſand, eight hundred and forty pounds, payd by the Biſhops to <hi>Henry</hi> 8. to redeem the premunire into which this perſwaſion had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed them, with the Petition and Statute <hi>of the ſubmiſſion of the Clergy,</hi> which in my apprehenſion runs direct coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Dr. <hi>Gaudens</hi> peremptory concluſion. It hath been obſerved to be the fatal chance of the Deputies of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to loſe their heads, and the Biſhops of <hi>England</hi> to run themſelves into a Premunire: which when his Majeſtie (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with their bold encroachment) doth exact, will make them feel, and it may be deal with them, as did the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> provoked by the ſame peremptorie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations. Theſe Sir are your errors in matters Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, which you muſt give little Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> leave to tell you, are more obvious, notorius, and abominable hereſies, then was that charged upon <hi>Aerius</hi> (though an undeniable uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal truth) by <hi>Epiphanius;</hi> nor doth he fear to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted by any ſober or judicious Prelate, reſolved to keep Epiſcopacy, one peep ſhort of Papacy, unto which I ſhall make bold to oppoſe theſe few concluſions of undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed verity, and univerſally confeſſed by all Antiquitie, which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119354:30"/> (that little Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> may not appear too great a dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour) let Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> (owning ſacred, or Eccleſiaſtick ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) deny it if he can.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Lord Jeſus Chriſt is the Shepheard and Biſhop of our ſouls: the great, good, chief, and onely one,</hi> to whom all muſt be gathered; by whom all muſt be ruled that will be ſaved, and from whom all muſt be authorized, that will feed his flock.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Lord Jeſus executeth this paſtoral charge, and Epiſcopal function, by the Miniſtry of men, ſucceſſively ſent, and commiſſioned by his immediate authority, and in his name, without which they may not Miniſter to, or be received by his flock.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the miſſion and commiſſion of Jeſus Chriſt, is directed and given to two onely officers in his Church, <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops or Elders, and Deacons,</hi> the one to look after the bodies, outward neceſſities, and condition of his ſheep, <hi>to ſerve Tables;</hi> the other to manage all the <hi>paſtoral charge,</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopal office,</hi> as it immediately concerneth the ſoul of his people.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That all Miniſters are equally inveſted with, and do intrinſecally poſſeſs authority from Chriſt, for adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all acts of feeding, or ruling the flock of Chriſt, without any difference of <hi>order, place, charge, name, office, or dignity;</hi> and therefore are joyned in the <hi>ſame general com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion;</hi> called by the <hi>ſame name,</hi> Biſhop or Presbyter; choſen by the <hi>ſame characters;</hi> conſeerated after the <hi>ſame order;</hi> charged with the <hi>ſame duty,</hi> feeding or overſeeing; and challenge the <hi>ſame dignity,</hi> eſteem, obedience and double honour from, and among the ſheep.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That for ſome time in the pure and primitive time and eſtate of the Church, the Presbyters did by and among themſelves govern the Church <hi>communi conſilio,</hi> without any over them, as <hi>Epiſcopus epiſcoporum,</hi> or <hi>Paſtor paſtorum,</hi> as having from Chriſt a different order and function, yea without any gradual priority, or preheminence of any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Presbyter above the reſt.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That in proceſs of time the Presbyters neglecting the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119354:30"/> courſe and care of <hi>Chriſtian mortification,</hi> by which they ought to have ſubdued their ambition and paſſions, and ſo ſilenced their ſchiſm, did (by the working of the man of ſin, and permiſſion of God) deviſe a <hi>politique</hi> way or remedy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and advancing among themſelves a <hi>Primus Presbyter ad ſchiſmatis remedium,</hi> who was after dignified with the title <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and was by Canons <hi>(honoris cauſa)</hi> placed in Cities, who was before in any poor village: This giveth juſt ground for <hi>Smectymnuus</hi> note, that Epiſcopacy above Presbytery was an <hi>humane invention on Diabolical occaſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. That all juriſdiction and ruling power was yet acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to abide originally, intrinſecally and properly in the Presbyterie, whoſe creature the Biſhop was, to act, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce and execute their decrees; and therefore when Biſhops began to encroach, and invade the Presbyters liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and authoritie, to uſurp and ingroſs their power and function, and make them ſubject and ſervile to them; Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons were made to limit, confine and ſubject the Biſhop, maintain and preſerve the Presbyters power in <hi>Ordination, Excommunication and Abſolution,</hi> not to be done without the Presbyters: So that Presbyterie was ever known in the Church as <hi>Chriſts and his Apoſtles inſtitution;</hi> and Biſhops apart and in preheminence to them, the Churches <hi>Canonical conſtitution,</hi> and <hi>Presbyters creation;</hi> to the formality of whoſe advancement <hi>conſenſus clericorum</hi> was eſſential.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That by this political preferment of a <hi>primus Presbyter,</hi> the man of ſin did work and exiſt in the Church; engroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the power of the Presbyterie; and advancing himſelf above them, he aſſumed by degrees a <hi>Principality,</hi> to which he made the Presbyters <hi>ſworn vaſſals,</hi> by which became the ſubject of Princes indulgence and benevolence; until capable of univerſal influence and extention through the Chriſtian world, he aſſumed an univerſal Papacie, which he execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſubordinate Biſhops, heads of Dioceſſes and Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (contracted univerſalities throughout the Church) thus <hi>Beza</hi> well notes <hi>Epiſcopi papam pepererunt,</hi> and <hi>Salmaſius</hi> diſcovers the <hi>apparatus ad papatum;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd many judicious men ſee nothing but a gradual difference between <hi>Englands</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:119354:31"/> Prelacie and <hi>Romes</hi> Papacie, this being <hi>in ſpecie</hi> the ſame with that, and ſo a formal <hi>papatus alterius mundi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. Under this uſurpation, Presbyterie ſenſible of its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecal power, did reſiſt, and often complain, and when it was by force (acted by fraud) reſtrained, yet made and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued its conteſts, and its paritie in order and authority; and hath ever been dogmatically aſſerted, and polemically debated by, not only the enemies, but friends of the Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, by Canoniſts, Schoolmen, Commentators and open diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes in Councils, where the Pope durſt never admit a free diſpute, not ſo much as in the Councel of <hi>Trent:</hi> and as the Reformation of the Church proceeded, Presbyterie not only pleaded, but reaſſumed its own proper power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; and managed the affairs of the Church, as againſt the Pope, ſo without Biſhops; and <hi>England</hi> it ſelf, though (through the policie which too much attended and acted its reformation) it retained an Epiſcopacie, yet did dethrone its <hi>ſpiritual juriſdiction,</hi> and reſolve it into a meer <hi>humane and civil conſtitution,</hi> acting <hi>circa eccleſiam,</hi> and moſt plainly avowed the <hi>intrinſecal power of Presbyters,</hi> in the act of the <hi>ſubmiſſion of the Clergie,</hi> and other Statutes diſavowing any <hi>eccleſiaſtical or ſcriptural</hi> conſtitution of Prelacie, and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them from all <hi>juridical acts,</hi> otherwiſe then by the <hi>Kings commiſſion,</hi> and in his name: And all our Engliſh Divines, have openly aſſerted, and polemically defended the power and authority of the Presbyters, in their conteſts againſt Papiſts, concurrence with, and defence of the reformed Churches, and their Presbyterial acts; and at length our late learned Primate of <hi>Armagh;</hi> in his grave Reduction, affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to be <hi>the Presbyters right, to rule and govern the Church, and propounded an expedient in order to the reſtitution thereof, too long held from them;</hi> the which being in its natural tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy <hi>deſperata cauſa papatus</hi> (as <hi>Voetius</hi> hath well termed his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Presbyterated reformed Churches) the man of ſin doth under a <hi>Caſſandrian</hi> accommodation withſtand, and endeavour to ſtifle it; in which however he ſucceed to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, he ſhall not prevail, Presbyterie being <hi>Chriſts own ordinance, and the primitive conſtitution of the Church, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119354:31"/> mediate diſcharge of his paſtoral and Epiſcopal office;</hi> whilſt this is a plain humane conſtitution, conform to the courſe of the world, and contrary to the charge of our great Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.25. <hi>The Princes of the Gentiles exerciſe domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over them, and they that are great exerciſe authority over them; but it ſhall not be ſo among you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, conſider well this Climax, I will aſſure you it is to me ſo obvious and apparent in Eccleſiaſtical ſtory, that he that will not ſee muſt turn Sceptique, and muſt ſay, <hi>Non per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſeris etiamſi perſuaſeris;</hi> and how much ſoever Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie be ſleighted, and repreſented to the world with the inſignificant, odious charge of <hi>Schiſm and ſuperſtition,</hi> Chriſts kingly Office in and over his Church is bottomed in it, and the recovery of its full liberty, to the exerciſe of its juſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, is not only juſtice, but duty, that may, that which muſt be purſued, pleaded for unto bonds, yea death it ſelf; and therefore to match your number; I upon theſe undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able premiſes make theſe concluſions, which if you will turn your Rhetorick into Reaſon, and with a calm and compoſed ſpirit debate it, I will be bound logically and theologically to defend againſt you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hierarchia Anglicana non eſt eccleſia, nec ad eccleſiae entitatem, aut gubernationem neceſſaria, adeo ut ejus extirpatio eſtimetus ſchiſma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hierarchia Anglicana eſt nullo modo divina, aut eccleſiaſtica, ſed mere humana, &amp; civilis, cujus abolitio, &amp; extirpatio ſit lici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſub juramento faederanda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Englands</hi> Hierarchy is not the Church, nor neceſſary to the being or government thereof, ſo as that the extirpation thereof ſhould be accounted ſchiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Englands</hi> Hierarchy is neither divine or eccleſiaſtical, but meerly civil and humane, whoſe abolition and extirpation may be lawfully ſworn and covenanted. Until Sir theſe be confuted, you who blame others, do your ſelf build upon a plain <hi>petitio pincipii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> being well conſidered, will be found no leſs erroneous in his <hi>Politiques</hi> then in his <hi>Eccleſiaſtiques,</hi> run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119354:32"/> away with certain general notions, as if univerſally gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and undoubtedly true, and agreed upon by all; whilſt indeed they are openly and generally denied: I ſhall gather them together as the former, and leave the Reader to take notice of them, as he reads his book, they running as a line through his book, ſome of them being obvious in every page, where his paſſion would give him leave to ſpeak like a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable creature. As that</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Hierarchy or Epiſcopacy is establiſhed by the Laws of England,</hi> which I have in my <hi>Analepſis Analepthe</hi> deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the <hi>Covenanters</hi> plea hath more fully and judiciouſly expoſtulated, and contradicted in Cap. 6. pag. 22, 23, 24. I do aver, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laws, finding Epiſcopacy conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant about the Church, doth reſtrain its exorbitancies, and direct its adminiſtrations, but neither Canon, nor common law doth eſtabliſh it, and <hi>in terminis</hi> declare, and authorize it to be the Government of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>No Oath may be fully ſworn, which ſhall bind to an endeavour to extirpate what is eſtabliſhed by law;</hi> and therefore, although ſworn by the legiſlative authority and command, or by the ſharers in the legiſlation, it is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> void, and yet endeavour of alteration is to every man <hi>ſui juris,</hi> no way inconſiſtent with that paſſive obedience, which we owe to laws in force; and all Laws lye vailed, and at the legiſlators feet, to take up, or refuſe and void; and an Oath is the moſt poſitive authentique repeal of a law vailed, and at the leaſt binding the ſharers in the legiſlation, and ſuch as ſhall ſucceed into their capacity, to repeal thoſe laws which eſtabliſh the thing, which they have ſworn to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>There is no legiſlative power, de facto operating, and exerted, binding the ſubject to any action, or obedience, unleſs all things concur, which may conſtitute a full and formal ſtatute law; and ſo</hi> all Votes, Orders, and Ordinances, Reſolves and Judgment of any the Eſtates of Parliament, are of no force, power or authority, during their ſeſſion; Which all Lawyers acquainted with <hi>Englands</hi> conſtitution will deny, unleſs their Oracles of divinity have at the <hi>Temple</hi> taught
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119354:32"/> them new notions of law, which the conſtant practice of Lords and Commons, and ſubjection and obedience of thoſe, whom they repreſent, doth ordinarily contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That Lords nor Commons, ſeverally, nor both conjunct can impoſe on themſelves, or others whom they repreſent, any Oath, without the knowledge, conſent and command of the King, and if they do, it is</hi> ipſo facto; <hi>void</hi> therefore you ſuggeſt that the proteſtation which is apparently ſworn by Parliament, and Kingdome without the King, to be <hi>precarious;</hi> whilſt there is nothing of petition in it, but much of <hi>legiſlation,</hi> and that manifeſt by the ſubjects obedience, even to your Champions, the Authors of the <hi>Oxford</hi> reaſons; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt be proved.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That the Parliament putting an Oath upon themſelves as the collective body of the Nation, doth not tranſmit an obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Nation, us and our poſterities, who ſhall any way ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed into that national capacity;</hi> as if Parliaments were not the Princes, yea more, the body of the people, doing in their names, and by their conſent, what ever they do; and if they do it by an act of permanent nature, binding poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in all ages, that can diſpoſe their ſucceſſion into that capacity: of this ſee more in my faſtning of St. <hi>Peters</hi> Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Sect, 6.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>That tumults, ſtirs, and the timorous withdrawings of ſome, doth nul and void a Parliament eſtabliſhed by a poſitive law, and without any poſitive, viſible and real force, ſecuring their doors, to the barring of the entrance of any the Members, to the diſcharge of their duties:</hi> and eaſie way to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve Parliaments, and blow them up without Gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>That the Parliament can Act, Vote, Determine, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute nothing under the Kings withdrawing from them, into any part of his own Country:</hi> Who may yet do all things in his infancy, or whilſt in a Forreign Country, as if the place of his retirement, or reaſon of his abſenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, did add or abſtract to the Authority of Parliament.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>That the two houſes alone, nor King alone, no nor King with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119354:33"/> them, have any legiſlative power to decree or execute what is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſnes againſt God or man.</hi> So that the legiſlation is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the piety and juſtice of the decree; And rebellion againſt authority, is acquitted by the iniquity of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. <hi>An authoritative aholiſhing of any ſubordinate order or ſociety of men, is injuſtice to the perſons, and poſſeſſions of the preſent Occupants:</hi> And ſo <hi>England</hi> is bound to pennance, for the aboliſhing Monks Nuns and Abbeys; and that <hi>no King or Parliament have a power, or can juſtly extirpate and aboliſh out of the Nation any trade, calling or order of men any way uſeful to the Common-wealth,</hi> Tinkers and Pedlers, and men of the like order, will certainly cleave cloſe to this conſervator of their liberty.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>That no King can lawfully ſwear to the diminution of his own prerogative and power, or honorable eſtate,</hi> which all people in the world, muſt and will contradict.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>The ſolemn League and Covenant, binding to an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to extirpate prelacy, is irreconcileable to the duty we owe to God and man. Firſt, to the Kings Supremacy. Second, to the Church and Countrys peace and honour. Third, to the glory of God, in the Government of the Church. Fourth, to the reformation of reformed Religion. Fifth, to the conſcience and care of avoiding Sacriledge, Schiſme, and Faction. Sixth, to the juſtice we ow to all godly, honeſt, and deſerving men, eſpecially Miniſters;</hi> cujus contrarium verum eſt.</p>
            <p>Sir, whilſt you take theſe for granted, which are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to right reaſon, natural policy, Eccleſiaſtical ſtory, yea and truth it ſelf, you may eaſily raiſe your Fabrick, ſwell your book, and run on in a magiſterial reda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gution, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latical determination, and raging, reviling, opprobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous rebuke; but Sir you muſt remember, a man that is firſt in his own cauſe ſeemeth righteous, but his Neighbour cometh after and findeth him out. <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.17.</p>
            <p>We ſhall leave the Doctor to a view of theſe Rafters, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned to his foundation, and promiſcuouſly ſcatterd up and down his book; And more particularly obſerve the ſtrength of his argumentation in his reply to what was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted againſt in his <hi>Analyſis,</hi> and ſpecially as it relateth to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119354:33"/> Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> leaving Anonymous to himſelf, who here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in will finde full work for his anatomizing genius.</p>
            <p>The firſt onſet of Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> (in this his vindication of his <hi>Analyſis</hi>) made upon Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> his <hi>Analepſis,</hi> is in page 147: and thus enters, viz. <hi>[Which was the thing Dr.</hi> Gauden <hi>had to prove (as Chriſt did the reſurrection) not out of the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter only, but the Analogie and equity of that Scripture, from the force of which M.</hi> Crofton <hi>cannot extricate himſelf by his more ſoberendeavours.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Under this charge I muſt enquire what it was he had to prove? and I find nothing in this ſentence dictating what it ſhould be, ſave only the relative <hi>[which]</hi> from which his rhetorick, or rather his indigeſted heap of words, hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved the antecedent at ſuch a diſtance, that I cannot eaſily find it; I looked into the Paragraph fore-going to find out the thing ſpoken of, as that which according to the gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical conſtruction ſhould make the Antecedent to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative; and there I find this general concluſion, viz. <hi>[Such Vows and Covenants, ſo much to the ſcandal of Religion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of Reformation, gratifying dangerous factions, diſgrace of this and all reformed Churches, diſhonor to Jeſus Chriſt, his Apoſtles and chief Succeſſors the Biſhops, ſo injurious to many worthy men, to the whole Church and Nation of</hi> England, <hi>ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought not to be taken by Chriſtian King and People: or if by force, fraud or fear and facility they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſo taken, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impoſed and miſtaken, yet they mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t never be kept in any ſuch ſence: bue either repented of, and diſſolved, or elſe the words muſt be reſolved and reduced to ſuch a ſence as is good, and lawful: Id quod erat demonſtrandum.]</hi> To leave his Libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to take up his <hi>petitio principii,</hi> as to our Covenant, not ſuch in point of <hi>matter or form,</hi> nor ſo <hi>impoſed or miſtaken,</hi> as he ſuggeſteth, and taketh for granted, and to demand his <hi>Id quod erat demonſtrandum:</hi> This ſentence muſt be the antecedent to his relative <hi>[which]</hi> for ſo it is connexed, <hi>which was the thing Dr.</hi> Gauden <hi>had to prove out of that Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what is the Scripture out of which he muſt prove this concluſion? I find no Scripture nigh hand, that can be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119354:34"/> the proof produced; running ſome ſeven pages back, through a wilde wilderneſs of words, I find in pag. 140. a quarrel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun about <hi>Numb.</hi> 30. and other Scripture is not urged; this was the Scripture which was produced in his <hi>Analyſis</hi> (though with a miſquoted verſe) and muſt be vindicated in this book; ſo that this only muſt be the Scripture predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to prove his <hi>[which]</hi> before noted, and then indeed Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> more ſerious endeavours cannot extricate him from the entanglements of the Doctors wilde fancy, for the Text neither the letter, nor analogy, doth afford any ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion: All Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> brains cannot beat ſuch a ſenſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the words, they are ſo far <hi>out.</hi> The Text in the <hi>letter</hi> of it is a ſpecial direction concerning the vow of a <hi>daughter or wife vowing without</hi> the knowledge of the <hi>Father or Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band:</hi> In the <hi>Analogie</hi> of it, of the <hi>Inferior ſwearing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the knowledge of the Superiour,</hi> and directeth an <hi>eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or irritation</hi> of the vow, not any <hi>ſencing or interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, id quod erat demonſtrandum.</hi> And how Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> can make it grammatically ſpeak, or logically conclude, <hi>Such a Vow ſo ſcandalous to religion, gratifying to faction, diſhonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Chriſt, diſgraceful to England, muſt not be ſworn, if ſworn, not kept; if kept, ſenced and interpreted,</hi> I am certain all the Doctors in <hi>Oxford</hi> cannot diſcern it: If Chriſt had thus proved the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> the Saducees would never have been ſilenced, and we muſt have been at a ſad loſs for the great Article of the reſurrection of the body, that ground of our Chriſtian hope. Will Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> pleaſe to frame his argument <hi>a pari,</hi> for little Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> reſcue he conceives it muſt run thus,</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 30. Directeth that the Oath or vow of a Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Wife, or other inferiour, made without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Father, Husband, or Superiour, ſhould be at the pleaſure of the Superiour, confirmed or made void; Ergo, no ſcandalous, diſgraceful, diſhonourable Oath, may be taken, if taken, muſt not be kept, if kept it muſt be well interpreted:</q> by what rules muſt we meaſure this argument? the Anticedent is particular, the conſequent is general; it muſt needs be a ſyllogiſme <hi>currens quatuor pedibus,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119354:34"/> running as faſt as <hi>B</hi> followeth <hi>A, C</hi> followeth <hi>B</hi> and ſo one followeth another, and all follow <hi>A</hi> immediately, the frame ſuch, upon which the concluſion followeth the connexed termes as naturally, as the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> at the conference at <hi>Ratisbone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qui negat articulum fidei eſt haereticus; ſed hoereticus eſt, qui negat Tobiam habuiſſe canem; Ergo, ſequitur, articulum eſſe fidei, quod Tobias canem habuerit.</hi> The barking Cur at the Moon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of Dr. <hi>Gaudens</hi> logique, is ſeen as plain as the ſun, continually diſturbing his reaſon.</p>
            <p>I find the Dr. in a Wilderneſs of words, and wood of invention, toſſing the words of this Scripture, telling us one while, they are meant of <hi>lawful vows,</hi> another while <hi>the Oath is made through weakneſs;</hi> another while <hi>to the damage of the ſuperiour;</hi> and ſo ſtretching them, as the onely ſquare and rule for all Oaths; but yet can ſtumble on no ready way, due proportion, or fit parallel, whereby to reſolve them, but at lenth prepoſterouſly breaks through them, with an invective againſt the nameleſs Libeller, which concludes with a <hi>doloſus verſatur in generalibus</hi> (which none is more guilty of then Dr. <hi>G.</hi>) and concludeth, <hi>that may be juſt by ſome general maximes, or cuſtomes of common law, which yet is very unjuſt, when brought to the rules of Chancerie, as D.</hi> B. <hi>well knows in</hi> Hipſlies <hi>caſe,</hi> pag. 145. The Dr. hath ſure made a good proficiency in his <hi>Temple Studies,</hi> but I muſt enquire what <hi>Chancery</hi> can comment on the <hi>maximes of the common Law;</hi> I know the juſt, and proper ſtrict rigour of them may be mitigated, muſt not be denied, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then as to execution, what Chancellour muſt do it on Gods Law? or hath a Commiſſion to interpret an Oath, beyond what its genuine ſence alloweth? or to reſtrain the performance of it unto God? Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> doth aſſume (not to ſay preſume) to do it, and we well know Biſhops have been Lord Chauncellours of <hi>England?</hi> Though we deny his Authority, let us a little conſider his equity, for the ſtrictneſs of an Oath is an heavy burden, and many times bindeth a man to loſs and grief; and he proceeds by ſome ſpecial caſes, which he ſuppoſe thought not to be made, or
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119354:35"/> kept; let us take a glance of them, that our minds may be cleared in the ſence of <hi>Numb.</hi> 30.</p>
            <p>His firſt caſe is [<hi>If Parents vow, not to give a Child in Marriage, or not till ſuch a time, or not to give him ſuch a portion, but to devote him to ſingle life, poverty, baniſhment, or baſe employmennt; it is ſinful and injurious, may n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t be made or kept:</hi> in this caſe he muſt give me leave to diſſent from him, untill he have ſtated the caſe more perticularly, as to the reaſon, and ends of ſuch a vow; and until, he have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Child as to all theſe things, is not, to the parent, <hi>ſui juris,</hi> to be diſpoſed of, debaſed, or advanced; although I ſhould neither adviſe, nor commend ſo harſh and heady an exerciſe of parental power, and prerogative, yet if pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the queſtion, I durſt not determine the negative: The Parent finds the Child Proud, Stubborn, Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, Perverſe, voweth to cut him ſhort in his portion, may he not do this in Juſtice, and in his juſt diſpleaſure perform it? may not the Parent ſend the ſtuborn Child to <hi>Barbadoes</hi> by ſlavery to ſubdue his ſpirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? may not the Parent vow he will not give in Marriage, to ſuch a perſon as he judged un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for his child? or is not the Parents conſent in his own power? the danger of a ſingle life are not proper effects of the Parents not giving in Marriage; and Dr. <hi>Saunderſon</hi> diſtinguiſheth between the thing ſworn,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De juram p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ect.</hi> 3. Sect. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which is, <hi>cauſa pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pria,</hi> and <hi>occaſio</hi> or <hi>cauſa per accidens</hi> of ſin, and concludeth that an Oath made concerning the laſt, is not unlawful. I ſhould wiſh Parents to be very wary of making ſuch vows; and Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> as wary of diſcharging them; though raſhly made; that may be ſinfully ſworn by a Parent, which muſt be ſorrowfully performed: if the parent have unadviſedly devoted the child to want, the law may rather take Alimony for him, then the parent perjuriouſly give it: I hope <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhall not be charged with <hi>injury</hi> to them, in ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away <hi>Hagar, and his ſon Iſhmael,</hi> Gods encouragement could not acquit the ſin; and what a parent may do, he may ſwear to do without injury: And methinks the caſe of the Iſraelites ſhould reſolve this caſe fully, they had, (I admit,) raſhly ſworn, <hi>they would not give their daughters to Benjamen;</hi> the effect reflects their Oath very
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119354:35"/> ſadly, and reduceth them into a ſtrait, yet they fear to break it, and upon Counſel from God, find out a way to ſave it, and make ſome ſupply unto the defect; which falling ſhort, they deviſe (ſome think indeed ſinfully) a ſecond ſtratagem rather then break their Oath: what ever others may ſay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this caſe, I cannot but obſerve, <hi>Children are fully ſui juris to the Parent;</hi> an <hi>hurtful oath</hi> is to the child no injury, ſtrictly to be ſo accounted; an Oath concerning them, when raſhly made, muſt be ſtrictly obſerved and kept, the light of nature, and law of Scripture, doth in my apprehenſion in this diſſolve our Chancellours injunction.</p>
            <p>The next caſe, is of the like nature, in reference to <hi>Servants and Subjects,</hi> for ſuppoſing their Maſters, and Princes to have (as Prelates ſuppoſe of every King) <hi>merum imperium,</hi> though they may ſwear raſhly, ſinfully in reference to God, yet not <hi>injuriouſly as to the ſlave or Subject:</hi> Although <hi>Gomarrus</hi> and others note, <hi>that man hath not from God, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> abſolute dominion over himſelf; yet they deny not but men may vow and muſt keep their vows to the latitude of that Dominion, God ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, given them over themſelves or others,</hi> and this is the rule our<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Biſhops Chancery ſhould interpret, and relieve againſt, for this will conclude againſt him, that <hi>a King may ſwear,</hi> or having ſworn, <hi>muſt performe a diminution of his own juſt So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty, and that authority and power which is given him by Law, and is neceſſary for his high calling:</hi> Is a man bound to take what the Law alloweth him, and that, whether he will or no? if ſo, if our prelate can beg the recogniſances forfeited by licenſed victuallers, allowed by the law to the King, it will make his Biſhoprick a fat one.</p>
            <p>But how do theſe caſes clear the concluſion to be proved out of <hi>Numb:</hi> 30? there is nothing relating to the Oath of the ſuperiours, but the aſſerting of their prerogative and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute dominion over their inferiours, to irritate, or eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh their vows; what ever the Libeller did, Mr. <hi>Grofton</hi> in his <hi>Analepſis</hi> allowed the Dr. this Text in its latitude, and referred him to be judged by it; and now granteth, that the inferiour in things, not <hi>ſui juris,</hi> may have the action vow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſuperſeded by the declared pleaſure of the ſuperiour and that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119354:36"/> whether it be ſon, or ſervant, but in our caſe he then affirmed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Parliament ſitting had over us a Legiſlative power, to which we owed ſubjection, they were in their capacity the Nation collective, and <hi>ſui juris,</hi> and to be obeyed during their Seſſion, by thoſe whom they repreſented; their power in this Covenant was no leſs legiſlative then in the Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>May</hi> 1641.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The King who then was hearing of it, did prohibit the Act, but never did declare it null and void; and Dr. <hi>Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon</hi> concludes the ſuperiours diſſent muſt be expreſt in a full, formal d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcharge; <hi>ut t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llendo t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llat, renuendo renuat,</hi> is required to reſcinde the oath: But our late King adviſed to keep the Oath, his preſent Majeſty ſware it, ſware his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to it, and to the Ordinances enjoyning it, and conjured his Subjects to the keeping of it.</p>
            <p>Both theſe Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſuggeſted in his <hi>Analepſis,</hi> and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more fully in his <hi>Analepſis Anelepthe,</hi> which the Doctor ſhould have conſidered before he had declaimed <hi>from the force of this Screpture. Mr.</hi> Cr. <hi>doth not, cannot extricate himſelf, by his more ſerious endeavours,</hi> whilſt Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> hath traverſed his ground, and turned the mouth of his cannon againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and will offer again to joyn iſſues with a man acted by reaſon, to eſtabliſh the Covenant by the <hi>force, equity, analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie</hi> of this Scripture, or otherwiſe to let it fall: But he muſt not be worded out of Gods warrant. But the judicious Doctor oppoſing;<note place="margin">p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>45, 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> counteth Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> obſervations <hi>piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſhifts, and not potent ſolutions, and ſmall twigs at which poor Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>as a drowning man did catch, yea weeds which ſink him, being of no deep reach, nor any skill in ſwimming.</hi> You are very right Doctor, for Mr <hi>Crofton</hi> (God be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) could never yet ſwim with the ſtream, or reach pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment with a profligated conſcience: But let us ſee theſe <hi>twigs and weeds</hi> he taketh notice of, and obſerve whether the Doctors wits be not run a woolgathering, in charging them with weakneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Analepſis</hi> pag. 12.</note>The firſt was, <hi>The two Houſes of Parliament are coordinato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſharers in the Legiſlation of England, and ſo a conſtant law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119354:36"/> authority.</hi> To this the Doctor replieth, <hi>He gently obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth a legiſlative power, at leaſt coordinate in the Parliament;</hi> More modeſt man he, this being out of his ſphear, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then as a Subject and Caſuiſt; yet you might have pleaſed to obſerve he hath more ſtrongly aſſerted and enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced it, <hi>to the faſtning of St. Peters fetters,</hi> Sect. 4. But the Doctor enquires, <hi>Can they legally exerciſe it without and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Kings conſent, being not in his nonago, nor out of his wits;</hi> that they may do it <hi>without the Kings conſent;</hi> none do or can deny it; common practice, with the peoples conſtant obedience doth plainly manifeſt it; as alſo the Proteſtation of <hi>May,</hi> 1641. (never doubted as to the validity of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) which you ſay was <hi>precarious,</hi> but Reſolves of the Houſe declares to have been <hi>authoritative:</hi> Votes, Reſolves, Orders and Ordinances of one or both Houſes do proclaim it; and the priviledges of Parliament, <hi>That the King take no notice of what is debated, or voted, ordered or acted by them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til it be by themſelves formally preſented to his Majeſty:</hi> And the very nature of coordinate power (if the Dr. underſtand it) with their actings in caſe of his abſence by minority, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, doth determine it: As to the exerciſe <hi>againſt the Kings conſent,</hi> I ſhall conclude nothing, but commend Mr. <hi>Prians Sovereign power of Parliaments</hi> to your ſerious ſtudy; yet this much matters not in our caſe: for a Parliament duly ſummoned, and rightly conſtituted, hath his <hi>Majeſties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> to exerciſe that legiſlation placed in them, ſo long as they ſhall continue in that capacity; I think no Engliſh man will deny this: And the legiſlative power of their Votes, Debates, Reſolves, Orders or Ordinances were never gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid by his Majeſty; though the peoples act of ſwearing the Covenant (upon an unhappy difference and miſapprehenſion) was by an unuſual way inhibited.</p>
            <p>But the Doctor further profoundly demands, <hi>Are they legiſlative in fact, where there is no law made (as none was for the Covenant?) was there legiſlation</hi> in actu ſecundo, <hi>in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe or act? as to commend a writer for a book never writ, or an architect for an houſe never built.</hi> Where are now your wits good Maſter of words? Is there is no writing or ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitecture
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119354:37"/> in <hi>actu ſecundo,</hi> in act and exerciſe, until the whole book be writ, or houſe built? I fancied the writing of every page, and framing of every board, or ſquaring of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very beam, and laying every brick, to be ſomthing more then <hi>ſcribendi,</hi> or <hi>aedificandi potentia;</hi> and if any more, how far is it ſhort of <hi>actus ſecundus?</hi> Is there no <hi>Legiſlation</hi> without a full and formal Statute law? What do you make of Votes, Reſolves, Orders, Ordinances of either or both Houſes ſuſpending, ſuperſeding the Laws and Courts of Judicature, directing and diſpoſing the Subjects? enquire at the Temple whether theſe be legiſlation in <hi>actu ſecundo?</hi> Let your old friends a little laugh to ſee the Prelate-Juſtice his profound notions of legiſlation.</p>
            <p>But the Doctors enforcement of theſe premiſes of legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>potentia</hi> and <hi>actu,</hi> is very conſiderable, <hi>At beſt the two Houſes, nor King, nor both together have any legiſlative power to decree, or execute what is unrighteous againſt God or man.</hi> Suppoſe they have not, have they therefore no <hi>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlation in actu ſecundo,</hi> act and exerciſe? elſe what is this to the purpoſe. But ſtay Sir, What is that you ſay? <hi>King and Parliament have no legiſlative power to decree or execute what is unrighteous againſt God or man:</hi> I muſt deny this; have you never read of wickedneſs <hi>eſtabliſhed by a law?</hi> Had Queen <hi>Mary</hi> and her Parliament, who caſt out the true and return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the falſe Religion, no legiſlative power by which they did it? Doth the injuſtice of the matter nullifie the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Law, and Legiſlators; is impiety enjoyned by a juſt authority, to be actually diſobeyed, and reliſted? will not this proſtitute legiſlation to every private fancy? and furniſh all Rebellion with Apology? I am not bound, for the thing decreed is unrighteous, and neither <hi>King nor Parliament, nor both, had legiſlative power to decree,</hi> and cannot therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute it; for execution is ſubſequent to legiſlation; I muſt not be puniſhed where I am not bound to obey. Doctor, whoſe wits are now a <hi>woolgathering,</hi> to run away from the Covenant by ſtating a doctrine of Sedition, yea Rebellion. Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſhould more ſoberly have ſaid [The King and Parliament have legiſlation to all acts of humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119354:37"/> but muſt be careful they do not decree unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, eſtabliſh iniquity by a Law.] You have indeed very powerfully oppoſed Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> his firſt obſervation, beating down all legiſlation <hi>in actu ſecundo,</hi> yea and in ſome caſes which will fall too often, and muſt be judged by every pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man, all <hi>potentia legem ferendi.</hi> What ſay you to the ſecond?</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Croftons</hi> ſecond notion, ſaith the Doctor, his <hi>ſecond no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing obſerved as his ſafety, is, that a thing may bind in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which doth not bind in law, or in the Judicature of man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This M. <hi>Crofton</hi> did ſay, and will ſtick to, againſt the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging billows of your proudeſt words. But what ſaith the Doctor to this notion? <hi>True,</hi> is it true, and yet M. <hi>Croftons nothing? True,</hi> and yet a <hi>pitiful evaſion, a ſmall twig, a ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weed?</hi> Sure Sir, the <hi>true</hi> of ſo big a bladder, will keep little M. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſwiming above water.</p>
            <p>How doth D. <hi>Gauden</hi> avoid the ſtrength of what he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth to be <hi>true,</hi> hath he well weighed it is an <hi>Oath that bindeth in conſcience,</hi> though <hi>not in law, or humane judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu?</hi> how is it that he having cryed <hi>true,</hi> turneth off with a <hi>but nothing can bind in conſcience, againſt the Laws of man, in caſes of equity, juſtice and right.</hi> Suppoſe Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> cry <hi>True</hi> to Dr. <hi>G.</hi> what hath he gained? Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> did not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that any thing of that nature did bind conſcience; but that the Cove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt not charged on any by a Statute Law, yet bindeth the conſcience of all perſonally, or politically ſubjected to it. And Dr. <hi>G.</hi> runs away with his <hi>petitio prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipii,</hi> that <hi>Englands</hi> Epiſcopacy is <hi>eſtabliſhed by Law,</hi> and cannot according to <hi>Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tice, Equity and Common right be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpated;</hi> which M. <hi>Cr.</hi> hath denied, and doth deny; and when it is proved, will further examine how far an oath bindes in conſcience againſt it: But as yet Dr. <hi>G.</hi> offers no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to prove it, but his Worſhips <hi>ſay ſo,</hi> which will not be beleived: Only M. <hi>Cr.</hi> muſt ſay, that my oath may bind me againſt what, according to <hi>equity and right,</hi> the Law muſt adjudge me; as in caſes of contracts, bargains, or alienation of Land or goods, where I have ſworn or vowed a releaſe, of which the Law according to common <hi>juſtice, equity and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119354:38"/> right,</hi> can take no cognizance, but muſt reſtore, I am bound from requiring, or by law receiving the reſtitution or performance. It is hard that Dr. <hi>G.</hi> ſhould loſe the <hi>power of conſcience,</hi> by preaching <hi>equity and right</hi> among the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> third Obſervation, of the <hi>Kings oath making a ſupply to the ſuppoſed defect of authority binding the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;</hi> is entred upon with a drop of his ſarcaſtical pen; for <hi>Mr.</hi> Cr. <hi>bold and odious, no leſs then fallacious</hi> (if you will make a right <hi>Shemaiah,</hi> add ſeditious and treaſonable too) <hi>urging by a Presbyterian pertneſs, the preſent taking of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in Scotland.</hi> I pray you ſir, though this be <hi>bold,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is it <hi>fallacious?</hi> that his Majeſty ſware the Covenant is not nor can be denied; the form of his Royal Coronation, his Royal Declaration from <hi>Dumferling,</hi> and the Hiſtory of King <hi>Charls</hi> the Second, have made it known through the world, that it cannot be hidden. Though had not Dr. <hi>G.</hi> blurred paper to bring perjury upon King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, it had not been here pleaded by Mr. <hi>Crofton.</hi> But Sir,</p>
            <p>Wherein is an argumentative urging the Kings taking the Covenant ſo <hi>odious a piece of Presbyterian pertneſs?</hi> Shall not every Diſputant have liberty with freedom to expreſs, what will enforce his argument? Is not the meaneſt Subject in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted in the Kings oath, and capacitated humbly to demand performance? Do not Royal acts fall under the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Caſuiſts, reſolving conſcience? Are not Kings ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of miniſterial admonition? how bold ſoever it may ſeem, none but a proud <hi>Paſhur,</hi> and ſhameleſs <hi>Semaiah,</hi> could count it <hi>odious</hi> in <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> to ſay to the King, <hi>Keep the oath, and thou ſhalt be delivered</hi> from that diſtreſs which may too late engage his Majeſty to ſend to his faithful Monitor to pray for him: Is not Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> capacitated in all theſe reſpects to conſider his Majeſties oath, even when he is abſtracted from his <hi>Presbyterian pertneſs?</hi> Sir, I muſt tell you it is more odious in you, to make his Majeſties <hi>Legiſlative authority,</hi> depend on the <hi>piety of his decrees,</hi> then for Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> to urge his <hi>Royal Oath,</hi> as a bar to the Nations <hi>perjury.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:119354:38"/>
            <p>Wherein lyeth the odium of an argumentative urging the King taking of the Covenant? it was but modeſtly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the <hi>Analepſis,</hi> though more fully and forcibly to the <hi>faſtning of St. Peters Fetters:</hi> It is every way viſible Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> doth neither juſtifie, nor commend the <hi>inſolent impoſing of it,</hi> but doth expreſly condemn that; although the <hi>maturity of his years</hi> here mentioned by this Doctor, maketh it the more obliging as having the full exerciſe of his <hi>judicium rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onale;</hi> which if it were any way reſtrained by the <hi>diſtreſs of his affairs,</hi> will not releaſe him; becauſe it was choſen as his beſt courſe; and <hi>juramentum metu extortum,</hi> is agreed to bind the conſcience, and as a moral rule, reacheth Kings as well, yea as much, as other men, though therein he is more obnoxious to temptations, and needs to have the caſe more clearly reſolved, if <hi>his Majeſty delight not to hear of it,</hi> (as Dr. <hi>G.</hi> ſcandalouſly reporteth,) more is the pitty, Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> hath in Loyalty to his Majeſty preſſed it, and perſwaded others to preſs it on the ſame principles in his <hi>Analepſis Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepthe,</hi> Sect 1. convincing, and affirming, his Miniſters and Chaplains ought as his Monitors to mind him of it, and affect him with it; though I fear, flattering prelates will rather expoſe him, to hear of it in Gods wrath, and by his Enemies reproach; for the breach thereof, then hazard their dignity, by diſcharge of the duty they owe to God and his Royal ſoul.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Kings taking the Covenant, can make any thing in it lawful, which by the rules of religion and civil juſtice is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> did not affirme, or urge it to that purpoſe; but that it <hi>maketh up the ſuppoſed defect of authority</hi> in the firſt taking the Covenant, is that which Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> ſaid, nor doth D. <hi>G.</hi> deny it, his conſent unto the ordinance for taking the Covenant, expreſſed by Oath, gives it (at leaſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,) the formality of a Law. That what his Majeſty did in <hi>Scotland,</hi> muſt not extend to <hi>England,</hi> is a moſt falſe maxime, according to which we were no way ſecured by what he declared from <hi>Bredah;</hi> but what he ſwear in any place, <hi>qua Rex Britanniae</hi> doth bind his ſoul in every place: Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> out of <hi>Grotious</hi> hath affirmed in his <hi>Analepſis Analepthe,</hi> Sect. 6.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119354:39"/> Which by alll theſe cavils, I diſcern Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> hath not read, I ſhall commend that book with theſe notions to his ſecond thoughts, he will find his ſuppoſed <hi>legiſtative Juſtice,</hi> and the like of Epiſcopacy contra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icted; and the authority pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing and impoſing the Solemn League and Covenant vindicated from all his trivial exceptions; but our Doctor proceeds to enforce his battery, and tells you.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pag, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>51.</note>Mr. <hi>Croftons next defence againſt Dr.</hi> Gaudens <hi>battery is not a Wool ſack, but a brown Paper, a Cobweb, pleading, quod fieri non debuit factum valet;</hi> yet this <hi>Cobweb</hi> is a ſufficient net for his <hi>flye</hi> with which he endeavours to pull it down, and moſt profoundly tells us; <hi>this may not be pleaded in moral caſes,</hi> I pray you Sir, in what then? you cry <hi>true to it,</hi> but it is <hi>in ſome ſtate policies, and civil neceſſities, or legal formalities,</hi> and accutely ampliſieth it: <hi>As Baſtards though they ſhould not have been begotten, yet muſt not when begotten and been be mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, but muſt be kept:</hi> Would not our Doctor deem it a barking at the bright Moon-light of this reaſon, I ſhould enquire whether the begetting of Baſtards be a <hi>ſtate policy, a civil neceſſity, or legal formality,</hi> to keep the Biſhops Courts in employment, that he hath no other inſtance of them, or chooſeth this as the chief? again doth the natural entity of the Child conſiſt in, and depend upon the plea of <hi>quod fieri non debuit, factum valet?</hi> certainly many of his well bred well brooding Chriſtians would gladly obliterate and not plead this rule, if the being of their brats of ſin and ſhame could ceaſe by it; this Sir is good ſport for your Anatomiſt. Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> muſt tell you that he ever concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it to relate to, and muſt be praedicated of moral enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, conſtituted by, and exiſting out of ſome eſſential acts irregularly applyed; as in creation of relation, office, or dignity a <hi>Novice</hi> ſhould not he made a Biſhop, but when conſecration hath paſſed on him, his defect in reaſon or religion will not diveſt him of his dignity, for <hi>fieri non debu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et factum valet:</hi> I ever judged natural beings, as Baſtards, cannot but exiſt in the world, without the help of a moral rule, by the neceſſity of nature; in reference to our caſe,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119354:39"/> what is material, unlawful, cannot be by this rule releived, becauſe it corrects not, ſupplys not the natural defect or ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regularity of any matter; but where the matter is good, and the general form <hi>invocation of God,</hi> is retained, but erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neouſly or ignorantly managed, as when an Oath is made by an <hi>Idol God,</hi> by the Heaven or Earth or other Elements, as the Heathen, who ought not, do commonly ſwear; now ſuch is the moral nature, or reaſon of an Oath, an intended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of the divine nature that it obligeth, and the errour or miſtaken ſpecial mode of ſwearing, will not make void the Oath; and hence it comes to be different queſtions, <hi>an juramentum hoc vel illud ſit licitum?</hi> and <hi>an hoc vel illud obligat?</hi> I would Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> would own Dr. <hi>Saunderſon</hi> as his dictator in the nature of an Oath; he ſhould not then ſo much need the dictates of little Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> who having urged this rule in his <hi>Analepſis,</hi> hath improved and enforced it, beyond the power of this battering Dr. to pierce and break thorough, in his <hi>Analepſis Analepthe, Sect.</hi> 2. where he will in the caſe of the Covenant find <hi>fieri non debuit, factum valet,</hi> explained and eſtabliſhed, to teach him and others, that Gods name prophaned by raſh irregular ſwearing, muſt not be blaſphemed by falſe ſwearing; an unadviſed Oath, muſt not be amended by open perjury, or repaired by rejection, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> doth not believe a <hi>baptiſme by, or ordination of a woman to be valid,</hi> becauſe there is a defect in the <hi>forma con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituens,</hi> which is of the <hi>eſſe</hi> of the ordinance, the woman not being <hi>ſubjectum capax of conferring the one, or receiving the other, hut how ever</hi> had he as a Biſhop pleaded, Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters ordained by Presbyters (though a Biſhop might have been more orderly, their ordination is valid; he had hit on a right inſtance though by an error, and many ptophane prelatical prieſts, which ought not to have been admitted, and ought to have been depoſed from the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> can own as Miniſters; though rude, yet in <hi>Moſes</hi> chair, <hi>quod fieri non debuit factum valet.</hi> Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> Wool-ſacks being thus pulled down, you ſhall hear the Dr. ſhout out his victorious entry on Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> arguments in Pag. 151.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:119354:40"/>
            <p>
               <hi>[Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>diſcovers his weakneſs, and exhauſted ſpirits (well</hi> he may in conteſting with ſo acute a diſputant) <hi>by bringing in a tumultuary rable, that ſhould pretend to be a Parliament, and impoſe a vow or Covenant on the people, againſt the immunities of Church and State, King and People, which we like Gugeons</hi> ſtulta facilitate <hi>ſwallow ſimply like baits, and feeling the hook of fraud, faction, injuſtice, the poor man by a terrible</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſuper ſuperſtition is affraid of a three years Famine, in caſe he and other honeſt men ſhould dare to reſume their reaſon and liberty, and keep themſelves to rules and actions of juſtice, which the laws of God, and men preſcribe; from which theſe pittiful trepanners, and impoſtors ſought to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them, and oblige them to the contrary unawars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this be a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſuper ſuperſtition,</hi> to tremble at Gods word, and fearful judgments there recorded, let it be Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> portion; yet I muſt tell you, the divinity of Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> (your predeceſſour) hath provoked it: your riſing Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy would ſtrike you into a pannique fear, if Gods judgments ſhould break out, and not be pacified, but by the ſacrifice of ſome that ſtrive to advance it; pardon the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, the cloſer it comes, the clearer the conviction; whilſt you enjoy your braveries, poor Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> walketh in the Scriptures, and there he finds <q>
                  <hi>Iſrael</hi> by a pack of tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panners and impoſtors the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> by the baits of old cloaths, mouldy bread, and clouted ſhooes ſeduced into a Covenant againſt the Laws, and immunities of their Church and State, their King and people, <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the people had <hi>ſtulta facillitate,</hi> like Gudgeons ſimply ſwallowed it; within three days they feel the hook of their fraud and falſhood; the people reſume their reaſon, and quarrel with their Princes for not keeping to rules and actions of juſtice, but they in a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſuper ſuperſtition,</hi> fear to break their Oath, and carefully keep it, ſome hundreds of years, until <hi>Saul</hi> affected with reaſon, and the liberty of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in a well meant zeal breaks the Oath with the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> which breach God avengeth with a three years famine, whoſe wrath was onely expiated by hanging up ſeaven of the chief Violators of the Vow;</q> will your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119354:40"/> pleaſe once a day to take a turn in poor Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> walk, and deliver your ſoul from this <hi>pittiful paſſion</hi> if you can: however you fancy that fraud and force make void an Oath, your Brother Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> all Proteſtant Divines and Civilians, yea Popiſh Cafuiſts, will dictate to you other things; and little Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> deſireth to fear an Oath, and to tremble at every tendency to a breach of faith, with a jealous God; but judicious Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> can find a difference in the caſe of the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> from the caſe ſuppoſed by <hi>Mr. Crofton,</hi> and makes it a ſpecialty to that people, and that in theſe particulers. Firſt, <hi>The League with the Gibeonites was onely civil and ſecular, not Religious.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Made by the chief councel and authority of the Nation.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>It was of things within their power, as civil and ſecular,</hi> Fourthly, <hi>No injury to honeſt men.</hi> Fifthly; <hi>Though unadvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in prudence and policy of War, yet it was confirmed by God to puniſh unadviſedneſs, to preſerve leagues obtained by honeſt fraud; God had mercy for the</hi> Gibeonites, <hi>as leſs ſinners and more diſpoſed to fear, and repent.</hi> A moſt profound comment, but Sir, was the Covenant with the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> wholy <hi>civil and ſecular</hi> within their power, were they not the <hi>Hittites</hi> by Gods expreſs command to be deſtroyed? obſerve well the Catalogue, <hi>Deut</hi> 7.1, 2. <hi>Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d.</hi> 23.32. your predeceſſour Dr. <hi>Hall</hi> ſaith <hi>the ſentence of Death was paſſed againſt all the</hi> Cananites, <hi>and that</hi> Joſhuas <hi>heart was clear from any intention to make a league with the</hi> Canaanites, <hi>and enters a caution againſt it;</hi> So Sir, this was a League againſt the Laws of <hi>Iſrael</hi> given by God, ſomething more then civil; confederacy with the <hi>Canaanites</hi> was inhibited for the ſafety of their Religion, leſt they ſhould be ſeduced by them: but Sir where the matter is religious; will the caſe alter, or the Oath be any more void, then where it is civil? the validity or religion of the matter, whilſt either it may be juſt and lawful, according as the occaſion of the Covenant doth direct.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In that the Covenant was made <hi>by the chief Councel and authority of the Nation;</hi> it doth not relieve the fraud: who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they were, they were cozened by a peop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e who appeared to them what they were not; Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> will not fear to affirm
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119354:41"/> the Solemn League and Covenant was ſworn by the chief Councel and authority of <hi>England,</hi> though not compleat. But the queſtion is of the <hi>fraud</hi> by which any are deceived into an oath.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Was the oath of the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> no way to the <hi>injury of honeſt men?</hi> you will not ſtand to it; was it no injury to <hi>Iſrael</hi> to loſe <hi>four Cities</hi> out of their inheritance given them by the Lord? Was it no injury to be <hi>engaged in war,</hi> and to hazard their lives for a company of Trepanners and cheaters? (who ſhould have faln by their ſword, and D. <hi>Gaudens</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretative ſpirit would have left to fall by the ſword of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other) was it no injury to have ſuch a <hi>temptation to Idolatry,</hi> which God had charged to be removed? and ſuch torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing affliction, <hi>Canaanites,</hi> as <hi>pricks in their eyes, and thorn-in their ſide?</hi> If it were no injury to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> what was the <hi>well-meant zeal</hi> of <hi>Saul,</hi> on which his reſumed reaſon did perjuriouſly deſtroy the <hi>Gibeonites?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. But ſay you it was <hi>confirmed by God;</hi> how Sir, not by any <hi>poſt-fact,</hi> or <hi>immediate ſignification of his pleaſure,</hi> nor by the ſpecial diſpenſation of the High Prieſt; but meerly by the <hi>power and vertue of the oath</hi> fraudulently obtained; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> admitttng God did confirm it; an oath obtained by <hi>bone, fraud and ſurpriſal</hi> (as you phraſe it) if any can be honeſt, is eſtabliſhed, as permanently binding, and the breach of it is puniſhable by God: hath not then Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> cauſe to fear, or muſt his fear be <hi>ſuper ſuperſtition,</hi> or not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather Dr. <hi>Gaudens</hi> obſervation be <hi>ſuper-ignorant,</hi> and <hi>ſuper-arogant,</hi> in reputing the hypotheſis, illuſtrating the very pinch of the Queſtion, againſt the very utmoſt ſuppoſed ſtrength of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, the leaſt iſſue of <hi>weakneſs and exhauſted ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits;</hi> yet this is as ingenuous, as the next note is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 352.</note>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Croftons <hi>Oratory, reaſon, and civility, failes his zeal, whilſt he makes ſuch a reflection on his honorable Covenanting Maſters, comparing them to Colliers, whilſt they acted like Kings:</hi> Where Sir did Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> make this reflection? had he not aſſerted, and eſtabliſhed their authority? though to detect the weakneſs of your argument, he imagineth what you
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119354:41"/> fancy to make againſt the binding power of an Oath, and your ſelf is conſtrained to ſee the weakneſs thereof, but ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſity muſt be venting though with falſhood, yet this is as honeſt as the next is ſound [that not the <hi>honour and authority, but reaſon and religion, in a Parliament muſt be weighed</hi>] as if there were nothing in ſuch an aſſembly but what is common to men; if your prelacy may be thus meaſured, it will ſoon be found a vanity. But Sir, I muſt tell you, <hi>the man can be afraid, God will be angry for not keeping Oaths unlawfully made, and alſo for keeping and making unlawful Oaths, or lawful Oaths by unlawful means;</hi> but he cannot admit the <hi>ſay ſo</hi> of a Runa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gado, as an evidence againſt the Covenant; but affirmes it will be broken before your ſtrain of Rhetorick can make extirpation to ſignifie reformation of your Epiſcopacy; the firſt being ſo plain in the words, and unavoidable ſence of the Covenant, that it needs no <hi>Presbyterian ſtretch,</hi> (as you ſcurrilouſly taunt) <hi>or ſtrappado</hi> more then it will endure, the Antiphraſtical ſtrain of an <hi>apoſtate Presbyter,</hi> and Engliſh Prelate.</p>
            <p>But ſtay Sir, you crow before the Victory; Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> was ſo far from ſhewing <hi>his wit and art in this defence,</hi> (as you falſely ſay) by <hi>preſently withdrawing,</hi> that he who out of his ſally port, appeared to you like a little <hi>Mark,</hi> and <hi>picol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homo,</hi> did ſo little fear your firſt Granado, that he followed you to your trenches, and encountered your main body encamped in the <hi>Oxford reaſons,</hi> and yet keeps the field within reach of your Gunſhot, not fearing to have his brains beaten out by Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> his reaſon, if God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraines the Prelates <hi>high commiſſion batteries</hi> againſt the truth, which they can neither bear nor contradict: let me tell our Champion, notwithſtanding his renewed aſſault, he muſt go down to the <hi>Romiſh Phylyſtines</hi> to ſharpen his prelatical <hi>Pikes,</hi> before his battering rams can make impreſſion on the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and enter the garriſon of <hi>Presbyterial refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> impregnably guarded by Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> his Woolſacks, which the Doctors skill cannot remove.</p>
            <p>Having as he thought reinforced his battering Rame, he
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119354:42"/> proceeds to what he calleth his <hi>gulph between the Covenant, and its legality and ſanctity, the tumultuating terrours of thoſe times in which it was contrived, conceived and brought forth or imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed;</hi> as if ſanctity and legality, could not exiſt in tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous days.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">pag. 177.</note>And he tells you in this mud Mr. <hi>Crofton was afraid to ſtick, and therefore he nimbly skips over it.</hi> Oh Doctor, its an advantage to be light and little, know you not its an eminent piece of dexterity in a Souldier to purſue an enemy beaten from his battering Ram, into, and over thoſe gulfes to which for want of ſtrength or courage he retireth, hoping to eſcape; and it is an <hi>Iriſh</hi> mans excellency to tread Bogs without ſinking: yet Sir, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> skipped not ſo ſoon over your Gulph, but he took a turn with you in it, and told you; <hi>the tumults were not ſo great and loud, but that Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ep.</hi> p. 14.</note> 
               <hi>commiſſioners of the Kirk and Kingdome of</hi> Scotland, <hi>aſſembly of Divines, did ſolemnly ſeek divine direction, ſeriouſly debate and determine the Covenant;</hi> and to this you make no reply, but tell your <hi>Libeller</hi> a tale of a tub, and ſtory of mad <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> in 1641. two years before the Covenant. Here Sir, Mr <hi>Crofton</hi> by his little reaſon, leapt ſo nimbly, and light ſo ſtrongly on you, that in this point you cry quarter, and confeſs the <hi>autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity, due meaning and matter of the Covenant, is more to be conſidered then the tumults and arms,</hi> and how ſuſpicious ſoever it may render it, <hi>what is juſt and good is not null be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe tainted with tumults;</hi>
               <note place="margin">pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 179.</note> this is that which Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> urged, and inforced by the inſtance of <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> whoſe perjury was odious having ſworn the beſt termes the ſtraights of his condition would allow him, as your ſelf yields, and was all in which Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> made the parallel; So that Sir, in this gulph you are become my Priſoner: but perceiving you are not willing to be held, but think you have a Weapon yet to weild, <hi>viz. the injuſtice of the matter;</hi> I will give you fair quarter, and ſtill liberty to fight, and therefore will let you go on your promiſe that you will not provoke by vain brags, and like the <hi>Athenians</hi> fight
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119354:42"/> againſt <hi>Alexander, verbis tantum;</hi> but preſently joyn iſſue, and try your ſtrength and skill at your Quarter Staff, the unjuſt matter of the Covenant; at which if you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail not, you muſt yeild your conſcience to it, or be Gods Priſoner of wrath for ever.</p>
            <p>Let not Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> fight with an <hi>Iriſh</hi> man in a bog, for he will turn his tune, and make you hear him cry the next time, <hi>honeſt Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>is more valorous, and anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth againſt the novelty and partiality of the Covenant, that it is neither new nor partial;</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 180</note> but Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> muſt ſay Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> is wilfully blind to enquire the ſence, in which Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſaith it is not new and partial, whilſt he might read plainly in the <hi>Analepſis,</hi> the matter is not new or partial, and Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſaith that formes and circumſtances are as chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>new and partial</hi> as time, at whoſe command they are; but ſuppoſing the matter to have been <hi>new to England,</hi> if <hi>good,</hi> Mr, <hi>Crofton</hi> did ſay and ſtands to it, it binds, and the novelty bars not the obligation, nor can or dare Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> deny it, though he can eaſily ſay, Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> obſervations are a <hi>palpable Sophiſtry, and playing at bo-peep,</hi> which were theſe two.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſuppoſed contrariety of the Law is of no force to ſuch as conclude a power in the Parliament, to put a period to thoſe laws, and an oath againſt them upon the people.</hi> Secondly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Analep</hi> p. 12</note> 
               <hi>An oath ſworn by the Legiſlators, and body of the people, is the moſt full diſcharge of all contrary laws:</hi> Both theſe Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> (and all rational men) do beleive: but that Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> muſt confeſs the <hi>Laws did eſtabliſh the Hierarchy,</hi> is the ſophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal groundleſs inference of him, who knoweth Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> doth deny it, and therefore urged his reaſons againſt a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed contrariety; but give a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>relate an inch he will take an ell; ſuppoſitions are ſufficient ſupports to a man of fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, who all along his diſcourſe playeth at <hi>bo-peep,</hi> begging what muſt never be granted whilſt his <hi>noſe is between his eyes:</hi> Thus he ſuppoſes the two Houſes into a <hi>non entity, as to their ſupream legiſlative power,</hi> by the temper they were
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119354:43"/> then in, and the abſence of the King, though they were animated by an expreſs Statute Law, which ſome (upon grounds, and by reaſons (beyond the reach of Dr. <hi>Gauden,</hi> or little Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> to reſolve) have openly averred to <hi>continue them yet in being.</hi> And thus he profoundly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth, a Parliament ſwearing <hi>qua</hi> Parliament, in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt formality and profeſſions of their national capacity was a <hi>perſonal covenanting;</hi> and this he ſuppoſeth, for fear their act ſhould,<note place="margin">pag. 181.</note> as Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> affirmeth it doth, <hi>engage all the Nation and their poſterity,</hi> ſo long as it ſhall be a Nation, <hi>as Adam did all mankind:</hi> And all this he ſuppoſeth to make us ſuppoſe, <hi>extirpation</hi> ſignifieth <hi>erection</hi> of the Prelatical Hierarchy.</p>
            <p>But ſtay, the Doctor hath a requeſt; What is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? <hi>I muſt deſire Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>to bate me an ace, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated ſtroak at the Royal aſſent (by which he again laſheth the King, as did the Monks of</hi> Canterbury <hi>King</hi> Henry <hi>the Third) is not a grain of allowance to the Engliſh Covenanters.</hi> I perceive his Majeſties <hi>Oath</hi> troubleth him, as it well may, for it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a rivet will never be looſened; yet he might have ſeen ſome difference between the mention of it, and the <hi>laſhing of the Monks of Canterbury;</hi> for that theirs was a <hi>formal penance,</hi> by and in defence of <hi>Epiſcopal Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction;</hi> this is at moſt a Miniſterial admonition, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſtical conſideration; <hi>the ſmiting</hi> deſired by <hi>David,</hi> as that which <hi>would not break his head;</hi> nay would be a <hi>kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and excellent oyl,</hi> better then the Archiepiſcopal unction: But I cannot bate him one ace of it, it doth add <hi>many grains</hi> to the Covenant, though current before: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever his Royal aſſent was given in <hi>Scotland, poſt factum &amp; pactum;</hi> Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> doth affirm it hath made the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant <hi>National,</hi> as far as the King is capable of a <hi>nation<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al capacity;</hi> and the Ordinance requiring it hath in <hi>foro conſcientiae,</hi> the formality of a Law. This Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> hath affirmed in his <hi>Analepſis Anelapthe,</hi> Sect. 6. and ſhall affirm whenever a <hi>Parliament ſhall put the queſtion to him;</hi> and if his Brethren ſhall not do it, it will be for want of due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119354:43"/> or courage: Sure our Doctor will not make all <hi>foreinſecal acts,</hi> and <hi>poſt-facts</hi> void, and of no efficacy; if he do, we muſt determine a nullity on the late Parliament, and take heed of a treaty out of our own land. But all men know Dr. <hi>G.</hi> is ſingularly well skilled in politicks. He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds in page 182, and 183, and tells us,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>goes as boldly to look on the next Gorgon or Meduſa's head, by which the Doctor ſets forth the horrour of the Covenant,</hi> which in his <hi>Analyſis</hi> was the <hi>unbleſt conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which attended it;</hi> and ſo exclaims againſt the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, or rather acclaims the <hi>happy days</hi> they had before it, and expect when it is ſunk. To which Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſhall ſay no more, but ſure thoſe happy days were not <hi>real, but ſeeming;</hi> for the Covenant doth naturally make for what is <hi>truly good.</hi> And as for Mr. <hi>Croftons boldneſs,</hi> he ſhall ſay no more, but the <hi>righteous are as bold as a lion;</hi> it is not ſnakes or worms of a dead head, which can frighten him. But Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> his defence and reſcue of the Covenant from the odium of theſe horrible effects (as to a proper and natural cauſality) is a plain <hi>Gorgon</hi> to Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> ſtriking him dead, by the very aſpect thereof: For as one <hi>planet ſtruck,</hi> he mumbles out an heap of words hardly to be underſtood <hi>[How far the covenanting planet or ſpirit had its influence on theſe, I will not diſpute.]</hi> Which amounts to thus much, I will not anſwer Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> enquiry, <hi>are theſe effects the proper brood and natural iſſue of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant?</hi> For if I do, I muſt confeſs I fathered them very wrongfully. Sir you do well to ſhew your skill in an acclamatory and calumniatory flouriſh, and preſently with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw with an <hi>I will not diſpute.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His next defence is againſt Mr. <hi>Croftons wiſh he had been at his elbow,</hi> when he mentioned the bafflings of the Covenant,<note place="margin">pag. 184, 186, 180.</note> wherein he acknowledgeth the truth of all Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> in his <hi>Analepſis</hi> had urged to demonſtrate the odious falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of the <hi>Kings ſhiprack on the Covenant;</hi> though he moſt unworthily reproacheth the poor <hi>Scots,</hi> with the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119354:44"/> want (not of fidelity and good will, but) of ſucceſs, Gods only gift: And inſtead of vindicating his <hi>Analyſis,</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>Croftons Analepſis,</hi> noteth, <hi>The vote of non-addreſſes was paſſed by the covenanters;</hi> but he doth not, nor dare not ſay by <hi>vertue of the Covenant;</hi> nay himſelf calls the promoters thereof the <hi>Cromwellian Faction,</hi> and quotes Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> as if all the world knew not theſe to be <hi>perjured Anti-cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> And himſelf is conſtrained to profeſs <hi>Dr.</hi> Gauden <hi>is not ſo illogical and atheological as to infer a nulling of all things</hi> (and all muſt be nulled if any on that ground) <hi>by the apoſtacy and perverſneſs of ſome:</hi> And ſo ſubſcribes to Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> concluſion and argument. What he ſuggeſteth of the <hi>rational baflings of the Covenant by the</hi> Oxford <hi>reaſons;</hi> Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> hath fully conſidered, and cut him out work enough, to contradict his <hi>Analepſis Anelepthe.</hi> His ſuaſo's to <hi>loyalty</hi> are as needleſs to a <hi>ſincere covenanter,</hi> as thoſe of ſubjection to <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and content with its reſtitution, are groundleſs.</p>
            <p>The Doctors oppoſing <hi>contrary Oaths to the Covenant</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth not Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> who yet hath conſidered them in his <hi>Analepſis Analepthe,</hi> ſect. 3. pag. 97, 98, 99. and therefore Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſhall only enquire <hi>what principle of morality or ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice maketh the Hierarchy a royal and ſucceſſive duty to our Kings? Is this duty immediately impoſed by God, or preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by the laws of the land,</hi> any more then that an Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal perſon ſhall put on the Crown, <hi>Lands</hi> late unction in <hi>forma crucis,</hi> or the offering the <hi>Regalia</hi> upon the Altar? or was not this the <hi>voluntary aſſumpſit of the Engliſh Kings:</hi> will not a previous oath bar ſuch a <hi>voluntary aſſumpſit,</hi> counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand cuſtom, and at leaſt ſuſpend an execution of laws which bear any aſpect to ſuch an action?</p>
            <p>When the Doctor hath cleared theſe, there will be a better ſupport to Epiſcopacy, then they can yet receive.</p>
            <p>What the Doctor diſcourſeth about the divine, civil, and moral authority of Epiſcopacy, in page 191, 192, 193, 194, is <hi>a petitio principii,</hi> and noted before in his collected er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119354:44"/> to be proved before the Covenant or its obligation can be ſtrained by them.</p>
            <p>His eighth difficulty he tells us <hi>ſeems to preſs heavy on the Analeptiſt;</hi> which was but a bare <hi>ſeem ſo,</hi> and that in his own account, who dreams of an Almighty power in his words without reaſon: It being an empty ſwada, and inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating plea without any force, by the uncertainty of its ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, as Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> in his <hi>Analepſis</hi> page 19. hath obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; perſwading to a <hi>ſence</hi> which the words of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant will no way afford; in reſpect of which he tells us, <hi>Mr.</hi> Cr. <hi>after ſome ſhuffling and confuſion</hi> (which let the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der judge) <hi>definitively reſolves, that the Covenant expreſly bindes againſt the very form and fabrick of the late Hierarchy in</hi> England (<hi>eſtabliſhed by law</hi> (is by him added and fancied, for it was never believed nor aſſerted by Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi>) and <hi>not againſt its abuſes, exceſſes and defects only.</hi> This Mr. <hi>Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> did conclude as <hi>definitively,</hi> as became a Diſputant or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſt; yet not as if he had <hi>been in the boſom of the firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers of the Covenant;</hi> but as the grammatical conſtruction, logical reſolution, vulgar acceptation, and genuine inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the words (which D. <hi>Gauden</hi> doth not dare to be tried by, yet this muſt convince and guide the very Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers themſelves, if never ſo willing to ſhift off the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant) do aſſure him, and from this concluſion he ſhall not eaſily recede; nor doth the Doctor urge any thing that may drive him from it: for <hi>to his [good Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>if the exceſſes, abuſes and defects of our former Epiſcopal conſtitution be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, what can remain but the good] Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm</hi> that the ſame being a civil, humane frame, alterable at mens will, if covenanted againſt, cannot be retained; but <hi>corruptio unius,</hi> muſt be <hi>generatio alterius;</hi> the frame muſt be exti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pated, unleſs it be found <hi>neceſſary,</hi> not <hi>ratione ſubjecti;</hi> as you profoundly ſay, <hi>you muſt have your horſe before the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers know it is neceſſary for you,</hi> but <hi>neceſſitate praecepti,</hi> becauſe of Gods poſitive will and inſtitution; therefore you muſt ſpecifie what is in your Hierarchie, that is <hi>[not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a good notional, entitive, national, and poli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cal, but moral</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:119354:45"/> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical, having in it ſomething more Chriſtian, Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical, perfect and divine, then any other government,</hi> and prove it; for your words are too many to be beleived, though Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> can eaſily believe many of you will witneſs your <hi>couches, mannors, ſtates, honours, revenues,</hi> to be as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to you (though primitive Biſhops went without them) as is your horſe; ſooner then you will ſpecifie that <hi>goodneſs</hi> which muſt, and onely can expunge <hi>extirpation</hi> out of the Covenant, and Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> muſt tell the Doctor, <hi>reformation</hi> of the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> was not Covenanted, but <hi>extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation,</hi> and his Dictionary will teach him to know, what it means, yea and let his profound reaſon know that every <hi>ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beian fancy</hi> can differ between the fabrick of <hi>mans body</hi> built by God and nature, and not within humane power, (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in caſe of juſtice) to demoliſh, and <hi>a political frame,</hi> reared by humane art, invention and induſtry, at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to be thrown down ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in; and therefore he is not more ſcurrilous then fooliſh, in demanding whether [if Mr. <hi>Cr. diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes be cured it be not enough to juſtifie his Phyſitian, unleſs his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy be taken in peeces codled and pur-boyld</hi>] for that there is not more of difference between an humane body, and an <hi>Epiſcopal frame,</hi> then is between the <hi>faederated extirpation</hi> of the one, and <hi>Phyſical expurgation</hi> of the other, commending the Phyſitian; but the Reader cannot without high content (unto open laughter) obſerve the apt ſimilies which boyled out of our Doctors codled brain, who muſt not be angry if Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> adhaere to his concluſion, who is ready to meet the Doctor unto a fair diſpute about his Epiſcopacy; and hopes until he have thereby convinced him, he will reſtrain his <hi>rods of Iron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 201.</note> 
               <hi>and ſeverity of power</hi> which he imprecates; and give us leave to live in <hi>Old England,</hi> without the logick of their high commiſſion; for he ſhall find little Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> who cannot be vanquiſhed by a flood of words, will eaſily fall under the power of reaſon; though he with plainneſs out of conſcience, have declared his judgement, not as the Doctor fancyeth on a <hi>preſumption of his Majeſties indulgence,</hi> whoſe judgment expreſſed and declared for
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119354:45"/> Epiſcopacy, may be a reaſon for ſubmiſſion negative, by non reſiſtance, not of conviction, or ſinful ſuſpenſion, or ſilencing of his judgment in his place, as with the modeſty and moderation, ſo the confidence of a Miniſter, <hi>for I fear God:</hi> but to proceed</p>
            <p>The Doctor tells us, having <hi>ſtrapped the ſweetneſs of Mr.</hi> Crofton (after which for its reaſon and ſobriety, truth and ſeriouſneſs, give me leave to ſay Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> needs not be aſhamed to lick his lips) he proceeds to his ninth <hi>reflection; the Covenant of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>the ten Commandements;</hi> to which Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> took exceptions in his <hi>Analepſis</hi> pag. 20. and tells us, that Mr. <hi>Crofton runs a calmer, but not clearer ſtream then the Libeller</hi> (and ſo the Doctor ſets up his own ſhadow to fight withal) <hi>and deſires a demonſtration to prove,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 257.</note> 
               <hi>that one compleat and grand Covenant given of God to the Jews, was the onely rule and dictate of what matter they ſhould Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;</hi> to which he inſultingly anſwers, as indeed to a frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous queſtion, <hi>he may as well look for a demonſtration to prove there is but one God, one true Religion, and one Sun in the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament,</hi> judiciouſly fought Doctor, muſt you not be hum'd; is Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſo little, you cannot ſee or diſtinguiſh him from your Umbra? I pray you where doth Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire this in his <hi>Analepſis,</hi> which onely you encounter? he did determine and agree to this, your grave eyes are dim, and Epiſcopal ſpectacles made at <hi>Rome</hi> duſty, otherwiſe you would have read true Engliſh. Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> his deſire to the Doctor was, <hi>to demonſtrate that the law of</hi> Moſes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Analep.</hi> p. 20.</note> 
               <hi>or Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in</hi> Horeb, was NOT ONELY the RULE and DICTATE of what MATTER (can you ſee it Sir) <hi>they ſhould Covenant, but the</hi> EXPRESSE COVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NANT, <hi>or did conſiſt in the</hi> EXACT RECITAL <hi>and</hi> REPETITION <hi>of the law or ten Commandements, ſo as that they never</hi> VARIED <hi>or</hi> ALTERED (Sir I would help your eye ſight) <hi>the ſame.</hi> Do not theſe words much agree with that you have falſely fathered on Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> his deſire? is this the <hi>praxis</hi> of your profound noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by which you would ſave the credit of your <hi>liturgy</hi> from
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119354:46"/> beginning its Rubrick with a <hi>lye,</hi> defending the <hi>ſameneſs of the words,</hi> by a ſuppoſed <hi>ſoundneſs of the ſenſe?</hi> But what ſay you yet to Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> his demand? were the Jews tied to thoſe words on no occaſion to vary them? that theſe did <hi>rule and limit their matter</hi> is agreed; but you dare not affirm they were tied to the <hi>order and number of words;</hi> yet on this ſcore you quarrel with the Covenant, and by a childiſh fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, caſt the words into 666, as if that number was as fatal to every thing, as it is to Papal, Prelatical Hierarchy; and will needs ſuppoſe, <hi>to live according to the word of God, and laws of the land,</hi> to be a ſufficient form for all Oaths or Covenants on any occaſion? but who made Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> the Dictator of the words, which ſhould be the <hi>ſame</hi> in all Covenants? theſe are not the words of <hi>Moſes, or Covenant in Horeb.</hi> I may ſir, come into your Dioceſs, and need your licenſe; and I will covenant with you to live <hi>according to the word of God and laws of the land:</hi> I hope you will require no other canonical oath, or ſubſcription. Sir, declare this, and ſtand to it, and you ſhall be the beſt Biſhop, and have your Dioceſſes ſtored with the beſt Miniſters in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Doctor having thus ſolidly defended his profound no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the one Covenant in the Old Teſtament, he proceeds to eſtabliſh his <hi>one baptiſmal covenant in the New:</hi> the man profeſſeth much to <hi>unity,</hi> and fondly dreams of nothing but <hi>unites,</hi> even of words and humane expreſſions, as if tens, or hundreds, or thouſands in a covenant were utterly Antia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmetical and Antichriſtian, againſt the rule of Nature and Scripture.</p>
            <p>Herein having ſufficiently ſcolded his Anatomiſt, he courts Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> with ſuch <hi>juſtice and civility</hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he can afford, which is comparatively very much, and tells us,</p>
            <p>Mr. Cr. <hi>inſtead of proving the Covenant to be ratified by any precept in the New Teſtament, or examples of any Chriſtians in ſucceeding ages; flieth to juſtifie it, by the dictates and diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Old Teſtament, by politick arts befitting any people, or Church National.</hi> But the Doctor ſhould have been ſo <hi>juſt and civil,</hi> as to have obſerved Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> diſtinctions
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119354:46"/> between the <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>circumſtances</hi> of the Covenant; how he concluded in his <hi>Analepſis,</hi> that the <q>New Teſtament di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth us as Chriſtians, but in Acts that pertain to us as a Kingdom, or Church national, it leaveth us to the dictates of Nature, and the diſcoveries of the Old Teſtament.</q> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Doctor hath unjuſtly couched the one, he doth not, he dares not contradict the other; but inferreth truly <hi>on the ſame grounds, that ſo much by him and others decried</hi> (oath he intends) <hi>with</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in it, which excluded Popery, and confirmed the already legal, and ſettled Epiſcopacy of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>had been as lawful and ſacred as this Covenant; and in ſome reſpect more allowable, becauſe it diſſeiſed no man of his free-hold or Eſtate.</hi> But ſure the Doctor runs too faſt, and now reckons without his hoſt, and by an after reckoning will find his miſtake, in theſe three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Epiſcopacy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> was <hi>legal, and already ſettled,</hi> which we have before charged as his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror; and by a <hi>petitio principii</hi> he all along builds upon it; but muſt go to the Temple, and beg ſome help of the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers to prove <hi>Id quod erat demonſtrandum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Admitting the dictates of Nature, and diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Old Teſtament to direct the circumſtances of an Oath; that the <hi>Oath with</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in it, will be found as lawful and ſacred as the Covenant,</hi> is a meer <hi>non ſequitur:</hi> For the dictates of nature do authorize any perſon to vow in his <hi>place, calling, and capacity to endeavour the extirpation of what he conceiveth or experienceth evil;</hi> but that Oath bindeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>giving conſent to alter,</hi> what on after conviction may appear, not only al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erable at the pleaſure of the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, to whom our conſent muſt be ſubject; but in it ſelf <hi>hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tful, yea ſinful;</hi> and ſo the ſubſerviency of the will to the underſtanding is ſuperſeded by an Oath. Again, the dictates of nature, and diſcoveries of the Old Teſtament do direct <hi>the matter of an oath to be expreſſed with all certainty and clearneſs;</hi> and the Covenant doth accordingly expreſs all the particulars covenanted; but this oath is ſo far from <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the matter ſworn,</hi> that it binds the conſcience to an
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119354:47"/> 
               <hi>&amp; caetera</hi> of infinite extenſion, and boreth a paſſage into a mans conſcience for whatſoever ſhall be fathered upon, and ſaid to be intended in the <hi>&amp; caetera;</hi> which might be at leaſt <hi>Moneks and Abbeys,</hi> no leſs legal and eſtabliſhed then this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy. Again, the dictates of Nature, and diſcoveries of the Old Teſtament do direct, the National tie of an oath to be ſtamped by the <hi>collective body of the Nation,</hi> as was the Covenant, but not the Oath <hi>&amp; caetera,</hi> which was by a picked, pack'd Convocation, without any authority, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical or civil, to impoſe or preſcribe an Oath upon the Subjects: Nay, if we give the Doctor his fancy, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Prelates <hi>Juſtices of the Peace,</hi> they run into a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire, who bind the Subject to the good behaviour by an oath not directed by Law.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That the Oath of the <hi>&amp; caetera diſſeiſed no honeſt man of his freehold or eſtate:</hi> I muſt underſtand him in his conſequences of it, as he doth the Covenant; and then I muſt enquire what it means, that the <hi>Miniſter, or beneficed, dignified perſon, refuſing this Oath, after one moneths conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſhall be ſuſpended</hi> ab officio, <hi>after two moneths conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> a beneficio, <hi>after three months conſideration ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of all promotion, and execution of his function:</hi> Sure the Doctor is as well ſtudied in the Canons of 1640. as the Covenant 1643. Is not a Benefice the Miniſters <hi>freehold and eſtate,</hi> as much as the Biſhoprick is the Biſhops? or are the ſuſpenſion <hi>a beneficio,</hi> yea deprivation no <hi>diſſeiſure of the ſame?</hi> and ſuſpenſion, <hi>ab officio,</hi> no <hi>injuſtice and impiety?</hi> Sir, Your ſecond thoughts will ſure ſink your parallel, and conſequence; and your reply will be found more light and ſhufling then Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Queries, which anſwer themſelves by way of expoſtulation,<note place="margin">Pag. 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> proving againſt Dr. <hi>Gaudens</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, that the <hi>New Teſtament is not the onely rule which muſt direct the Nationalty, or other circumſtances of a Covenant determinable by the light of nature:</hi> As to the queſtion you pretend not anſwered, it is but now ſtarted, and is not in your <hi>Analyſis, [What erigents in religion did ever put any Church or Chriſtian Subjects upon ſuch a way of publick cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119354:47"/> &amp;c.</hi> Yet by your leave Sir, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> did ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which may anſwer it: Find you a Church or Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian people, and erigents of Religion, <hi>ſo capacitated</hi> for nature, number, quality, and juſt authority, <hi>Analepſis</hi> p. 22. and Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> will finde ſuch a <hi>Covenant?</hi> untill then ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Query, <hi>Muſt we enquire onely what hath been done in the Chriſtian Churches, to do that and no more, without regarding what may be done; the condition of the Church ſo requiring.</hi> And ſtudy Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> his <hi>Analepſis Anelephthe,</hi> ſect. 3.</p>
            <p>The Doctor hath not more <hi>ſhufled</hi> about Mr. Croſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing expoſtulation, then he <hi>poorly ſhifts</hi> off his vindication and reſcue of the Covenant from the odium of the <hi>Ligue de Saint in France,</hi> which he (as writing after his friends <hi>John Ruſſels</hi> copy) in his margin, with a notorious falſhood calls Mr. <hi>Croftons patte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> and in the Text upbraidingly crieth out, Mr. <hi>Crofton not like an Eagle, but a meaner bird, ſtoops to feed</hi> on that <hi>long ago dead and noyſom carkaſs, the holy League in France, as a very exemplary parellel for his holy Covenant.</hi> Doctor, are not you aſhamed to father the Brats of your own fancy on Mr: <hi>Crofton.</hi> This parellel is your own baſtard, and <hi>quod fieri non debuit, factum valet;</hi> you begot it you muſt keep it: Did not you in your <hi>Analyſis</hi> labour to make the Covenant odious by this example? Doth Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> own or allow this <hi>League de Saint?</hi> Nay doth he not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn it? onely ſtave off the odious reflection deſigned by an envious Renegado and Apoſtate.</p>
            <p>I pray Sir, read Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> words again, and ſee whether Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> feed on this as a <hi>pattern,</hi> on only a fence againſt your aſſault made by it: May not the <hi>League de Saint, and Oath</hi> &amp; caetera <hi>in England,</hi> (there is your parallel Dr.) <hi>though SINF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L IN THE MATTER</hi> (Sir rub your Romiſh ſpectacles) <hi>be good ſpurs and directions in Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an policy? may not the ſame means</hi> (as abſtracted from the matter) <hi>be uſed to corroborate true Religion and Reformation? why may not Popiſh policy teach Proteſtants to combine by Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant?</hi> Reverend Sir, read my ridle, <hi>Out of the eater came
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119354:48"/> forth meat, and out of the ſtrong came forth ſweetneſs.</hi> Sir was not Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> herein like an Eagle on the horns of an Hart, ſcattering that duſt in your eyes, that cauſed you to throw your ſelf into the praecipice of falſe accuſation? or appear, not you, like the envious and cruel <hi>Vulture,</hi> killed by the oyl of Roſes, which ſprang and grew out of the dung of a noyſom dead carkaſs. O man be honeſt though a Prelate.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">p. 242, 243.</note>The Doctor tells us, <hi>Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>ſtranges at Dr.</hi> Gauden, <hi>not finding the like lineaments in the Covenant, as in the baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Covenant,</hi> you are again miſtaken Doctor, for Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> ſtranged at <hi>the tranſport of ſo grave and ſerious a Divine, to oppoſe the baptiſmal Covenant to this,</hi> Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> did eaſily admit they were <hi>diſparata,</hi> but not <hi>oppoſita contraria:</hi> this was Dr. <hi>Gaudens</hi> work to demonſtrate, if you will believe him; he tells us the <hi>inconſiſtency is plain, and fully explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Dr. Gauden,</hi> where or how? why, <hi>if it obligeth to injuſtice, oppreſſion, ſedition, ſacriledge, ſchiſme, and Iliades of miſerable innovations, at this rate it will appear</hi> but <hi>ifs</hi> or <hi>ands,</hi> are no proofs or demonſtrations; if they were I would ſoon prove your <hi>Prelacy</hi> a <hi>Papacy,</hi> and ſtore your Table with Epiſcopal plenties and dainties, <hi>for if the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments fall, we ſhall catch Larks;</hi> this way of diſputing is apparently Jeſuitical, Machiavilian and barbarous, ſo far from <hi>baptiſmal,</hi> that it is plainly <hi>irrational;</hi> what good, duty, Juſtice, morality, or Religion may not be ruined, if a mans fancyed <hi>if,</hi> be reaſon enough againſt it, if the Biſhoprick of <hi>Exeter</hi> be unjuſtly held by Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> from Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> or <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells</hi> from <hi>D. B.</hi> it is unjuſt and ſacrilegious, and they are both bound to abandon their places, and avoid their Seats, and to reſtore them, how like you the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? is it not very Logical and Cogent? Sir draw up a poſitive charge, and prove it, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> will ſtand to it, <hi>that he will renounce the Covenant,</hi> in the mean time let me de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Doctor, to take a view of the parallel between this and the baptiſmal vow or covenant, propoſed by Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> in his <hi>Analepſis Analephthe Sect.</hi> 3. pag. 35. and avoid it if
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119354:48"/> he can, onely take notice it is the <hi>honeſty of the Covenant, not all Covenanters,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> pleads with confidence, he confeſſeth many <hi>cups</hi> may be found in his brethrens ſacks, but not in any <hi>Article of the Covenant,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Gaudens</hi> multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed reiterated <hi>Ifs,</hi> do make me confident of <hi>Benjamins innocency,</hi> and apt to think things unknown are thruſt upon them; but not from ſo pious a principle, and to ſo chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table an end, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> acted from and aimed at: but truely Doctor, it is a Sophiſtical evaſion to confound things and perſons in a <hi>diſpute,</hi> but this the learned Doctor doth decline as to <hi>the name, office, degree, order and Authority of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop in Scripture,</hi> Sir do you not now appear a greater dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour then little Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 249.</note> who rationally urged his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, and is no way affraid or unwilling in this caſe to try a turn with Dr. <hi>John Gauden</hi> on the queſtions before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, who yet will hold to his ingenuous agnition, which ſo much pleaſeth you, <hi>viz. that the Covenant is not levelled againſt any real excellency in the Biſhops</hi> (which is all that Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> agnifed,<note place="margin">Analep. Pag. 25.</note> though you according to your uſual falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood do add, <hi>authority, eſtate and honour,</hi>) which Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> noted to be unwarrantable, <hi>neither to be aſſumed by them, nor attributed to them,</hi> and Sir I muſt tell you, <hi>ruine and extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the frame of the <hi>Engliſh Hierarchy,</hi> doth no way interfere with the <hi>preſervation and eſteem</hi> of any real excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency in Biſhops but that Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> may be ready and bound (if in a capacity) to vail that <hi>pompous worldly State, and wicked ſuperiority, which Church Governours had obtained;</hi> a note or inſtance of which he gave in <hi>Lawn ſleeves,</hi> no more puerile or <hi>ſcurrilous,</hi> nor <hi>unbeſeeming a Scholar, or Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> then the baſeneſs and contemptible inferiority of Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, was by you marked out, <hi>in a black coat,</hi> to which that was oppoſed, is below the ſobriety <hi>of a man,</hi> the humility of a <hi>Primus Presbyter,</hi> and reverence of a Chriſtian to the pooreſt meaneſt Miniſter of Chriſt; and ſpeaks your prelatical Pride, much more then your <hi>Rochet and Chymer ſets out your pomp,</hi> which my baptiſme binds againſt; and will engage the <hi>Boanergeſſes</hi> of God to thunder out terrour
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119354:49"/> againſt Covenant breaking? which you account a <hi>weak Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſh flaſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 249, 251.</note> yet will not be quenched by your <hi>firſt demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> or this <hi>reply,</hi> by your judicious ſelf, proclaimed <hi>rational, and conſcientious, though to all men beſide, proud, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, ridiculous, weak,</hi> and wicked, whilſt Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſeeketh not to ſtrain the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ovenant beyond its own <hi>juſt and ingenuous reſolution,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag 251.</note> 
               <hi>ſence, operation, influence and obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> conſenting to, and rejoycing in, its <hi>limitation to the Word of God, and dutys of our places and callings,</hi> by which Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> is reſolved he will be judged, and is in himſelf aſſured, that King and Kingdome accordingly keeping their Covenant, the controverted Epiſcopacy will be at an end, and the commiſſion of our preſent Prelate Juſtices expired and uſeleſs; covenanters by their good <hi>behaviour,</hi> proving the <hi>ſolemn League and Covenant</hi> to be, as indeed it is <hi>Berith Anti-Baall,</hi> which Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> blaſphemouſly denominateth <hi>Baal Berith,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> is nor ſhall no way be <hi>ſhye of retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection how or by whom, to what or in what ſence it binds, and the rationality of its obligation,</hi> all which he hath ſeriouſly conſidered in an oppoſition to the <hi>Oxford Reaſons,</hi> to which the Doctor ſo often retireth, as he may ſee in my <hi>Analepſis Anelephthe,</hi> pag. 265.</p>
            <p>We have ſeen the Doctors ſtrength in the defence of his <hi>indirect anſwer,</hi> and conſideration of the Covenant, which being done, he proceeds to reinforce his <hi>direct anſwer,</hi> and <hi>Goliah</hi> like, being encouraged by the ſtature of little Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> not taking notice of his ſtone and ſling, he triumphantly enters, and tauntingly crieth, <hi>Mr.</hi> Croftons <hi>fear (good man) is leſt Dr.</hi> Gaudens <hi>down right blows, may quite break in ſunder,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 273, 274.</note> 
               <hi>whatever may be of ſacred bond in the Covenant;</hi> the Reader that well regardeth the ſtrength of his book, cannot but with Laughter ſay, there was <hi>great cauſe of fear,</hi> but the beſt is, it was but a fear, and ſo on paſt, for in the next aſſault Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> is victor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Croftons <hi>note, that the paucity of the Covenanters doth not diſcharge its obligation, is true;</hi> had not Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> much cauſe of fear and trouble? I but in <hi>making Dr.</hi> Gauden one
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119354:49"/> 
               <hi>of the number, Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>reckoned without his hoſt;</hi> when that appears, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> will cry <hi>true;</hi> but the Doctor doth not, dare not deny he ſware it: which if he ſhould, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> can tell who heard him preanh upon the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, acd ſaw him in the Pulpit at <hi>Bocking</hi> lift up his hand, and ſwear it: He doth indeed, like a <hi>ſhifting runnegado,</hi> labour to darken the act which retorts on his conſcience, in his now eſtate, and tell us, <hi>he never took an oath, but thoſe appointed by Law;</hi> he might reckon the Covenant to be of this nature, for the <hi>Authority of Parliament is by the Petition of Right</hi> the legal appointment of an Oath: He tells us a large ſtory how he did <hi>ſenſe the Covenant,</hi> and with what <hi>nonſenſe</hi> he did approve it, underſtanding <hi>Extirpation</hi> to ſignifie <hi>Reformation,</hi> and ſo by general <hi>ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voes</hi> and <hi>reſtrictions,</hi> he cheated others and himſelf, which Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> hath detected in his <hi>Review of Reordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> pag. 35. but may as ſoon acquit his ſoul from the bond, as make the words of the Covenant bear his ſence; let him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>now equivocation in an Oath, is no way ſhort of <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> and <hi>Saphira's lie unto the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> it is much pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience that the puniſhment hath not yet proclaimed it; The Lord grant it may lead unto repentance. He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>is apt to think the Covenant national</hi> (not as in a Presbyterian illegal <hi>&amp; caetera</hi> ſence, which the Doctor adds, but will not alter the caſe, the ſence being no way conſiderable to the Nationalty of it, but in any ſence) <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies as little as other mens thoughts to the contrary.</hi> But good Sir, weigh the Reaſons brought by Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> and his anſwer to what you have objected as to the troubles of the Houſes, abſence of ſome members, or the like, in <hi>Analepſis Anelepthe;</hi> ſect. 6. which had you read, would have ſaved, or encreaſed your labour in your Reply. Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> muſt not ſhufle that into this book, and therefore ſhall make bold to tell you, <hi>His ſacred Majeſty and the Kingdom muſt ſubmit to the plain and literal ſence thereof,</hi> though it ſeem as <hi>ſowre grapes,</hi> unleſs we will by Gods wrath <hi>ſet our own and childrens teeth
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119354:50"/> on edge;</hi> for the capacity of the Covenanters doth extend the obligation. But</p>
            <p>The Doctor <hi>judgeth an oath extorted by fear to a mans pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate damage doth binde;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag 279.</note> ſure he means a <hi>proper damage;</hi> for I cannot think he will in cool blood deny the Parents oath to the damage of the family; or progenitors in a corporation, to the damage of ſucceſſors; or Governours to the damage of the people or Subjects to binde, becauſe theſe are <hi>ſui juris;</hi> and then he yeilds as much as I deſire, to ſhut out, yea thruſt out and pluck up his Epiſcopacy, and in this point we ſhall agree. But now he ſhufles to defend his ſtrange no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of morality; Of which</p>
            <p>The firſt is, <hi>Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>carps at the Doctors owning the bonds of God, which are moral, to have in them ſufficient and indiſpenſable obligations of the ſoul to all duty.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> By your leave Doctor this is falſe: Mr. <hi>Croftons wonder</hi> was at the Doctors <hi>Antitheſis of the words</hi> of a Covenant, <hi>to Reaſon, Juſtice, Truth, Religion, Duty:</hi> which he never denied to tye <hi>as well</hi> as Oaths, but not <hi>as much,</hi> muchleſs more; as your <hi>iron adamantine bonds of Reaſon, moralitie,</hi> &amp;c. oppoſed to the <hi>cords and withs of Oaths,</hi> did ſuggeſt in your <hi>Analyſis;</hi> but now indeed you confeſs that Oaths do harden and <hi>ſoder theſe moral chains unto a greater toughneſs;</hi> which was the thing Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> aſſerted in his <hi>Analepſis:</hi> I confeſs retraction of error is the beſt vindication; but you ſhould be ingenuous, and do it without ſhufling, and ſuggeſting a falſhood againſt your Antagoniſt: But Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> will grant to you, that new Covenants cannot <hi>abſolve or abrogate old lawful Oaths;</hi> but what it may do <hi>to laws</hi> I muſt diſpute, when done by Legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators, I affirm it to be the fulleſt repeal: But if I admit it, it will not ſecure your Biſhops <hi>Lands, Honor, Office, or Authority,</hi> until you have proved your Epiſcopacy to be eſtabliſhed by law, which may be done by an act of the next Parliament, if the long Parliament be not in being, as hath been affirmed; though it is out of Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> way to determine; and he is well adviſed by the Doctor to let <hi>wiſe men ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage</hi> affairs, as is but reaſon; for no doubt <hi>wiſemen</hi> will hear and weigh the doubts of the <hi>meaneſt men,</hi> the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119354:50"/> of which, proud Prelates think to be <hi>pragma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Sir, Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> thinks whatever <hi>Jepthas</hi> vow was, <hi>it</hi> was <hi>literally fulfilled;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 281,</note> and I hope Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> will not aſſert a Popiſh <hi>commutation</hi> of an Oath; and the Popiſh Caſuiſts conclude, <hi>Non poſſe promiſſum commutari in evidenter pejus;</hi> an oath may not be changed for the worſe: And Sir, if he vowed (which I will not conclude) his daughters life, I think her <hi>virgin liberty</hi> to be leſs and worſe. And Dr. <hi>Saunderſon</hi> determineth <hi>Vinculum juramenti non poſſe remitti vel ſolvi ex parte per commutationem, ſine conſenſu partium omnium:</hi> The exchange muſt be by conſent of all parties concerned: But the Scripture mentioneth not <hi>Gods con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> nor <hi>Jeptha's exchange;</hi> what he vowed that he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: For <hi>ubi lex non diſtinguit, non eſt diſtinguen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His ſecond ſuggeſtion was, <hi>That a Covenant cannot bind a man by the power of his own imagination, Analyſis,</hi> p. 15. To this Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> excepted in his <hi>Analepſis,</hi> pag. 19. and he replys <hi>It is true, that imagination or meer preſumption, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not binde, contrary to what in Reaſon, Juſtice, Law and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion you owe to another.</hi> But Doctor,<note place="margin">Pag. 282, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> have you not again run from your own ſecond ſuggeſtion? How long will you ſhufle? your ſuggeſtion was of <hi>any Covenant,</hi> your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of <hi>Covenants to the wrong of others;</hi> and therefore you add, <hi>the meaſure of an erroneous conſcience may bind to things of our own injury;</hi> but not otherwiſe; your ſuggeſtion oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a mans own <hi>imagination</hi> to <hi>others interpretation;</hi> your reply oppoſeth <hi>our own to others wrong;</hi> where ſhall we hold you? can Jeſuitiſm it ſelf be more ſubtile and ſophiſtical? I pray come to the queſtion, doth an erroneous conſcience binde, and doth it univerſally bind? I have ſworn, and do ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine it is no wrong to my neighbour; though I ought to be the better informed by right reaſon, and rules of juſtice; yet whilſt in my error, muſt I conſcienciouſly wrong my neighbour, or captivate my conſcience by Dr. <hi>G.</hi> ſay ſo? you profeſs Sir to be beſt in a particular caſe; I pray you reſolve
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119354:51"/> it clearly and plainly. You boaſt of this ſecond ſuggeſtion, as having as much <hi>ſtrength as I confeſs your next hath;</hi> when indeed you have made it the ſame; and inſtead of defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſecond, you have ſpoken <hi>the third in a ſecond book;</hi> profound diſputing! I will admit <hi>this ſtrength,</hi> and yet your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred <hi>ſafety of your Epiſcopacy</hi> (which I ſtand by is no wrong to remove) is a plain <hi>non ſequitur;</hi> grounded on your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>petitio prinipii;</hi> for I muſt enquire what is the <hi>right of Epiſcopacy?</hi> may not the power that founded Prelacy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate it? Is it not <hi>ſui juris?</hi> May not Epiſcopacy be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed without wrong, as well particular Biſhopricks be given to lay perſons for two, three, four, five, ten, fifteen, twenty, thirty years together, and the See kept vacant? tell us was the Church ſo long injured? May not Engliſh authority aboliſh Prelacy, with as little wrong as <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> did? I know my <hi>horſe and ſadle, wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 183.</note> 
               <hi>houſe and lands;</hi> but yet I <hi>know not the pretended right of Epiſcopacy;</hi> and conceive there is ſome difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween perſonal and political right: When God ſtirreth up the Kings heart to con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ider, and raiſeth up an Engliſh Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to take notice of, they will know <hi>their right in and over Epiſcopacy,</hi> and make Biſhops know they are their <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, horſe and ſaddle,</hi> to be diſpoſed at their pleaſure, without complaint of wrong. Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> ſhall freely truſt them to it, and God to give them thereunto hearts of wiſdom, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and courage.</p>
            <p>The Doctors aſſertion more then his judgement, leads him to an exclamation, <hi>Mr.</hi> Croftons <hi>next paragraph is a factious quaerie, not worth any ſober mans Reply.</hi> It is well Sir, it is not <hi>ſeditious;</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4</note> for many Deputy Lieutenants are become ſo far the Biſhops ſlaves and Conſtables, as to reſolve the peace and order of the Kingdom into owning the Biſhops, and make the contrary <hi>ſedition?</hi> But Sir, what is the Query? I preſume it toucheth the Prelates copy-hold; you cry ſo of <hi>faction,</hi> whether the Statute <hi>of</hi> 17. <hi>Caroli hath not cut ſhort their horns?</hi> And you tell us of a Councellor who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in the negative. Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> knows him not, but hath
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119354:51"/> heard of a Convention of Prelates, who on advice with Councel diſcerned the affirmative, and received the ſilence of the learned in the Law to their enquiry; you may if you pleaſe take ſilence for conſent: I am prone to think Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> knows this ſtory to be true, and that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor who concluded for <hi>Epiſcopal Juriſdiction,</hi> did deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it could not be executed <hi>without the Kings commiſſion,</hi> barred by the Statute of 17 <hi>Caroli primi.</hi> But this was fit for the Doctor to tell.</p>
            <p>The Doctors next fling is at Mr. <hi>Croftons fear of National perjury;</hi> before conſidered,<note place="margin">pag. 185.</note> and on good grounds will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince men it is not cauſeleſs: Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> would be glad to ſee how the Nation will eſcape it; but he will meet Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> on any ground, with his Majeſties leave to maintain the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant, is a full and formal and National obligation.</hi> This paſt</p>
            <p>He findes himſelf grieved that Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi> chargeth Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to have <hi>brought reformation to a palpable retrogradation;</hi> but like a ſubtil Sophiſter, he coucheth Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative inſtances of the returned Liturgy, moſt conform to the Romiſh Maſs book; Incloſed-in-Altars, or railed Communion-Tables, Croſſes, Surplices, Popiſh Oblations, and other ſuperſtitious Rites; to ſay nothing of prophaned Sabbaths by biſhops <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arding; ſuppreſſing pious, painful Preachers thruſt out, and prophane, drunken deboiſt, cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical, Common-prayer-book men forced in, whereſoever a Biſhops power can reach; all which are read in ſuch legible characters that all can run and read them: It may be this is the Reformation deſired by our Prelates and amongſt others by Dr. <hi>G.</hi> If ſo I have done them wrong, they do not <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trograde it,</hi> but drive it on, like <hi>Phaeton</hi> to the apparent ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of <hi>Charls</hi> his wain. If you ſay this is <hi>rude Rhetorick,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it is <hi>plain Engliſh:</hi> As for bringing <hi>horſes to Church,</hi> it is as much Mr. <hi>Croftons reformation,</hi> as Biſhops Pallaces and holineſs of Church, Chancels, or other places, which it is known he hath equally oppoſed, and loveth no leſs then pulling down <hi>croſſes</hi> and ſetting up <hi>weathercock Covenanters,</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:119354:52"/> as Biſhops or Prieſts in the Church; let what will ſtand on the ſteeple, theſe will turn with every wind.</p>
            <p>His next fret is, at Mr. <hi>Crofton? wiping his noſe on the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops lawn ſleeves;</hi> as mannerly Sir, as with his nailes at <hi>Exeter</hi> to tear them, for Linnen is fit for that uſe, eſpecially when black becomes deſpicable by it; you now profeſs <hi>love and eſteem</hi> for Presbyters; but when you taught the people to know them but as their equals and inferiours, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in black coats, <hi>Analyſis,</hi> pag. 17. you expoſed them to contempt.</p>
            <p>His laſt work is to explain himſelf, concerning <hi>the good,</hi> againſt which, his <hi>Analyſis</hi> urged, <hi>no Oath could bind,</hi> the man is become a Biſhop, it is below him to learn, at leaſt to let the world ſee, that a little deſpicable Presbyter is to him an <hi>inſtructor,</hi> who never affected to be a <hi>dictatour,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in an angry ſtile he muſt correct his errour, and tell us <hi>When Dr.</hi> Gauden <hi>affirmed an Oath cannot bind againſt what is in nature good, he meant, ſo far onely as that good may be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally neceſſary for him and his:</hi> But Sir that we may yet know your meaning, I ſhould enquire what you mean by <hi>morally neceſſary,</hi> when Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> tells you, Epiſcopacy muſt not be reſtored againſt the Covenant, <hi>though good, unleſs found neceſſary</hi> you put the caſe of your good horſe <hi>neceſſary for you;</hi> and truely Sir, I cannot ſee any more <hi>moral neceſſity</hi> in your horſe, then your <hi>Epiſcopal fines of Gold and ſilver,</hi> and other things that may be barred by an Oath, you are the moſt unhappy Maſter of words, that I have met with, to darken your meaning <hi>by declaring what you mean.</hi> Sir I do ſay all good, not good by <hi>the neceſſity of nature, or divine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept,</hi> but at mans choice to take or refuſe, in order to the <hi>bene eſſe</hi> of him or his, may be concluded by an Oath, and charity commands me to think, this is that you would ſay you meant (though you ſhot far wide) in your <hi>Analyſis,</hi> if your many words, and whirling tongue would let your mind regularly dictate its expreſſions.</p>
            <p>We have ſeen the ſtrength of Dr. <hi>Gaudens Argumentation,</hi> which truely I cannot commend; though I think an errour
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119354:52"/> weakly vented, is very ſinfully defended; whilſt the excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt him, do by his own expreſſion appear cogent, he ſhould meekly yield to the conviction, and bear the ſhame, which ſtrugling to avoid, he hath added folly, vanity, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry, and falſe quotations and ſuggeſtions; the effects of a ſtubborn mind, unwilling to give God Glory, and fallen under the curſe of calling <hi>good evil, and evil good;</hi> and more immediately ſubjected himſelf to Gods wrath, by <hi>hardning his neck againſt reproof,</hi> and labouring not onely to vindicate and defend his own apoſtacy, but by his wordy influence to incourage the prophane; and as far as in him lyeth, plunge both <hi>King and Kingdome,</hi> under the guilt of <hi>perjury, or breach of Covenant,</hi> the quarrel of which, the God of jealouſie hath avenged, as to the <hi>civil part,</hi> and will undoubtedly avenge as to the religious part, againſt the violent rejections, or fraudulent evaſions of the ſons of men.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="by_the_same_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:119354:53"/>
            <head>Books written by Mr. <hi>Zach. Crofton.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Foelix ſcelus, Querela piorum, &amp; Auſcultato Divina;</hi> Or, Proſpering prophaneneſs provoking Holy conference, and Gods attention, in which you have the happy eſtate of the wicked, the holy exerciſe of the godly, the hazard and event of both. Plainly propounded in ſundry Sermons Preached at <hi>Botolphs Algate London:</hi> and after contracted in two Sermons Preached in <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Weſt-cheſter, July</hi> 17. 1659.</p>
            <p>Catechizing Gods Ordinance: Or a ſhort Treatiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that Antient Approved Soul-edifying Singularly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary exerciſe of Catechiſing.</p>
            <p>The peoples need of a living Paſtor: Aſſerted and explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a Sermon Preached <hi>Novemb.</hi> 4. 1656. At the ſad and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Funeral of that late learned, pious and eminent hopeful Miniſter of the Goſpel, <hi>Mr. John Froſt,</hi> Batchelor in Divinity, late fellow of St. <hi>Johns</hi> Colledg in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and Paſtor of St. <hi>Olaves Hart-ſtreet London.</hi> Together with a Narrative of his Life and Death.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Or St. <hi>Peters</hi> bonds abide, being an anſwer to Dr. <hi>Gaudens</hi> ſence and ſolution of the Solemn League and Covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The faſtening of St. <hi>Peter's</hi> Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, by ſeven kinds or propoſitions.</p>
            <p>A ſerious review of Presbyters reordination by Biſhops, in a Letter Written unto a Miniſter in <hi>Warwickſheir,</hi> reſolving this caſe of conſcience, Whether a Miniſter ordained by Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters may with a good conſcience be reordained by a Biſhop, Presbyter and Deacon, ſo that they will declare their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination to be meerly accumalative and the man ſhall not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce his Ordination by it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bethſhemeſh</hi> clouded, or ſome Animadveriſions on the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binical Talmud of Rabbi <hi>John Rogers,</hi> of <hi>Thomas-Apoſtles Lond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Altar-Worſhip, Or bowing to the Communion Table, conſidered, as to the novelty, vanity, iniquity, malignity, charged upon it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fraterna Correptio:</hi> Or the Saints zeal againſt ſinful Altars: delivered in a Sermon Preached on a day of Humiliation for the <hi>Errors, Hereſies and Schiſms</hi> of our times and Nations.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
